<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<search>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Logging</title>
    <link href="/2023/10/02/Logging/"/>
    <url>/2023/10/02/Logging/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="1-Durability–Why-we-need-Logging"><a href="#1-Durability–Why-we-need-Logging" class="headerlink" title="1 Durability–Why we need Logging"></a>1 Durability–Why we need Logging</h2><p>Let’s first consider a NaiveDB,<br>-step 1: Admit one transaction T<br>-step 2: Execute T to completion<br>-step 3: <strong>Atomically</strong> flush T’s writes to disk<br>-step 4: Admit the next transaction</p><p>That’s easy. But what if, at some point, the disk&#x2F;memory&#x2F;CPU&#x2F;server crashed down, or I cut down the power? To avoid bad things happening, we need to make database <strong>Durability</strong>: Once a transaction commits, its effects must be persistent; the DBMS can tolerate systems failures.</p><p><strong>Durability</strong>: The database must recover to a valid state no matter when a crash occurs.</p><ol><li>Committed transactions should persist.</li><li>Uncommitted transactions should roll back.</li></ol><p><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%201.jpg" alt="example"></p><h2 id="2-WAL"><a href="#2-WAL" class="headerlink" title="2 WAL"></a>2 WAL</h2><p>To reach durability, we introduce a protocol, <strong>Write-Ahead Logging(WAL)</strong>: Flush the log record for an update before the corresponding data page gets to disk; Write all log records for a transaction before commits.</p><p>Before making any changes to the actual data or its structures(like a B+ tree), the system first writes those changes to a log. This log is sequentially written, making it fast to append data.</p><p>Why we use it?</p><ol><li><p><strong>Data Integrity and Durability</strong>: In case of a system crash or power failure, any transactions not permanently written to the data files can be recovered and completed using the log. This ensures that the database remains in a consistent state.</p></li><li><p><strong>Backup and Point-in-time Recovery</strong>: If you have a backup of a database and a subsequent WAL, you can restore the database to any point in time covered by the log. This can be useful for recovering from both catastrophic failures and human errors, like unintended data deletions.</p></li></ol><h2 id="3-Buffer-managerment-policies"><a href="#3-Buffer-managerment-policies" class="headerlink" title="3 Buffer managerment policies"></a>3 Buffer managerment policies</h2><h3 id="3-1-Steal"><a href="#3-1-Steal" class="headerlink" title="3.1 Steal?"></a>3.1 Steal?</h3><p><strong>No Steal</strong>: Dirty pages stay in DRAM until the transaction commits.<br><strong>Steal</strong>: Dirty pages can be flushed to disk before the transaction commits.</p><ol><li>Ad: other transactions can use the buffer slot in DRAM</li><li>Challenge: systems crashed after flushing dirty pages but before the transaction commits. &#x3D;&gt; <strong>Dirty data on disk!</strong></li><li>Solution: <strong>UNDO</strong> logging before each update</li></ol><h3 id="3-2-Force"><a href="#3-2-Force" class="headerlink" title="3.2 Force?"></a>3.2 Force?</h3><p><strong>Force</strong>: All dirty pages must be flushed when the transaction commits.<br><strong>No force</strong>: Dirty pages may stay in memory after the transaction commits.</p><ol><li>Ad: reduce #random IO(high!)</li><li>Challenge: system crashes after the transaction commits but before the dirty pages are flushed &#x3D;&gt; <strong>missing updates from committed transactions!</strong></li><li>Solution: <strong>REDO</strong> logging before each update.</li></ol><p>Notice: the reason choose logging, is that flushing logs can be much cheaper than flushing data pages. Log record can be much smaller than a data page; Logging incurs sequential IO; data page updates incur random IO.</p><h3 id="3-3-Policy-How-to-choose"><a href="#3-3-Policy-How-to-choose" class="headerlink" title="3.3 Policy: How to choose?"></a>3.3 Policy: How to choose?</h3><p>Let’s make a table,<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%202.jpg"></p><h4 id="3-3-1-Force-amp-amp-No-Steal"><a href="#3-3-1-Force-amp-amp-No-Steal" class="headerlink" title="3.3.1 Force &amp;&amp; No Steal"></a>3.3.1 Force &amp;&amp; No Steal</h4><p>We start with the easiest one.</p><p>It is the most strict policy. We do not write logs before the transaction is committed and force flushing logs to disk when the transaction is committed.</p><p>When the system crashes, every committed transactions must persist to disk and every uncommitted transactions must not persist on disk. So we do nothing, <strong>NO REDO nor NO UNDO</strong>. (Philip Bernstein, Vassos Hadzilacos, Nathan Goodman, Concurrency Control and Recovery in Database Systems, 1987)</p><h4 id="3-3-2-Force-amp-amp-Steal"><a href="#3-3-2-Force-amp-amp-Steal" class="headerlink" title="3.3.2 Force &amp;&amp; Steal"></a>3.3.2 Force &amp;&amp; Steal</h4><p>We allow system write logs before the transaction is committed, but force flushing logs to disk when the transaction is committed.</p><p>Log <strong>UNDO</strong> record before each update to database; Log <strong>COMMIT</strong> record when a transaction finishes execution. Modified data pages can be written to disk <strong>after the corresponding UNDO record but before the COMMIT record</strong>.</p><p>So we do <strong>UNDO</strong> only (NVM-based database), <strong>UNDO</strong> uncommitted transactions.</p><h4 id="3-3-3-No-Force-amp-amp-No-Steal"><a href="#3-3-3-No-Force-amp-amp-No-Steal" class="headerlink" title="3.3.3 No Force &amp;&amp; No Steal"></a>3.3.3 No Force &amp;&amp; No Steal</h4><p>We do not allow system write logs to disk before the transaction is committed, but do not force flushing logs to disk when the transaction is committed.</p><p>Log <strong>REDO</strong> record before each update to database. Log <strong>COMMIT</strong> record when a transaction finishes execution. Modified data pages can be written to disk <strong>after COMMIT record is logged</strong>.</p><p>So, we <strong>replay REDO logs</strong> for comitted transactions.</p><h4 id="3-3-4-No-force-amp-amp-Steal"><a href="#3-3-4-No-force-amp-amp-Steal" class="headerlink" title="3.3.4 No force &amp;&amp; Steal"></a>3.3.4 No force &amp;&amp; Steal</h4><p>We not only allow system write logs to dish before the transaction is committed, but also do not force flushing logs to dish when the transaction is committed. The most flexible!</p><p>Log combined <strong>REDO&#x2F;UNDO</strong> record before each update to database; Log <strong>COMMIT</strong> record when a transaction finishes execution; Modified data pages can be written to disk <strong>any time after the corresponding REDO&#x2F;UNDO records</strong>.</p><p>So, we <strong>UNDO uncommitted</strong> transactions and <strong>REDO</strong> committed transactions.</p><h3 id="3-4-ARIES–A-No-force-amp-amp-Steal-Procotol"><a href="#3-4-ARIES–A-No-force-amp-amp-Steal-Procotol" class="headerlink" title="3.4 ARIES–A No force &amp;&amp; Steal Procotol"></a>3.4 ARIES–A No force &amp;&amp; Steal Procotol</h3><p>ACM Trans. Database Syst. 1992</p><h4 id="3-4-1-Baseline-Design"><a href="#3-4-1-Baseline-Design" class="headerlink" title="3.4.1 Baseline Design"></a>3.4.1 Baseline Design</h4><p>Let’s start with an easiest thinking.</p><p>We want to forward scan of entire log: redo all records; keep a table for active transactions. We backward scan of entire log: undo uncommitted transactions. So we introduce data structures like this:</p><p><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%203.jpg" alt="Data Structure"></p><p>LSN here refers to Log Sequence Number, which can consider as a kind of unique ID.</p><ol><li><p>But it is inefficiency in the <strong>REDO</strong> process. Unnecessary to redo all records; Need to redo only records that are not reflected in data pages.</p></li><li><p>It is also inefficiency in the <strong>UNDO</strong> process. Unnecessary to scan the entire log; Need to undo only records of uncommitted transactions.</p></li><li><p>It also lack of checkpointing. Unnecessary to start from the beginning of log; Start with the first log record that is not reflected in data pages.</p></li></ol><p>Let’s optimized one by one.</p><h4 id="3-4-2-Optimize-REDO-process"><a href="#3-4-2-Optimize-REDO-process" class="headerlink" title="3.4.2 Optimize REDO process"></a>3.4.2 Optimize REDO process</h4><ol><li><strong>pageLSN</strong>: LSN of the log record that describes the latest update to the pate.</li><li>in <strong>REDO</strong> scan: Apply REDO only if <code>record.LSN &gt; page.page.LSN</code>.</li><li><strong>Write</strong>: update <code>pageLSN</code> (for the buffered page) for each write.</li></ol><p>The new data structure is like below:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%204.jpg" alt="Data Structure"></p><h4 id="3-4-3-Optimize-UNDO-process"><a href="#3-4-3-Optimize-UNDO-process" class="headerlink" title="3.4.3 Optimize UNDO process"></a>3.4.3 Optimize UNDO process</h4><ol><li><strong><code>prevLSN</code></strong>: preceding log record written by the same transaction.</li><li><strong><code>lastLSN</code></strong>: LSN of the last log record written by the transaction.</li><li><strong>UNDO</strong> scan: Follow <code>lastLSN</code> and <code>prevLSN</code> to undo records.</li><li><strong>REDO</strong> scan: update <code>lastLSN</code> in <code>Transaction Table</code> based on the last update of the transaction.</li></ol><p>The new data structure is like below:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%205.jpg" alt="Data Structure"></p><h4 id="3-4-4-Add-Checkpoint"><a href="#3-4-4-Add-Checkpoint" class="headerlink" title="3.4.4 Add Checkpoint"></a>3.4.4 Add Checkpoint</h4><ol><li><strong><code>pageID</code></strong>: ID of a dirty page</li><li><strong><code>recLSN</code></strong>: LSN of the first log record since when the page is dirty</li><li><strong>Fuzzy Checkpoing</strong>: log DPT and TT async.</li><li><strong>REDO</strong> scan: start from the smallest LSN in DP.</li></ol><h4 id="3-4-5-Compensation-Log-Record-CLR"><a href="#3-4-5-Compensation-Log-Record-CLR" class="headerlink" title="3.4.5 Compensation Log Record(CLR)"></a>3.4.5 Compensation Log Record(CLR)</h4><p>The action of applying <strong>UNDO</strong> leads to a CLR.</p><ol><li>In undo scan, do not reapply <strong>UNDO</strong> if CLR exists. Do not <strong>UNDO</strong> a <strong>UNDO</strong> operation</li><li><code>UndoNxtLSN</code>: LSN of the next record to be processed during the undo scan.</li></ol><p><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%206.jpg" alt="CLR"></p><p>This is because:</p><ol><li><strong>Avoid Infinite Loops</strong>: If the system kept reapplying the UNDO for a CLR, it would enter into an infinite loop. This is because when you undo a CLR, you’d create another CLR to compensate for that, and then undo that CLR, creating yet another CLR, and so on.</li><li><strong>CLR Represents an Undo</strong>: The very existence of a CLR for a log record indicates that the effects of the original log record have already been undone. Reapplying the UNDO would be redundant and unnecessary.</li><li><strong>Consistency &amp; Idempotence</strong>: One of the primary design goals of recovery algorithms like ARIES is to ensure that the recovery actions are idempotent. That means you can apply them multiple times and still achieve the same state. If you were to reapply the UNDO for a CLR, this idempotent property could be violated.</li></ol><p>The new data structure is like below:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%207.jpg" alt="Data Structure"></p><h4 id="3-4-6-ARIES-Big-Picture"><a href="#3-4-6-ARIES-Big-Picture" class="headerlink" title="3.4.6 ARIES-Big Picture"></a>3.4.6 ARIES-Big Picture</h4><p>Start from the last complete checkpoint.</p><ol><li><strong>Analysis phase</strong>:<br>1.1 rebuild transaction table (for undo phase): for each log record, if <code>update</code> or <code>CLR</code>, insert to transaction table if not exists; if <code>end</code>, delete from transaction table<br>1.2 rebuild dirty page table (for redo phase): if <code>update</code> or <code>CLR</code>, insert to dirty page table if not exists</li><li><strong>REDO phase</strong>:<br>redo transactions whose effects may not be persistent before the crash<br>2.1 From log record containing <strong>smallest <code>RecLSN</code></strong> in the dirty page table. Before this LSN, all redo records have been reflected in data pages on disk.<br>2.2 Can <strong>skip</strong> a redo record for the following cases where the corresponding page has already been flushed before the crash. The page is not in DPT; The page is in DPT but <code>redo_record.LSN</code> &lt; <code>DPT[page].recLSN</code>; After fetching the data page, <code>redo_record.LSN</code> &lt;&#x3D; <code>page.page_LSN</code>.</li><li><strong>UNDO phase</strong>:<br>undo transactions that did not commit before the crash<br>3.1 Choose largest <code>LastLSN</code> among transactions in the TT.<br>3.2 If the log record is an <code>update</code>, <strong>UNDO</strong> the update, write a <code>CLR</code>, add <code>record.prevLSN</code> to TT.<br>3.3 if the log record is an <code>CLR</code>, add <code>CLR.UndoNxtLsn</code> to TT.<br>3.4 If <code>prevLSN</code> and <code>UndoNxtLSN</code> are <code>NULL</code>, remove the transaction from TT.</li></ol><p><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%208.jpg"></p><h4 id="3-4-7-Example"><a href="#3-4-7-Example" class="headerlink" title="3.4.7 Example"></a>3.4.7 Example</h4><p>Let’s consider a situation<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%209.jpg"></p><p><strong>Analysis phase</strong> start at checkpoint<br>step 1:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2010.jpg"><br>step 2:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2011.jpg"><br>Step 3:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2012.jpg"><br>Step 4:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2013.jpg"><br>Step 5:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2014.jpg"></p><p><strong>REDO phase</strong> with given data pages<br>Step 1:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2015.jpg"><br>Step 2:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2016.jpg"><br>Step 3:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2017.jpg"><br>Step 4:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2018.jpg"><br>Step 5:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2019.jpg"></p><p><strong>UNDO phase</strong><br>Step 1:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2020.jpg"><br>Step 2:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2021.jpg"><br>Step 3:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2022.jpg"><br>Step 4:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2023.jpg"><br>Step 5:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2024.jpg"><br>Step 6:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2025.jpg"></p><h2 id="4-Acknowledgement"><a href="#4-Acknowledgement" class="headerlink" title="4 Acknowledgement"></a>4 Acknowledgement</h2><p>Thanks UW-Madison COMP 564 Prof Xiangyao Yu!</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Techniques</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>database</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Mid-Autumn</title>
    <link href="/2023/10/01/life_experience_3/"/>
    <url>/2023/10/01/life_experience_3/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Gossip</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>emo</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>COMP 571</title>
    <link href="/2023/09/30/COMP571/"/>
    <url>/2023/09/30/COMP571/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="Programming"><a href="#Programming" class="headerlink" title="Programming"></a><strong>Programming</strong></h2><h3 id="Week-1"><a href="#Week-1" class="headerlink" title="Week 1"></a>Week 1</h3><h4 id="HTML"><a href="#HTML" class="headerlink" title="HTML"></a>HTML</h4><ol><li>hyper-text markup language, defines the structure of the web, make up of a series of “elements” defined by “tags”. Each element can have a unique <code>id</code> attribute, used for CSS and JS</li><li>Document Object Model(DOM), HTML is a tree, while each element is a node.</li><li><code>html</code>: encapsulate entire html document<br><code>head</code>: include metadata, such as CSS and JS scripts<br><code>body</code>: main HTML contentw<br><code>h1</code>: headers<br><code>p</code>: paragraph text<br><code>strong</code>, <code>em</code>: connotation<br><code>a</code>: anchor text(links)<br><code>img</code>: images (with <code>alt</code> attribute)<br><code>br</code>: linebreak<br><code>ul</code>, <code>ol</code>, <code>li</code>: lists<br><code>table</code>, <code>threads</code>, <code>tbody</code>, <code>tr</code>, <code>th</code>, <code>td</code>: tables<br><code>div</code>: divisions(sections)<br><code>form</code>: encapsulates many inputs<br><code>label</code>: label an input (include <code>for</code> attribute)<br><code>input</code>: user input<br><code>button</code>: buttons</li></ol><h4 id="CSS"><a href="#CSS" class="headerlink" title="CSS"></a>CSS</h4><ol><li>Cascading Sytle Sheets, defines the styles to be used, uses a cascading hierachy of selectors and decoration boxes consisting of key-value pairs</li><li><code> </code> applies to all HTML elements with a particular tag, <code>#</code> to particular id, <code>.</code> applies to particular class</li><li><img src="../img/COMP571/COMP 571 1.jpg" width="400" height="150"></li><li>CSS Inline:<br><img src="/../img/COMP571/COMP%20571%202.jpg"><br>CSS Internal:<img src="../img/COMP571/COMP 571 3.jpg" width="200" height="200">CSS External:Same as internal but with styling in an external file.</li><li>Not all browsers support all CSS.</li></ol><h4 id="JavaScript"><a href="#JavaScript" class="headerlink" title="JavaScript"></a>JavaScript</h4><ol><li>A dynamic, loosely-typed language. The data type is inferred from the declaration and can be changed.</li><li>Variables are containers that hold data. Types: numbers, string, boolean, null, undefined, symbol, object(only stored in heap).</li><li>Variables can be declared with <code>var</code>, <code>let</code>, <code>const</code>.<br><img src="/../img/COMP571/COMP%20571%204.jpg"></li><li>Query the data type at runtime using <code>typeof</code>.</li><li>Conditionals:<br>5.1 <code>if</code>, <code>else if</code>, <code>else</code><br>5.2 <code>switch</code> statements<br>5.3 <code>evalExpr ? trueExpr : falseExpr</code></li><li>Any value that is not <code>false</code>, <code>undefined</code>, <code>null</code>, <code>0</code>, <code>NaN</code>, <code>&quot;&quot;</code> returns <code>true</code>.</li><li>Comaparison:<br><img src="/../img/COMP571/COMP%20571%205.jpg"><br>Weak comparison do not care about type, <code>&quot;5&quot; == 5</code> returns <code>true</code></li><li>Objects: unordered collections of data defined using key-value pairs. (attributes&#x2F;properties).<br><code>object.attribute</code> or <code>object[&quot;attribute&quot;]</code></li><li>Arrays: a varaible that contains multiple elements, do not have to be the same type</li><li>Loops:</li></ol><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">for</span> (<span class="hljs-keyword">let</span> i = <span class="hljs-number">0</span>; i &lt; <span class="hljs-number">10</span>; i++) &#123;&#125;<br><span class="hljs-keyword">for</span> (<span class="hljs-keyword">let</span> attr <span class="hljs-keyword">in</span> course) &#123;<br>&#125;<br><span class="hljs-keyword">for</span> (<span class="hljs-keyword">let</span> item <span class="hljs-keyword">of</span> arr) &#123;<br>&#125;<br><span class="hljs-keyword">while</span> (cond) &#123;&#125;<br><span class="hljs-keyword">do</span> &#123;&#125; <span class="hljs-keyword">while</span> (cond);<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><ol start="11"><li>Functions:</li></ol><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">(<span class="hljs-keyword">const</span>) <span class="hljs-keyword">function</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">var</span>(<span class="hljs-params">para</span>) &#123; <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> result; &#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><h4 id="DOM"><a href="#DOM" class="headerlink" title="DOM"></a>DOM</h4><ol><li><p>HTML is a tree, where each element is a node. We use JS to manipulate this tree.</p></li><li><p>Use <code>document</code> to reference the DOM</p><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">let</span> title = <span class="hljs-variable language_">document</span>.<span class="hljs-title function_">getElementById</span>(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;articleTitle&quot;</span>);<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li><p>Add an action for some elememt when some event happens:</p><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">title.<span class="hljs-property">textContent</span> = <span class="hljs-string">&quot;My Website!&quot;</span>;<br>loginBtn.<span class="hljs-title function_">addEventListener</span>(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;click&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-function">() =&gt;</span> &#123;<br>  <span class="hljs-title function_">alert</span>(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;You are advancing to the next part..&quot;</span>);<br>&#125;);<br><span class="hljs-keyword">for</span> (<span class="hljs-keyword">let</span> callout <span class="hljs-keyword">of</span> callouts) &#123;<br>  callout.<span class="hljs-property">style</span>.<span class="hljs-property">color</span> = <span class="hljs-string">&quot;red&quot;</span>;<br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li></ol><h3 id="Week-2"><a href="#Week-2" class="headerlink" title="Week 2"></a>Week 2</h3><h4 id="JSON"><a href="#JSON" class="headerlink" title="JSON"></a>JSON</h4><ol><li>A JS Object is executable code, JSON is a language-agnostic respresentation of an object. Cannot write comments in JSON.</li><li><code>JSON.parse</code> JSON String-&gt;JS object, <code>JSON.stringify</code> JS Object-&gt;JSON String</li><li>HTTP Request for JSON: <code>sync</code> and <code>async</code>(recommended). <code>XMLHttpRequest</code> (old) and <code>fetch</code> (new).</li><li>fetch():<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-title function_">fetch</span>(url)<br>  .<span class="hljs-title function_">then</span>(<span class="hljs-function">(<span class="hljs-params">response</span>) =&gt;</span> response.<span class="hljs-title function_">json</span>())<br>  .<span class="hljs-title function_">then</span>(<span class="hljs-function">(<span class="hljs-params">data</span>) =&gt;</span> &#123;&#125;)<br>  .<span class="hljs-title function_">catch</span>(<span class="hljs-function">(<span class="hljs-params">error</span>) =&gt;</span> <span class="hljs-variable language_">console</span>.<span class="hljs-title function_">error</span>(error));<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure>happens async,<br><code>then</code> and <code>catch</code> take a callback function as an argument. A callback function is passed into another function as an argument, which is then invoked inside the outer function to complete a routine or action.</li></ol><h4 id="Write-clean-code"><a href="#Write-clean-code" class="headerlink" title="Write clean code"></a>Write clean code</h4><ol><li>imperative: <code>for (let obj of arr) &#123;&#125;</code><br>declarative: <code>arr.forEach((obj) =&gt; &#123;&#125;)</code><br>prefer declarative programming,<br><code>forEach</code>, <code>map</code>, <code>filter</code>: used on arrays, take a call back as an argument<br><code>slice</code>, <code>concat</code>, <code>some</code>, <code>every</code>, <code>reduce</code></li><li><code>Object.keys(obj)</code> get the keys of an object</li><li><code>setInterval(callback, interval)</code> perform a callback function every interval milliseconds<br><code>setTimeoue(callback, timeout)</code> perform a callback function in timeout milliseconds</li><li><code>slice(begI, endI)</code> returns a shallow copy with an optional beginning and ending index</li><li><code>concat</code> joins two arrays together</li><li><code>some(cb)</code> returns <code>true</code> if the callback returns true for some element of the array, <code>false</code> otherwise.<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">[<span class="hljs-string">&quot;sam&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-string">&quot;jacob&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-string">&quot;jess&quot;</span>].<span class="hljs-title function_">some</span>(<span class="hljs-function">(<span class="hljs-params">p</span>) =&gt;</span> p === <span class="hljs-string">&quot;jess&quot;</span>); <span class="hljs-comment">//true!</span><br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li><code>every(cb)</code> returns <code>true</code> if the callback returns true for every element of the array, <code>false</code> otherwise.<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">[<span class="hljs-string">&quot;sam&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-string">&quot;jacob&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-string">&quot;jess&quot;</span>].<span class="hljs-title function_">every</span>(<span class="hljs-function">(<span class="hljs-params">p</span>) =&gt;</span> p === <span class="hljs-string">&quot;jess&quot;</span>); <span class="hljs-comment">// false!</span><br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li><code>reduce(cb, start)</code>: takes a 2-para callback (previous and current values) and s starting value<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">[<span class="hljs-number">2</span>, <span class="hljs-number">4</span>, -<span class="hljs-number">1.1</span>, <span class="hljs-number">7.2</span>].<span class="hljs-title function_">reduce</span>(<span class="hljs-function">(<span class="hljs-params">prev, curr</span>) =&gt;</span> prev + curr, <span class="hljs-number">1.2</span>); <span class="hljs-comment">//13.3</span><br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li><code>...</code> Spread Operator <code>const newCats = [...cats, &quot;darcy&quot;]</code>, also with objects, are both shallow copies.<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> fruits = [<span class="hljs-string">&quot;apple&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-string">&quot;banana&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-string">&quot;apple&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-string">&quot;banana&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-string">&quot;apple&quot;</span>];<br><span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> countObj = fruits.<span class="hljs-title function_">reduce</span>(<span class="hljs-function">(<span class="hljs-params">acc, curr</span>) =&gt;</span> &#123;<br>  <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> &#123;<br>    ...acc,<br>    [curr]: (acc[curr] || <span class="hljs-number">0</span>) + <span class="hljs-number">1</span>,<br>  &#125;;<br>&#125;, &#123;&#125;);<br><span class="hljs-variable language_">console</span>.<span class="hljs-title function_">log</span>(countObj); <span class="hljs-comment">//Output: &#123;apple: 3, banana: 2, orange: 1&#125;</span><br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li><code>??</code> Null Coalescing Operator: if left-hand is null or undefined, use right-hand.<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> <span class="hljs-variable constant_">IS_ENABLED</span> = env.<span class="hljs-property">IS_ENABLED</span> ?? <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li></ol><h4 id="Copy"><a href="#Copy" class="headerlink" title="Copy"></a>Copy</h4><ol><li>Why: using spread operator, copying a template object, passing an object to function where we do not want the object to be modified, data safety</li><li>Reference Copy: <code>let A = B</code>, change A will also change B, same mem area, any changes made through <code>a</code> will also reflect in <code>b</code>.</li><li>Shallow Copy: <code>let A = &#123;...B&#125;</code>, creates a new object, but just copies refs to those inner object, changes to inner objects in a shallow copy can affect the original, and vice versa.</li><li>Deep copy, through <code>JSON.parse()</code>, totally seperate mem.</li></ol><h4 id="Bootstrap"><a href="#Bootstrap" class="headerlink" title="Bootstrap"></a>Bootstrap</h4><ol><li>Layouts: Containers are the most basic element of layouts<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">&lt;div <span class="hljs-keyword">class</span> = <span class="hljs-string">&quot;container&gt;</span><br><span class="hljs-string">...</span><br><span class="hljs-string">&lt;/div&gt;</span><br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure>containers will contain rows and columns to form a grid<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">&lt;div <span class="hljs-keyword">class</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;container&quot;</span>&gt;<br>  <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">div</span> <span class="hljs-attr">class</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;row&quot;</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">    <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">div</span> <span class="hljs-attr">class</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;col-*&quot;</span>&gt;</span><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">div</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">  <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">div</span>&gt;</span></span><br>&lt;/div&gt;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li>Responsive Design: adapts content to a variety of devices and screen sizes.<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">&lt;div <span class="hljs-keyword">class</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;col-12 col-sm-6 col-md-4&quot;</span>&gt;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li>Content: includes basic HTML elements, typography, code, images, tables, figures<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">&lt;img src=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;...&quot;</span> <span class="hljs-keyword">class</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;img-fluid&quot;</span>&gt;<br>&lt;table class=&quot;table&quot;&gt;<br>   &lt;thead class=&quot;thead-dark&quot;&gt;<br>      &lt;tr&gt;<br>      ...<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li>Components: include all other visual&#x2F;interactive elements that make up the design, buttons, forms, navbar, tooltips, etc.</li><li>Utilities: not elements themselves, but modify&#x2F;control other elements</li></ol><h3 id="Week-3"><a href="#Week-3" class="headerlink" title="Week 3"></a>Week 3</h3><h4 id="React"><a href="#React" class="headerlink" title="React"></a>React</h4><ol><li>React: also called ReactJS, a JS library for building user interfaces</li><li>Why use?<br>2.1 <code>innerHTML</code> is bad(XSS injection attack)<br>2.2 efficient DOM updating: no longer access elements via <code>document.</code>, which will friendly in interactive pages<br>2.3 declarative programming: every component is a function</li><li>Component: every thing is a component, a function, inheriting <code>props</code> and maintaining an internal <code>state</code>. Re-render when its <code>props</code> and <code>state</code> changes, or its parent re-renders. The <code>return</code> is what is displayed for a component.</li></ol><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">function</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">App</span>(<span class="hljs-params"></span>) &#123;<br>   <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> (<br>      &lt;div&gt;<br>         <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Welcome</span> <span class="hljs-attr">person</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#x27;Charlie&#x27;</span>&gt;</span><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">Welcome</span>&gt;</span></span><br>   );<br>&#125;<br><span class="hljs-keyword">function</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">Welcome</span>(<span class="hljs-params">props</span>) &#123;<br>   <span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> [name, setName] = <span class="hljs-title function_">useState</span>(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;asd&quot;</span>)<br>   <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">h1</span>&gt;</span>Welcome, &#123;props.person&#125;<span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">h1</span>&gt;</span></span><br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><ol start="4"><li><code>useState</code> Hook: used to maintain state. Takes an initial value as an argument. Returns a pair of the read-only state value and a mutator function. Always use the mutator function to modify state. Mutator happens asynchronously, use <code>useEffect</code>.</li><li><code>useEffect</code> Hook: used to perform an action on component load or state chagne. Takes a callback function and an array of state dependencies as arguments. Listen for changes!<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-title function_">useEffect</span>(<span class="hljs-function">() =&gt;</span> &#123;<br>  <span class="hljs-title function_">alert</span>(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;You changed your name to &quot;</span> + name);<br>&#125;, [name]);<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li></ol><h3 id="Week-4"><a href="#Week-4" class="headerlink" title="Week 4"></a>Week 4</h3><ol><li>Set State:<br><code>SetNum(4)</code>: overwriting the value<br><code>setNum(n =&gt; n+1)</code>: update the existing value</li><li>React will keep old state when hot reloading, choose overwrite to avoid duplicates upon saving solution.<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">function</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">AllHurricanes</span>(<span class="hljs-params"></span>) &#123;<br>  <span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> [hurricanes, setHurricanes] = <span class="hljs-title function_">useState</span>([]);<br>  <span class="hljs-title function_">useEffect</span>(<span class="hljs-function">() =&gt;</span> &#123;<br>    <span class="hljs-title function_">fetch</span>(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;http://...&quot;</span>)<br>      .<span class="hljs-title function_">then</span>((res = res.<span class="hljs-title function_">json</span>()))<br>      .<span class="hljs-title function_">then</span>(<span class="hljs-function">(<span class="hljs-params">data</span>) =&gt;</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">setHurricanes</span>(data));<br>  &#125;);<br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li>Displaying Arrays of Data<br>3.1 <code>map</code> each piece of data to JSX<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br><span class="line">11</span><br><span class="line">12</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> (<br>  <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">div</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">    <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">h1</span>&gt;</span>Hurricane Finder<span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">h1</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">    &#123;hurricanes.map((hurr) =&gt; (</span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Hurricane</span></span></span><br><span class="hljs-tag"><span class="language-xml">        <span class="hljs-attr">name</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;hurr.name&#125;</span></span></span><br><span class="hljs-tag"><span class="language-xml">        <span class="hljs-attr">category</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;hurr.category&#125;</span></span></span><br><span class="hljs-tag"><span class="language-xml">        <span class="hljs-attr">start_date</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;hurr.start_date&#125;</span> // &lt;<span class="hljs-attr">Hurricane</span> &#123;<span class="hljs-attr">...hurr</span>&#125;/&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">      /&gt;</span><br><span class="language-xml">    ))&#125;</span><br><span class="language-xml">  <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">div</span>&gt;</span></span><br>);<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure>3.2 <code>key</code>: speed up rendering, always use a unique key for the parent-most element rendered in a list, needs to be unique among siblings, should usually not be the index of the item<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> (<br>  <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">div</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">    <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">h1</span>&gt;</span>Hurricane Finder<span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">h1</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">    &#123;hurricanes.map((hurr) =&gt; (</span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Hurricane</span> <span class="hljs-attr">key</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;hurr.id&#125;</span> &#123;<span class="hljs-attr">...hurr</span>&#125; /&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">    ))&#125;</span><br><span class="language-xml">  <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">div</span>&gt;</span></span><br>);<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li>Responsive Design<br>4.1 use react-bootstrap<br>4.2 use <code>Container</code>, <code>Row</code>, <code>Col</code> components, <code>xs</code>, <code>sm</code>, <code>md</code>, <code>lg</code>, <code>xl</code>, <code>xxl</code> are props<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">&lt;<span class="hljs-title class_">Container</span>&gt;<br>  <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Row</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">    <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Col</span> <span class="hljs-attr">xs</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;12&#125;</span> <span class="hljs-attr">md</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;6&#125;</span> <span class="hljs-attr">lg</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;3&#125;</span>&gt;</span><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">Col</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">  <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">Row</span>&gt;</span></span><br>&lt;/<span class="hljs-title class_">Container</span>&gt;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li>Pagination: also available in <code>react-bootstrap</code>, handling large sums of data, use a state variable to track which page is active, use with <code>slice</code> to only show the item on the current page.</li><li>Text input: HTML <code>input</code> tag, or <code>Form.Control</code> in React-bootstrap<br>6.1 in a controlled way useing its <code>value</code> and tracking <code>onChange</code> events<br>6.2 in an uncontrolled manner using <code>useRef</code></li></ol><h3 id="Week-5"><a href="#Week-5" class="headerlink" title="Week 5"></a>Week 5</h3><ol><li>React Fragment:<br>A JSX component can only return one thing. Sometimes we use <code>&lt;&gt;&lt;/&gt;</code> instead of <code>&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</code>, which is a React Fragment, a virtual separator not represented in the real DOM</li></ol><h4 id="State-Management"><a href="#State-Management" class="headerlink" title="State Management"></a>State Management</h4><p>How do we talk back to our parent? How do siblings talk to each other?</p><ol><li>Passing Callbacks</li><li><code>useContext</code>: a useful hook for managing state across web apps with large component hierarchies.<br>2.1 Create and export a context<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> <span class="hljs-title class_">MydataContext</span> = <span class="hljs-title function_">createContext</span>([]);<br><span class="hljs-keyword">export</span> <span class="hljs-keyword">default</span> <span class="hljs-title class_">MyDataContext</span>;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure>2.2 Provide the context with some value<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">function</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">ParentComponent</span>(<span class="hljs-params"></span>) &#123;<br>   <span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> [data, setData] = <span class="hljs-title function_">useState</span>([<span class="hljs-string">&quot;...&quot;</span>, ...]);<br>   <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> (<br>      <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">MyDataContext.Provider</span> <span class="hljs-attr">value</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;data&#125;</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">         <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">SomeChildComponent</span> /&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">         <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">SomeOtherChildComponent</span> /&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">MyDataContext.Provider</span>&gt;</span></span><br>   )<br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure>2.3 Use the context in a child component<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">function</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">SomeChildComponent</span>(<span class="hljs-params"></span>) &#123;<br>   <span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> data = <span class="hljs-title function_">useContext</span>(<span class="hljs-title class_">MyDataContext</span>);<br>   <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> (...);<br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li>Cookies, Session, Local: these exist in browser, persist even after a page refesh<br><img src="/../img/COMP571/cookies%201.png"><br><img src="/../img/COMP571/cookies%202.png"><br><img src="/../img/COMP571/cookies%203.png"></li><li><code>sessionStorage</code> &amp; <code>localStorage</code>:<br>4.1 only store strings, Use <code>JSON.parse</code> and <code>JSON.stringify</code><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-variable language_">sessionStorage</span>.<span class="hljs-title function_">setItem</span>(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;nums&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-title class_">JSON</span>.<span class="hljs-title function_">stringify</span>([<span class="hljs-number">2</span>, <span class="hljs-number">6</span>, <span class="hljs-number">19</span>]));<br><span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> storedNums = <span class="hljs-title class_">JSON</span>.<span class="hljs-title function_">parse</span>(<span class="hljs-variable language_">sessionStorage</span>.<span class="hljs-title function_">getItem</span>(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;nums&quot;</span>));<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li>Third Party Libraries: Redux, Recoil, MobX, XState</li></ol><p>Persist long-term? Server-side storage with <code>PUT</code>, <code>POST</code>, <code>DELETE</code></p><h4 id="Navigation-w-x2F-React-Router"><a href="#Navigation-w-x2F-React-Router" class="headerlink" title="Navigation w&#x2F; React Router"></a>Navigation w&#x2F; React Router</h4><ol><li><p>Types of Routers:<br>1.1 <code>BrowserRouter</code>: typically<br>1.2 <code>MemoryRouter</code>: same as <code>BrowserRouter</code>, but the path is hidden from the browser in memory<br>1.3 <code>HashRouter</code>: support for older browsers<br>1.4 <code>StaticRouter</code>: used for server-side rendering<br>1.5 <code>NativeRouter</code>: not! use <code>react-navigation</code> instread!</p></li><li><p>Routing: using a <code>Router</code>, <code>Routes</code>, and <code>Route</code>!</p><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">&lt;<span class="hljs-title class_">BrowserRouter</span>&gt;<br>  <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Routes</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">    <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Route</span> <span class="hljs-attr">path</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;/&quot;</span> <span class="hljs-attr">element</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;</span>&lt;<span class="hljs-attr">Layout</span> /&gt;</span>&#125;&gt;</span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Route</span> <span class="hljs-attr">index</span> <span class="hljs-attr">element</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;</span>&lt;<span class="hljs-attr">Home</span> /&gt;</span>&#125; /&gt;</span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Route</span> <span class="hljs-attr">path</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;about-us&quot;</span> <span class="hljs-attr">element</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;</span>&lt;<span class="hljs-attr">AboutUs</span> /&gt;</span>&#125; /&gt;</span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Route</span> <span class="hljs-attr">path</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;other-info&quot;</span> <span class="hljs-attr">element</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;</span>&lt;<span class="hljs-attr">OtherInfo</span> /&gt;</span>&#125; /&gt;</span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Route</span> <span class="hljs-attr">path</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;*&quot;</span> <span class="hljs-attr">element</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;</span>&lt;<span class="hljs-attr">Home</span> /&gt;</span>&#125; /&gt;</span><br><span class="language-xml">    <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">Route</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">  <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">Routes</span>&gt;</span></span><br>&lt;/<span class="hljs-title class_">BrowserRouter</span>&gt;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li><p>Browser <code>outlet</code>: shows the component returned by the child route</p></li><li><p><code>useNavigate</code>: useful for programmatic navigation</p><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br><span class="line">11</span><br><span class="line">12</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">export</span> <span class="hljs-keyword">default</span> <span class="hljs-keyword">function</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">OtherInfo</span>(<span class="hljs-params"></span>) &#123;<br>  <span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> navigate = <span class="hljs-title function_">useNavigate</span>();<br>  <span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">handleclick</span> = (<span class="hljs-params"></span>) =&gt; &#123;<br>    <span class="hljs-title function_">navigate</span>(<span class="hljs-string">&quot; / home &quot;</span>);<br>  &#125;;<br>  <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> (<br>    <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">div</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">h2</span>&gt;</span>0ther Info!<span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">h2</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Button</span> <span class="hljs-attr">onClick</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;handleclick&#125;</span>&gt;</span>Back to Home<span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">Button</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">    <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">div</span>&gt;</span></span><br>  );<br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>navigation for a <code>BrowserRouter</code> is done via URLs</p><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br><span class="line">11</span><br><span class="line">12</span><br><span class="line">13</span><br><span class="line">14</span><br><span class="line">15</span><br><span class="line">16</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">&lt;&gt;<br>  <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Navbar</span> <span class="hljs-attr">bg</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;dark&quot;</span> <span class="hljs-attr">variant</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;dark &quot;</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">    <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Nav</span> <span class="hljs-attr">className</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;me-auto&quot;</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Nav.Link</span> <span class="hljs-attr">as</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;Link&#125;</span> <span class="hljs-attr">to</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;/ &quot;</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">        Home</span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">Nav.Link</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Nav.Link</span> <span class="hljs-attr">as</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;Link&#125;</span> <span class="hljs-attr">to</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot; / about-us &quot;</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">        About Us</span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">Nav.Link</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Nav.Link</span> <span class="hljs-attr">as</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;Link&#125;</span> <span class="hljs-attr">to</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot; /other-info &quot;</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">        0ther Info</span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">Nav.Link</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">    <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">Nav</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">  <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">Navbar</span>&gt;</span></span><br>  <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Outlet</span> /&gt;</span></span> <span class="hljs-comment">// shows the component returned by the child route</span><br>&lt;/&gt;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li></ol><h3 id="Week-6"><a href="#Week-6" class="headerlink" title="Week 6"></a>Week 6</h3><ol><li><p>CRUD operations:<br><img src="/../img/COMP571/CRUD.png"></p></li><li><p>HTTP request:<br><img src="/../img/COMP571/HTTP%20request.png"></p><figure class="highlight plaintext"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs URL">https://www.example.com/packers/AaronRodgers/stats?all=true&amp;since=2010<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p><code>AaronRodgers</code> is a path parameter<br><code>all</code>, <code>since</code> are query parameters<br>for JSON body, need an additional HTTP header, <code>Content-Type: application/json</code><br><img src="/../img/COMP571/HTTP%20Code%201.png"><br><img src="/../img/COMP571/HTTP%20Code%202.png"></p></li><li><p><code>fetch</code>: POST, PUT, DELETE</p></li><li><p>Handling Text Input: using HTML <code>input</code> tag or the React-Bootstrap <code>Form.Control</code> component.<br>4.1 in a controlled way using its <code>value</code> and tracking <code>onChange</code> events.<br>4.2 in an uncontrolled manner using <code>useRef</code></p><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> inputVal = <span class="hljs-title function_">useRef</span>();<br><span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> (<br>  <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">div</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">    <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">label</span> <span class="hljs-attr">htmlFor</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;myInput&quot;</span>&gt;</span>Type something here!<span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">label</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">    <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">input</span> <span class="hljs-attr">id</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;myInput&quot;</span> <span class="hljs-attr">ref</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;inputVal&#125;</span>&gt;</span><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">input</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">  <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">div</span>&gt;</span></span><br>);<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>The value of a ref can be retrieved via its <code>current</code> property, <code>inputVal,current.value</code>.<br>React generally recommends controlled components. Controlled components can cause many re-renders, however uncontrolled components give you no control over the <code>onChange</code> property.<br>4.3 Best practise: if using react-bootstrap components, be sure each <code>Form.Control</code> has an <code>id</code> associated with the <code>htmlFor</code> of a <code>Form.label</code>.</p></li><li><p>Credentialed Requests: for requests for logging in, must include credentials. Return a session for the user, is typically stored in an http-only cookie, not accessible by JavaScript. Must explictly include credentials to every endpoint affecting authorization.</p><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-title function_">fetch</span>(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;https://example.com/api/submit&quot;</span>, &#123;<br>  <span class="hljs-attr">method</span>: <span class="hljs-string">&quot;POST&quot;</span>,<br>  <span class="hljs-attr">credentials</span>: <span class="hljs-string">&quot;include&quot;</span>,<br>&#125;);<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li><p>Memoization: Storing the result so you can use it next time instead of calculating the same thing again and again<br>6.1 <code>useCallback</code>: to memoize functions</p><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">function</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">MyApp</span>(<span class="hljs-params"></span>) &#123;<br>  <span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">myComplicatedFunction</span> = (<span class="hljs-params"></span>) =&gt; &#123;...&#125;;<br>  <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">   <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">buttom</span> <span class="hljs-attr">onClick</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;myComplicatedFunction&#125;</span>&gt;</span>Click Me<span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">button</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">   <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/&gt;</span></span><br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>We create the function <code>myComplicatedFunction</code> on every render! (Like, if parent render, the children has to render too)</p><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">function</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">MyApp</span>(<span class="hljs-params"></span>) &#123;<br>   <span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> myComplicatedFunction = <span class="hljs-title function_">useCallback</span>(<span class="hljs-function">() =&gt;</span> &#123;...&#125;, []);<br>   <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">   <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">buttom</span> <span class="hljs-attr">onClick</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;myComplicatedFunction&#125;</span>&gt;</span>Click Me<span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">button</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">   <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/&gt;</span></span><br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>Takes a callback function to <code>memorize</code> and an optinal list of dependencies. (when to re-‘memoize’)<br>6.2 <code>useMemo</code>: same as <code>useCallback</code>, except memorizes the value of a callback rather than the callback itself.<br>6.3 <code>memo</code>-ized Components: used for creating purely functional components. Given the same props, the function renders the same output.</p></li></ol><h2 id="Design-Thinking"><a href="#Design-Thinking" class="headerlink" title="Design Thinking"></a>Design Thinking</h2><h3 id="Week-1-1"><a href="#Week-1-1" class="headerlink" title="Week 1"></a>Week 1</h3><h4 id="six-phases-DT"><a href="#six-phases-DT" class="headerlink" title="six phases DT"></a>six phases DT</h4><ol><li><strong>Emphathize</strong>: conduct research to develop an understanding of your users.<br>method: <strong>Think-Aloud</strong><br>1.1 Identify representative users.<br>1.2 Ask users to perform representative tasks.<br>1.3 Observe and record what they say and do, noting obstacles, pain points, and failures<br>Write down notes to board? Adobe XD</li><li><strong>Define</strong>: Combine all your data and derive where your users’ problems exist.<br>gather, analyze, recommend<br>method: <strong>affinity diagramming</strong>, organizing data into clusters based on “affinity”<br>2.1 Start with an initial set of categories<br>2.2 Sort notes into these categories<br>2.3 Add subcategories&#x2F;consolidate as needed<br>2.4 Present each category<br>2.5 Rank categories in severity, combining importance, prevalence, frequency<br><img src="/../img/COMP571/COMP%20571%206.jpg"></li><li><strong>Ideate</strong>: Generate a range of crazy, creative ideas. Both indicidually or collaboratively<br>indea creation -&gt; critiquing<br>3.1 defer judgement, encourage wild ideas, build on the ideas of others, stay focused on the topic, one conversation at a time, be visual, go for quantity<br>3.2 Conceptual design, an abstract characterization of the context, use, or experience with an envisioned design solution that highlights the main premise of the solution<br>3.2 Sketching ideas: a sketach is a quick and rough drawing that gives a general outline of an idea. 画草图<br>more effective than words, quick and inexpensice, disposable, can be plentiful<br>3.3 Storyboarding ideas: a sequence of visual frames that illustrate user interaction with the envisioned system, capturing social, environmental, and technical factors that shape user experience.</li></ol><h3 id="Week-7"><a href="#Week-7" class="headerlink" title="Week 7"></a>Week 7</h3><ol><li>Usability: The effectiveness, efficiency, and satisfaction with which a specified set of users can achieve a specified set of tasks in a particular environment. Build an interactive product is accessible by as many people as possible. Making systems accessible to individuals with diabilities.</li><li>Disability: impairment, activity limitation, participation restrictions.</li><li>Impairment:<br>3.1 Sensory impairment: Involves impairment in one or more senses, such as<br>loss of vision or hearing.<br>3.2 Physical impairment: Involves loss of function to one or more parts of the<br>body, e.g., congenitally or a!er stroke or spinal-cord injury.<br>3.3 Cognitive impairment: ncludes cognitive deficits, such as learning<br>impairment or loss of memory&#x2F;cognitive function due to aging or conditions such as Alzheimer’s disease.</li><li>Common impairment:<br>4.1 visual: Impairments in vision, including low vision, blindness, and color blindness.<br>4.2 motor, mobility: Muscular or skeletal impairments in the hands or arms that affect user input as well as impairments that affect mobility, where users are in a wheelchair or bedridden.<br>4.3 auditory: Deficits that affect hearing at different levels of severity, including deafness.<br>4.4 serzures: Neurological impairments, such as photosensitive epilepsy, that result in sensitivity to light, motion, and flickering on screen, which might<br>trigger seizures.<br>4.5 cognitive, learning: Congenital, developmental, and traumatic<br>(e.g., traumatic brain injury) conditions that result in cognitive or learning challenges.</li><li>Types if impairment: permanent, temporary, situational</li><li>Accessibility: The usability of a product, service, environment, or facility by people with the widest range of capabilities.</li><li>Two way to address accessibility: accessible design, assistive tech.</li><li>Accessible Design:<br>8.1 Medical Model: personal attribute, any restriction or loakc of ability to perform an acticity<br>8.2 Social Model: context dependent, people are disabled by barriers in society, not by their impairment or difference.</li><li>Universal Design: The design of products and environments to be usable by all people, to the greatest extent possible, without the need for adaptation or specialized design.</li><li>UD Principle:<br>10.1 Equitable use: The design is useful and marketable to people with diverse abilities.<br>10.2 Flexibility in use: The design accommodates a wide range of individual preferences and abilities.<br>10.3 Simple and Intuitive use: Use of the design is easy to understand, regardless of the user’s experience, knowledge, language skills, or current concentration level.<br>10.4 Perceptibale information: The design communicates necessary information effectively to the user, regardless of ambient conditions or the user’s sensory abilities.<br>10.5 Tolerance for Error: The design minimizes hazards and the adverse consequences of accidental or unintended actions.<br>10.6 Low Physical Effort: The design can be used efficiently and comfortably and with a minimum of fatigue.<br>10.7 Size and Space for Approach and use: Appropriate size and space is provided for approach, reach, manipulation, and use regardless of user’s body size, posture, or mobility.</li><li>UD Assistive Tech: specialized tools that close accessibility gaps<br>Screen readers, screen magnification, text readers, braille for the web, alternative input devices, head&#x2F;mouth wands&#x2F;pointers, motion&#x2F;eye tracking, single-switch, speech input, alternative &amp; Augmentative communication</li></ol>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Courses</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>course notes</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>COMP 320</title>
    <link href="/2023/09/28/COMP320/"/>
    <url>/2023/09/28/COMP320/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>（我也不知道为什么要做 COMP 320 的 Notes，这感觉就像在我这个年纪学习如何上厕所）</p><h2 id="Repoducibility"><a href="#Repoducibility" class="headerlink" title="Repoducibility"></a>Repoducibility</h2><ol><li>Each process owns address space. (one huge list)</li><li>Multiple lists start at different address in address space; normally, append is faster than pop, since pop need to move all next items forward 4 bytes. (? Really)</li><li>Use ASCII to store strings, use specific ISA to store codes.</li><li>A CPU can only run programs that use instructions it understands, interpreters&#x2F;compiler make it sense to run the same code on different machines.</li><li>OS: allocate and abstract resources</li><li>commits: explicit snapshots&#x2F;checkpoints; explicit commit messages (who, what, when, why)</li><li>Tag “good” commits to create releases.</li><li>git:<br>8.1 HEAD: wherever you currently are (one and only one)<br>8.2 tag: label tied to a specific commit number<br>8.3 branch: label tied to end of chain (moves upon new commits)<br>8.4 detached HEAD: refers to a situation where the HEAD pointer (which usually points to a branch reference) directly points to a specific commit, rather than pointing to the latest commit of a branch. In simpler terms, when you’re working in a normal branch (say, “master” or “main”), the HEAD points to the name of that branch, and that branch name points to the latest commit. Any new commits you make will advance the branch to point to the newer commit, and HEAD follows along because it’s pointing to the branch name.</li><li><code>time.time()</code> returns seconds since 1970</li></ol><h2 id="Performance"><a href="#Performance" class="headerlink" title="Performance"></a>Performance</h2><ol><li>Affect performance<br>1.1: Speed of CPU<br>1.2: Speed of Interpretation<br>1.3: Algorithm<br>1.4: Input size</li><li>Complexity analysis only cares about “big” inputs.<br><img src="/../img/COMP320/COMP320%20Performance%201.jpg"></li><li>A step is any unit of work with boudned execution time. (“bounded” does not mean “fixed”)</li><li>Big O:<br>4.1 Goal: categorize functions by how fast they grow. Do not care about scale. Do not care about small inputs. Care about shape of the curve. Find some multiple of a general function that is an upper bound<br><img src="/../img/COMP320/COMP320%20Performance%202.jpg"><br><img src="/../img/COMP320/COMP320%20Performance%203.jpg"></li><li>O(1): x &#x3D; L[0], x &#x3D; len(L), L.append(x), L.pop(-1)<br>O(N): L.insert(0, x), L.pop(0), x &#x3D; max(L), L2.extend(L1), x &#x3D; sum(L), found &#x3D; X in L</li><li><img src="/../img/COMP320/COMP320%20Performance%204.jpg"></li></ol><h2 id="Object-Oriented-Programming"><a href="#Object-Oriented-Programming" class="headerlink" title="Object Oriented Programming"></a>Object Oriented Programming</h2><ol><li><code>Dog.speak(fido, 5)</code>, not an example of type-based dispatch.</li><li>Special Methods: (implicity)<br>2.1 Not all <code>__some__</code> is special methods<br>2.2 <code>__str__</code>, <code>__repr__</code>, control how an object looks when we print it or see it in <code>Out[N]</code>.<br>2.3 <code>__repr_html__</code>, generate HTML to create more visual representaitons of objects in Jupyter.<br>2.5 <code>__eq__</code>, <code>__lt__</code>, define how &#x3D;&#x3D; behaves for two different objects, sorting(<code>__lt__</code>)<br>2.6 <code>__len__</code>, <code>__getitem__</code>, build our own sequences that we <code>index</code>, <code>slice</code>, and <code>loop</code> over.<br>2.7 <code>__enter__</code>, <code>__exit__</code>, context managers, (like automatically close file)</li><li>Inheritance: method inheritance, method resolution order, overriding methods, constructor, calling overidden methods, abstrace base classes</li><li>Every class in python implicitly inherits from the build-in <code>object</code> class if no other explicitly specified.</li></ol>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Courses</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>course notes</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>ECE 252</title>
    <link href="/2023/09/19/EE252/"/>
    <url>/2023/09/19/EE252/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="Week-1"><a href="#Week-1" class="headerlink" title="Week 1"></a><strong><em><em>Week 1</em></em></strong></h2><h3 id="Universal-Compute"><a href="#Universal-Compute" class="headerlink" title="Universal Compute"></a><strong>Universal Compute</strong></h3><ol><li>Turing Machine: any computable computation can be implemented by some machine</li><li>Universal Turing Machine: A programmable computer is effectively a Universal Turing Machine (minus infinite memory).</li><li>A computer can compute anything that’s possible to compute given enough memory and time.</li><li>Design trade-off: Time, Cost, Power&#x2F;Energy.</li></ol><h3 id="Complexity"><a href="#Complexity" class="headerlink" title="Complexity"></a><strong>Complexity</strong></h3><ol><li>1st transistor -&gt; Bell Labs, 1st IC -&gt; Jack Kilby(MSEE’50), 1st microprocessor -&gt; Intel</li><li>Moore’s Law: number of transistors on a microchip doubles approximately every two years(24 month). -&gt; Cost halves every two years.</li></ol><h3 id="Abstraction"><a href="#Abstraction" class="headerlink" title="Abstraction"></a><strong>Abstraction</strong></h3><ol><li>Use abstraction to manage complexity.</li><li>The ISA lies at the software&#x2F;hardware boundary.</li><li>Problem Statement –Software Design–&gt; Algorithm –Programming–&gt; Program –Compilation–&gt; ISA –Processor Design–&gt; Microarchitecture –Logic&#x2F;Circuit Design–&gt; Logic Circuits –Implement&amp;Fabricate–&gt; Devices</li></ol><h3 id="Electral-Infomation"><a href="#Electral-Infomation" class="headerlink" title="Electral Infomation"></a><strong>Electral Infomation</strong></h3><ol><li>Analog: continuous range of values</li><li>Digital: discrete set of values (almost all eletronic device)</li><li>In reality, the voltage levels are actually ranges of voltages.</li><li>Voltage &#x3D; Current * Resistance</li><li>Any data processed by a digital computer is represented by sequences of 1s and 0s</li></ol><h2 id="Week-2"><a href="#Week-2" class="headerlink" title="Week 2"></a><strong><em>Week 2</em></strong></h2><h3 id="Number-representation"><a href="#Number-representation" class="headerlink" title="Number representation"></a><strong>Number representation</strong></h3><ol><li>demical-10, Binary-2, Octal-8, Hexademical-16</li><li>least-significant, right most; most-significant, left-most</li><li>$D_{N-1}\cdots D_{1}D_{0}&#x3D;D_{N-1}*r^{N-1} + \cdots + D_{1}<em>r^1 + D_0</em>r^0$</li><li>Each position represents a power of base; Digital value says how many of that power of base.</li><li>A value is a particular quantity, a number is a way to represent a value. Same “number”, different value.</li></ol><h3 id="Base-conversion"><a href="#Base-conversion" class="headerlink" title="Base conversion"></a><strong>Base conversion</strong></h3><ol><li>Binary &lt;-&gt; Hex: directly substitute a hex digit for a 4-bit binary number.</li><li>Binary &lt;-&gt; Octal: directly substitute a octual digit for a 3-bit binary number.</li><li>Octal &lt;-&gt; Hex: use binary as an intermediate form.</li></ol><h3 id="Arithmetic"><a href="#Arithmetic" class="headerlink" title="Arithmetic"></a><strong>Arithmetic</strong></h3><ol><li>Substraction using borrowing: If necessary, bowrrow the base’s value from one position higher</li><li>Multiple by power of base, shifts number to the left. Divide by power of base, shifts numbers to the right.</li></ol><h3 id="Signed-Numbers"><a href="#Signed-Numbers" class="headerlink" title="Signed Numbers"></a><strong>Signed Numbers</strong></h3><ol><li>Signed-Magnitude: The most significant bit is the sign, the remaining bits are the numbers magnitude.</li><li>2’s Complement representation: positive numbers start with 0, negative numbers start with 1 ($-2^N$).</li><li>Fast Negation: complement each bit and the add 1.</li><li>Addition: works the way it does for unsigned binary number except the carry-out is not meaningful.</li><li>Substraction: add the negation of the value we wish to subtract</li><li>Operand&#x2F;Result bitwidths match: operands and results must have the same number of bits for the math to work correctly.</li></ol><h3 id="Sign-Extention"><a href="#Sign-Extention" class="headerlink" title="Sign Extention"></a><strong>Sign Extention</strong></h3><ol><li>Extend 2’s complement number: for positive: zero-extension; for negative: one-extension</li><li>Negative 1 in 2’s complement: $-1\cdots1$</li><li>Unsigned number: $[0, 2^n -1]$, signed number: $[-(2^{n-1}-1), 2^{n-1}-1]$, 2’s-complement number: $[-2^{n-1}, 2^{n-1}-1]$</li><li>Overflow: The result cannot be correctly represented in the required number of bits.</li><li>lf adding two negative 2’s-complement numbers overflows, the sign of the result will appear to be non-negative.</li><li>lf the result of adding two positive 2’s-complement numbers appears to be positive, then the operation did not overflow.</li><li>lf adding two unsigned numbers overflows , the result will appear to be<br>smaller than it should be.</li></ol><h2 id="Week-3"><a href="#Week-3" class="headerlink" title="Week 3"></a><strong><em>Week 3</em></strong></h2><h3 id="Fixed-Float"><a href="#Fixed-Float" class="headerlink" title="Fixed Float"></a><strong>Fixed Float</strong></h3><ol><li>Radix point: separates the integer portion from the fractional portion of the numebr</li><li>when the format defines a “fixed” position for the radix point within the number’s digits</li><li><img src="/../img/EE252/EE252%201.jpg"></li><li>Shifting right by $N$ bits is equivalent to dividing by $2^N$</li><li>location of radix is not visible, not encoded in the number, must told. We never know the meaning of a binary number just by looking at it.</li></ol><h3 id="Floating-Float"><a href="#Floating-Float" class="headerlink" title="Floating Float"></a><strong>Floating Float</strong></h3><ol><li><img src="/../img/EE252/EE252%202.jpg" alt="IEEE 32-bit"></li><li><img src="/../img/EE252/EE252%203.jpg" alt="Comparison"></li><li>Precision: number of significant digits. No need to transform 10.</li></ol><h3 id="ASCII"><a href="#ASCII" class="headerlink" title="ASCII"></a><strong>ASCII</strong></h3><ol><li>7 bits to represent 128 different characters.</li><li>UTF-8, 16, 32</li></ol><h2 id="Week-4"><a href="#Week-4" class="headerlink" title="Week 4"></a><strong><em>Week 4</em></strong></h2><h3 id="Logic-Functions"><a href="#Logic-Functions" class="headerlink" title="Logic Functions"></a><strong>Logic Functions</strong></h3><ol><li>AND: result is true if all operands are true</li><li>OR: result is true if any operand is true</li><li>NOT: result is the opposite of the operand value</li><li><img src="/../img/EE252/EE252%204.png" alt="Symbols"></li><li>XOR: the result of a two-operand OR is true if both operands are true, the odd function</li><li>A bitwise operation computes each bit of an N-bit result based on the value in the correponding position of the N-bit operands.</li></ol><h3 id="Combiational-Logical"><a href="#Combiational-Logical" class="headerlink" title="Combiational Logical"></a><strong>Combiational Logical</strong></h3><ol><li><img src="/../img/EE252/EE252%205.png" alt="Transistors"></li><li><img src="/../img/EE252/EE252%206.png" alt="Logic Gates"></li><li>Waveforms: a waveform is a visual way to represent signal values over time.</li><li>Logic circuits are at a higher level of abstraction. Each transistor acts like a switch.</li><li>NOT gate use 2 transisters.</li></ol><h3 id="Combinational-Blocks"><a href="#Combinational-Blocks" class="headerlink" title="Combinational Blocks"></a><strong>Combinational Blocks</strong></h3><ol><li>Decoder: converts an n-bit input code word into a unique m-bit ouput value, where $m&#x3D;2^n$.</li><li>Exactly one output can be true at any given time.</li><li><img src="/../img/EE252/EE252%207.png" alt="Decoder"></li><li>Multiplexers: based on the select input, choose one of the data inputs to drive the output</li><li><img src="/../img/EE252/EE252%208.png" alt="Muxes"></li><li>Full adder: at every position, determine 2-bit sum of adding each addend’s bit in that position plus a carry-in. A full adder performs addition for single bit position.</li><li><img src="/../img/EE252/EE252%209.png" alt="Full Adder"></li><li>Ripple Carry Adder: serires of full adders, where each full adder performs the addition for a single bit position.</li></ol><h2 id="Week-5"><a href="#Week-5" class="headerlink" title="Week 5"></a><strong><em>Week 5</em></strong></h2><h3 id="Sequence-Logic"><a href="#Sequence-Logic" class="headerlink" title="Sequence Logic"></a><strong>Sequence Logic</strong></h3><ol><li>Before, are all combinational logic. Circuit outputs only depend on current input values.</li><li>A circuit’s current state is the binary number that is currently stored in the circuit’s flip-flops.</li><li>Sequence logic: circuit outputs depend on both current input values and past stored values.</li><li>D flip-flop: output is always equal to the value it is storing<br><img src="/../img/EE252/Week5%201.png" alt="Full Adder"></li><li>D flip-flop updates when the clock transitions from 0 to 1 (rising edge)</li><li>FSM (finite state machine): any circuit built from flip-flops is FSM</li><li>State Diagram:<ol><li>state is represented by a circle, the circle also indicate the output in that state.</li><li>state transitions represented by an arrow from one state to another. Labeled with the input condition.</li></ol></li></ol><h3 id="FSM"><a href="#FSM" class="headerlink" title="FSM"></a><strong>FSM</strong></h3><ol><li>sequential circuits.</li><li>track of which state it is currently in</li><li>The FSM contains one flip-flop per bit of state</li><li>depends both upon the current state and the inputs, the next state is a function of the current state and current input values.</li><li>Start state &lt;-&gt; reset state</li><li>Some state machines do not have an input, or the input does not affect a particular state transition, this type of transition is an unconditional transition.</li><li>“X” means shorthand for “any value of”</li><li>The output will be the current state output.</li></ol><h3 id="Registers-Memory"><a href="#Registers-Memory" class="headerlink" title="Registers Memory"></a><strong>Registers Memory</strong></h3><ol><li>A register is a group of flip-flops used to stire multi-bit binary values.</li><li>Write-Enable: whether take the input to store</li><li>Address: M bits, $2^M$ locations to access.</li><li>Each location stores a single N-bit word: data size, # bits per location</li><li>Capacity &#x3D; (# locations) * (data size)</li><li>Address selects which register supplies data out using Mut.</li><li>Address selects which register may be written to using decoder. Selected register will only be written if WE&#x3D;1</li></ol>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Courses</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>course notes</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>美东游记-波士顿</title>
    <link href="/2023/09/01/life_experience_2/"/>
    <url>/2023/09/01/life_experience_2/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>正如之前的安排，8 月中旬去了美国东海岸旅游了一趟。路线是芝加哥-&gt;波士顿-&gt;纽约-&gt;华盛顿（主要是去 UMD）。一路风尘，回来安顿下来之后写一些随感。</p><p>在开始之前，我突然想起了余秋雨的《文化苦旅》，是初中的时候班主任推荐的。说实在我并不觉得《文化苦旅》的文笔有多好，指类似于《生活在树上》给人眼花缭乱的感觉，也不觉得其有多朴实，指类似于《骆驼祥子》给人过于“地道”的感觉。《文化苦旅》就像是普通人写的一本普通游记，平淡的记录一路上发生所有的事情，辅以一些历史资料和个人感悟。唯一令人印象深刻的是余秋雨（似乎？）一路跨国欧亚大陆的长途旅行。假使我有这份财富和运气，将来我也要这么走一趟（笑）。</p><p>那，就万物起始，从 7 天呆在波士顿的旅行开始。</p><p>抵达波士顿的第一天，借宿在 Y 同学的家里。不远就是 MIT 的校区。MIT 给我的第一印象就是和 Skd 很像，校园不大，各楼之间都有走廊相连接，专业设置也大体是理工科。当然 MIT 的学术成就和影响是 Skd 万万望尘莫及的。（人，要有理想，万一一百年后 Skd 也能成为东方 MIT 呢）</p><p>7 天的空闲时间我基本呆在 MIT 的 Hayden Library。是一个坐落在 Charies River 旁的小型图书馆，其四周都是落地窗，24H 开放（工作时间对公众开放）。借了 Y 同学的校园卡，得以在里面搬砖敲代码。我着实喜欢这样的图书馆，从窗口望出去，草坪，河水，和远处的 CBD 构成绝妙的图像平衡。<br><img src="/../img/life_experience_2/IMG_library.JPG" alt="Hayden Library"></p><p>来波士顿的首要目标就是炫意大利小镇的龙虾意面，这家店叫 The Daily Catch。店不大，开在拥挤的街道上，有点苍蝇馆子的味道。来之前有所听闻其名声和巨长的排队人数，我便早上 10 点就从 Hayden Library 出发，但到那儿依然排了半个小时的队伍。</p><p>我没有具体看菜单，毕竟是奔着龙虾来的（大体还是一些经典的意大利菜，龙虾意面标注在菜单的正中央，大写加粗）。原本是打算和 Y 同学一起吃，但是 Y 同学沉迷 research，只好点了一人份的龙虾意面。<br><img src="/../img/life_experience_2/IMG_1146.JPG" alt="The Daily Catch"><br><img src="/../img/life_experience_2/IMG_1147.JPG" alt="Lobster Noodles"><br>说实话，分量确实很大（将近 70 刀！），也满足了我关在 Madison 半年对于美食的极高期待。店里面都是三三两两的游客，邻桌是带父母来波士顿旅游的华侨。我独自一人在店中狂炫龙虾，倒也是一种奇特的经历。</p><p>来波士顿之前有所听闻 MFA 的莫奈藏品。对于我这种毫无艺术细胞的人来说，印象派画家，尤其是莫奈，通过其更加通俗易懂的表达形式，相比于抽象派更能吸引我。说起来我和莫奈的渊源也有些奇妙，小学的时候在某本杂志上看到过对于莫奈画的赏析，讲的是《日出·印象》；那个时候惊叹于真的有人可以画出早晨港口那种烟雾朦胧的感觉。</p><p>不过可惜的是 MFA 只收藏了莫奈的《睡莲》等练习画，没能看到《日出》，也没能看到《草地上的午餐》，着实有点可惜。后来去纽约的时候，大都会博物馆的整个欧洲艺术展区都在维护，此躺美东旅行没有看到对于我来说的莫奈的代表作，实在是可惜。<br><img src="/../img/life_experience_2/IMG_1161.JPG" alt="Les Meules"><br><img src="/../img/life_experience_2/IMG_1155.JPG" alt="La Japonaise"></p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Gossip</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>traveling</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>近期随感</title>
    <link href="/2023/07/09/life_experience_1/"/>
    <url>/2023/07/09/life_experience_1/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>恍惚间，已经是 23 年 8 月 1 号了。抵美的第八个月。</p><p>上次更新博客已经是一个月前，看来当初还颇有自知之明。简单梳理一下这个月发生的事情。</p><p>大部分同期交换的同学已经回国，作为留守人员，承担着送人和薅羊毛的责任和权利，虽然后者偏多。处在异国他乡，尤其是在麦屯这种独立日都看不到烟花的乡村，感到寂寞是常有的事。好在麦迪逊风光确实不错，大部分时间也很安全，我赖以四处走动。贴上几幅随手所拍。<br><img src="/../img/life_experience_1/IMG_0985.JPG" alt="Lake Mendota (near Memorial Union)"><br><img src="/../img/life_experience_1/IMG_0996.JPG" alt="Memorial Union"><br><img src="/../img/life_experience_1/IMG_1011.JPG" alt="Lake Mendota"><br><img src="/../img/life_experience_1/IMG_1025.JPG" alt="Place near my house"><br><img src="/../img/life_experience_1/IMG_1039.JPG" alt="Mills Concert Hall"><br><img src="/../img/life_experience_1/IMG_1060.JPG" alt="Just Keep Swimming!"><br><img src="/../img/life_experience_1/IMG_1079.JPG" alt="Washburn Observatory"><br><img src="/../img/life_experience_1/IMG_1088.JPG" alt="Way to McDonald&#39;s!"><br>不得不承认，麦迪逊的夏天确实如当地人口中那样美好。其夏日白天因为高纬度而漫长，即使忙碌到 8 点也可以踩着夕阳去湖边听免费的音乐会。气温又刚刚好，差不多等于上海的春秋季，适合穿着短袖套一件外衣出门。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Gossip</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>emo</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Hello World ?</title>
    <link href="/2023/07/03/hello-world/"/>
    <url>/2023/07/03/hello-world/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>欢迎来到我的博客!</p><p>因为在主页上挂着Hexo的Introduction着实是有些奇怪，所以先写一点文字，一是让博客里有一些电子垃圾，二是留一些以后可以怀念的文字。</p><p>当然我并不能确保特定的更新频率，而且维护博客大概也会上我的人生必做清单（这个清单上已经有如下事项：读完紫龙书，读完C++大部头，完成Sencondary Market Project的前后端分离），当然了，也很难想象会有人特地来赏光我的博客。所以，我对于这个博客的定义更倾向于是一点点的个人介绍，大量的生活经历分享和不知所云的灌水文字。</p><p>或许不久以后因为申请会陆续挂上个人简历和项目链接，不过相比全是paper的大佬博客，这儿不过是“存在主义”罢了，仅供commitee或者prof一笑。</p><p>好了，回归正题。</p><p>既然是作为可以怀念的文字，我先写写为何突发奇想创建自己的博客。我现位于UW-Madison，WISC，作为交换生在北美虚度光阴。上学期初寻找系统方向的Prof能够接纳我进组做一些项目<del>带带我水文章</del>，觉得需要创建一个个人网站来贴点CV和toy project。不曾想Prof Xiangyao Yu欣然接受我的申请，并且与我合作了一个项目<del>我觉得大概是CAII写的RISCV Simulator起了作用</del>，导致筹划到一半的个人网站不了了之。到了暑假，不堪项目的推进，托福和GRE，还有几个toy competition的压力，便乘机做个博客，写点不用debug多线程的文字，贴点四处晃荡的图片，以期在满屏error和low performance的大山下苟延残喘。</p><p>对于博客的内容，我想有一部分会是对过往岁月的“追忆”，我对此有充足的理由。首先，根据幸存者偏差的乱用，我们往往会注意到不如以前的事务，比如Madison的中餐让我开始可以接受博海一楼的自选菜。此外，随着心智和年龄的增长，我往往会对过往的人和物有更多的理解和思考，并且自责于当时的错误做法，遗憾于产生的bad ending，留下这些思考可以作为一面明镜，警醒我现在的所作所为，毕竟人往往会进入同一条河流。当然了，更多的其实还是像林海音之于《城南旧事》，曹雪芹之于《红楼梦》，对于自己曾经岁月的无限追忆，因为其美好，其蕴含的无限可能。</p><p>还有一部分会是一些技术的留档，<del>f**k you, CSDN</del>虽然我觉得其实如果自己真要用了使用chatgpt会更方便（GPT-4已经能帮我调多线程Bug了，我哭死）。考虑到之后回国可能的TGW问题，或是一些刁钻的环境问题，或是一些第三方库古怪的调用，我还是会不定期将一些技术整理成文档上传。</p><p>当然了，肯定还有一部分是关于美食，旅游等生活方面的分享，毕竟我已经没有了高中从医救济苍生的伟大理想，Just enjoy the fking world!之后8月中旬会飞往波士顿和旧金山，十分期待某人请客的龙虾。</p><p>最后，创建博客还基于一点点个人的想法，大刘说过“给岁月以文明，给时光以生命”，仅以此给这个宇宙和这片时间一点点来自Zhenghong Yu的痕迹。</p><p>Welcome to my blog!</p><p>Since it’s extraordinary to have Hexo’s Introduction on the homepage, I will write a little bit of text first to keep some e-waste in the blog and leave some text I can remember later.</p><p>Of course, I can’t ensure a specific update frequency, and maintaining the blog would probably be on my life’s must-do list (which already includes the following: finish reading the Purple Dragon book, finish reading the bulk of C++, and finish separating the front and back ends of the Secondary Market Project), and of course, it’s hard to imagine that anyone would specifically come to my blog. So, my definition of this blog is a personal introduction, more of life experience sharing and watered-down words.</p><p>Maybe I’ll put up a CV and links to my toy projects later for my application. Still, compared to a blog full of papers, this is just an “existentialist” blog, just for the committee or prof to have a laugh.</p><p>Okay, back to business.</p><p>Since this is meant to be a nostalgic text, I’ll start by writing about why I suddenly wanted to start my own blog. I am currently located at UW-Madison, WISC, and spend my time in North America as an exchange student. At the beginning of last semester, I was looking for a Prof in the Systems field to take me on as a member of his group to do some projects <del>bring me up to water papers</del> and thought I needed to create a personal website to post some CVs and toy projects. To my surprise, Prof Xiangyao Yu readily accepted my application and collaborated with me on a project<del>It was probably the RISCV Simulator by CAII that did the trick</del>. And caused the half-planned personal website to fall through. In the summer, I was overwhelmed by the project, the TOEFL and GRE, and the pressure of a few toy competitions, so I took the opportunity to make a blog, write some text without debugging multiple threads, and post some pictures that wander around, to survive under the mountain of errors and low performance.</p><p>I think part of the blog’s content will be a “reminiscence” of the past, and I have good reasons for this. By the indiscriminate use of survivorship bias, we tend to notice things that are not as good as they used to be, such as Madison’s Chinese food, which has made the self-chosen dishes on the ground floor of Bohai acceptable to me. In addition, as my mind and age grow, I tend to understand and think more about people and things from the past, blame myself for the mistakes I made at the time, and regret the bad endings that resulted. Leaving these reflections as a clear mirror to remind me of what I do now; after all, people tend to enter the same river. Of course, it is more like Lin Haiyin’s “Old Stories from the South of the City” or Cao Xueqin’s “Dream of the Red Chamber,” the endless remembrance of my former years of its beauty and the infinite possibilities.</p><p>There will also be a part of it that will be some technical documents, <del>f**k you, CSDN</del>. Though it would be more convenient to use chatgpt if I really had to use this (GPT-4 has been able to help me tune multi-threaded bugs, lmao). Considering the possible TGW problems, tricky environment problems, or weird calls to third-party libraries, I will occasionally upload some techniques.</p><p>Of course, I’m sure there will be some food, travel, and other aspects of life to share; after all, I no longer have the great ambition to be a doctor in high school; I just want to enjoy the fking world!</p><p>Finally, the blog is also based on a bit of personal thought; as Liu said, “Give years to civilization, give time to live,” so this is just a way to give this universe and, this time, a little trace from Zhenghong Yu.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Introduction</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>introduction</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>RISCV-Simulator Part1</title>
    <link href="/2023/07/03/RISCV-Simulator/"/>
    <url>/2023/07/03/RISCV-Simulator/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="1-开源声明"><a href="#1-开源声明" class="headerlink" title="1 开源声明"></a>1 开源声明</h1><p>该项目是上海科技大学CS211 Advancing Computer Architecture课程设计，引用北京大学hehao写的RISCV平台（<a href="https://github.com/hehao98/RISCV-Simulator">https://github.com/hehao98/RISCV-Simulator</a> ）。</p><h1 id="2-平台安装与测试"><a href="#2-平台安装与测试" class="headerlink" title="2 平台安装与测试"></a>2 平台安装与测试</h1><p>其实整个平台的简介，安装和运行原作者已经有了详尽的文档（<a href="https://hehao98.github.io/posts/2019/03/riscv-simulator/">https://hehao98.github.io/posts/2019/03/riscv-simulator/</a> ）。个人推荐是直接阅读原文。项目本体应该没有显著的bug（我并不敢打包票，因为我自己就发现了一个并且提了issue，然而作者表示3年前写的，已经忘光了lmao），个人测试在大部分linux发行版上面都可以正常运行。</p><h1 id="3-项目框架介绍和Lab总览"><a href="#3-项目框架介绍和Lab总览" class="headerlink" title="3 项目框架介绍和Lab总览"></a>3 项目框架介绍和Lab总览</h1><p>（其实想吐槽一下整个平台有屎山的味道，但是转念一想，毕竟不是人人都是pintos这种历经了数十年打磨的项目，也就心平气和了）<br>项目结构其实很简单，在4个Lab中基本只需要关注<code>\src</code>即可，文件名基本说明了其功能，详细情况我将在具体的Lab分析中谈及。<code>\test</code>放置测试文件，需要编译为RISCV放置在<code>\riscv-elf</code>中运行。<br>Lab 0主要是实现原子指令。Lab 1涉及实现不同policy的Cache。Lab 2实现基于感知机的分支预测。Lab 3实现多核CPU。<br>在Part 1中，我将分析Lab 0和其具体实现。</p><h1 id="4-Lab-0"><a href="#4-Lab-0" class="headerlink" title="4 Lab 0"></a>4 Lab 0</h1><p>Lab 0 相对来说是四个项目中最简单的一个（合理，毕竟谁也不想一上来就写多线程），而且我不幸的发现，这是唯一一个我不需要回去看代码就能开些blog的Lab了。</p><h2 id="4-1-文档分析"><a href="#4-1-文档分析" class="headerlink" title="4.1 文档分析"></a>4.1 文档分析</h2><p>首先我们通读Lab要求文档（<a href="https://github.com/HarukiMoriarty/CS211-AdvancingCA-Shanghaitech/blob/main/Lab/Lab0/CS211-Lab0.pdf">https://github.com/HarukiMoriarty/CS211-AdvancingCA-Shanghaitech/blob/main/Lab/Lab0/CS211-Lab0.pdf</a> ）。显然，我们需要实现两个原子指令，<code>Load Reserved(LR)</code>和<code>Store Conditional(SC)</code>。</p><p>我们先简短介绍一下原子指令。原子指令是一种重要的并发工具，保证其执行过程中不会被其他进程或线程中断，从而确保数据的一致性和操作的完整性。</p><p>RISCV的原子指令不止LR&#x2F;SC，同样存在一批以“AMO”为前缀的原子指令，Lab 0中我们仅考虑LR&#x2F;SC。在这时我们便遇到了第一个问题，在不同版本RISCV文档中，对于LR&#x2F;SC的实现要求是不同的，特指功能要求（因为structure是一样的）。我选择了V1版本（Volume 1, Unprivileged Specification version 20191213）。有兴趣的大佬可以参考21年的新版本(v2)，对于LR&#x2F;SC指令的要求更为宽松。</p><p>我们首先展示LR&#x2F;SC指令结构（没啥好分析的，直接上图）<br><img src="/../img/riscv/instruction%20structure.png"><br>LR&#x2F;SC都是32位指令，opcode为<code>0X2F</code>；funct5为<code>0x3</code>；对于8B数据，funct3为<code>0x3</code>，对于4B数据，funct3为<code>0x2</code>；本次Lab不考虑数据对齐。</p><p>然后我们分析其基本功能，LR指令从rs1处获得数据地址，从rd处获得符号位扩展，并且对这个地址进行注册保留。SC指令从rs1处获得数据地址，从rs2处获得数据，当且仅当该地址注册保留依旧有效（valid）时成功执行，将数据从rs2写入内存，向rd中写入0；如果执行失败，则仅向rd中写入非0值。根据V1版本推测，我倾向于无论成功与否，LR&#x2F;SC指令的执行都会清除指向地址的注册保留。</p><p>我们考虑更多，如果（指令流上）同时存在多个嵌套LR-SC指令对怎么办？这不仅仅包括，单一核(hart)执行了嵌套的LR-SC指令，也包括多个核同时对一个地址进行LR-SC指令。V1采取了更为保守的策略，只允许SC追踪最近的，同一个核的LR指令。</p><p>我在这里附上原文，An SC can only pair with the most recent LR in program order. An SC may succeed only if no store from another hart to the reservation set can be observed to have occurred between the LR and the SC, and if there is no other SC between the LR and itself in program order. An SC may succeed only if no write from a device other than a hart to the bytes accessed by the LR instruction can be observed to have occurred between the LR and SC. Note this LR might have had a different effective address and data size, but reserved the SC’s address as part of the reservation set.</p><p>很绕，我进行简要概括，即，在当前核LR到SC的程序流中，不能出现额外的LR&#x2F;SC指令，不能出现其他核访问保留注册地址的操作，不能出现本核对于注册保留地址进行写操作，并且SC指令观察到保留注册依然有效，才能成功执行。</p><p>这其实极大的简化了Lab的难度，在一开始我和马老师的讨论中考虑了更为复杂的情况，也是21版V2中所考虑的，允许一些只读指令在注册保留的地址上操作，并且允许LR&#x2F;SC指令的嵌套。V1近乎苛刻的要求反而是让人感觉相当奇怪的（不过，先正确，再效率）。这一点其实可以另外写一篇文章讨论。</p><h2 id="4-2-框架分析与设计实现"><a href="#4-2-框架分析与设计实现" class="headerlink" title="4.2 框架分析与设计实现"></a>4.2 框架分析与设计实现</h2><p>本Lab只需要动<code>/src/Simulator</code>即可。</p><p>我们先总览Simulator，其本质上就是实现了CPU的五级流水，将他们实现为具体的五个函数，fetch，decode，excute，memoryAccess，和writeBack，简明易懂。</p><p>我们不妨先将LR&#x2F;SC指令的解码和信息传递完成。</p><figure class="highlight lasso"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br><span class="line">11</span><br><span class="line">12</span><br><span class="line">13</span><br><span class="line">14</span><br><span class="line">15</span><br><span class="line">16</span><br><span class="line">17</span><br><span class="line">18</span><br><span class="line">19</span><br><span class="line">20</span><br><span class="line">21</span><br><span class="line">22</span><br><span class="line">23</span><br><span class="line">24</span><br><span class="line">25</span><br><span class="line">26</span><br><span class="line">27</span><br><span class="line">28</span><br><span class="line">29</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs lasso"><span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span><br>namespace RISCV<br>&#123;<br>    <span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span><br>    enum Inst<br>    &#123;<br>        <span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span><br>        LRW = <span class="hljs-number">54</span>,   <span class="hljs-comment">/* add encode lr.w instruction as 54 */</span><br>        LRD = <span class="hljs-number">55</span>,   <span class="hljs-comment">/* add encode lr.d instruction as 55 */</span><br>        SCW = <span class="hljs-number">56</span>,   <span class="hljs-comment">/* add encode sc.w instruction as 56 */</span><br>        SCD = <span class="hljs-number">57</span>,   <span class="hljs-comment">/* add encode sc.d instruction as 57 */</span><br>        <span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span><br>    &#125;;<br>    <span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span><br>    <span class="hljs-comment">/* add LR SC instruction with opcode 0X2F */</span><br>    const int OP_CAS = <span class="hljs-number">0x2F</span>;<br>    <span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span><br>    <span class="hljs-keyword">inline</span> bool isReadMem(Inst inst)<br>    &#123;<br>        <span class="hljs-comment">/* As LR and SC both need memory access and write back to </span><br><span class="hljs-comment">        reg, so we need to handle with harzard in pipline */</span><br>        <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span> (<span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span> || inst == LRW || inst == LRD<br>            || inst == SCW || inst == SCD)<br>        &#123;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>        &#125;<br>        <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> <span class="hljs-literal">false</span>;<br>    &#125; <br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>我们首先在头文件Inst数据结构中加上四个LR&#x2F;SC指令的代号数字，然后将其列入内存操作指令中。</p><figure class="highlight d"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br><span class="line">11</span><br><span class="line">12</span><br><span class="line">13</span><br><span class="line">14</span><br><span class="line">15</span><br><span class="line">16</span><br><span class="line">17</span><br><span class="line">18</span><br><span class="line">19</span><br><span class="line">20</span><br><span class="line">21</span><br><span class="line">22</span><br><span class="line">23</span><br><span class="line">24</span><br><span class="line">25</span><br><span class="line">26</span><br><span class="line">27</span><br><span class="line">28</span><br><span class="line">29</span><br><span class="line">30</span><br><span class="line">31</span><br><span class="line">32</span><br><span class="line">33</span><br><span class="line">34</span><br><span class="line">35</span><br><span class="line">36</span><br><span class="line">37</span><br><span class="line">38</span><br><span class="line">39</span><br><span class="line">40</span><br><span class="line">41</span><br><span class="line">42</span><br><span class="line">43</span><br><span class="line">44</span><br><span class="line">45</span><br><span class="line">46</span><br><span class="line">47</span><br><span class="line">48</span><br><span class="line">49</span><br><span class="line">50</span><br><span class="line">51</span><br><span class="line">52</span><br><span class="line">53</span><br><span class="line">54</span><br><span class="line">55</span><br><span class="line">56</span><br><span class="line">57</span><br><span class="line">58</span><br><span class="line">59</span><br><span class="line">60</span><br><span class="line">61</span><br><span class="line">62</span><br><span class="line">63</span><br><span class="line">64</span><br><span class="line">65</span><br><span class="line">66</span><br><span class="line">67</span><br><span class="line">68</span><br><span class="line">69</span><br><span class="line">70</span><br><span class="line">71</span><br><span class="line">72</span><br><span class="line">73</span><br><span class="line">74</span><br><span class="line">75</span><br><span class="line">76</span><br><span class="line">77</span><br><span class="line">78</span><br><span class="line">79</span><br><span class="line">80</span><br><span class="line">81</span><br><span class="line">82</span><br><span class="line">83</span><br><span class="line">84</span><br><span class="line">85</span><br><span class="line">86</span><br><span class="line">87</span><br><span class="line">88</span><br><span class="line">89</span><br><span class="line">90</span><br><span class="line">91</span><br><span class="line">92</span><br><span class="line">93</span><br><span class="line">94</span><br><span class="line">95</span><br><span class="line">96</span><br><span class="line">97</span><br><span class="line">98</span><br><span class="line">99</span><br><span class="line">100</span><br><span class="line">101</span><br><span class="line">102</span><br><span class="line">103</span><br><span class="line">104</span><br><span class="line">105</span><br><span class="line">106</span><br><span class="line">107</span><br><span class="line">108</span><br><span class="line">109</span><br><span class="line">110</span><br><span class="line">111</span><br><span class="line">112</span><br><span class="line">113</span><br><span class="line">114</span><br><span class="line">115</span><br><span class="line">116</span><br><span class="line">117</span><br><span class="line">118</span><br><span class="line">119</span><br><span class="line">120</span><br><span class="line">121</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs d">......<br>namespace RISCV<br>&#123;<br>    ......<br>    <span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> <span class="hljs-built_in">char</span> *INSTNAME[]&#123; <span class="hljs-comment">/* add instruction name */</span><br>        ......,<span class="hljs-string">&quot;lrw&quot;</span>,<span class="hljs-string">&quot;lrd&quot;</span>,<span class="hljs-string">&quot;scw&quot;</span>,<span class="hljs-string">&quot;scd&quot;</span>&#125;;<br>&#125;<br>......<br><span class="hljs-keyword">void</span> Simulator::decode()<br>&#123;<br>    ......<br>    <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span> (<span class="hljs-keyword">this</span>-&gt;fReg.len == <span class="hljs-number">4</span>) <span class="hljs-comment">// 32 bit instruction</span><br>    &#123;<br>        ......<br>        <span class="hljs-keyword">switch</span> (opcode)<br>        &#123;<br>            ......<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">case</span> OP_CAS: <span class="hljs-comment">/* add OP_CAS handler */</span><br>            &#123;<br>                <span class="hljs-comment">/* read data in reg[rs1] which store the address */</span><br>                op1 = <span class="hljs-keyword">this</span>-&gt;reg[rs1]; <br>                <span class="hljs-comment">/* read data in reg[rs2] which is no mean in LR, </span><br><span class="hljs-comment">                    store the old_value in SC */</span><br>                op2 = <span class="hljs-keyword">this</span>-&gt;reg[rs2]; <br>                reg1 = rs1;<br>                reg2 = rs2;<br>                dest = rd;  <span class="hljs-comment">/* The reg which should be write back */</span><br><br>                <span class="hljs-comment">/* Get the funct5 */</span><br>                uint32_t  temp = (inst &gt;&gt; <span class="hljs-number">27</span>) &amp; <span class="hljs-number">0</span>x1F;<br>                <span class="hljs-keyword">switch</span> (temp)<br>                &#123;<br>                <span class="hljs-keyword">case</span> <span class="hljs-number">0</span>x2:   <span class="hljs-comment">/* LR instruction */</span><br>                    <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span> (funct3 == <span class="hljs-number">3</span>)    <span class="hljs-comment">/* LR.D instruction */</span><br>                    &#123;<br>                        instname = <span class="hljs-string">&quot;lrd&quot;</span>;<br>                        insttype = LRD;<br>                    &#125;<br>                    <span class="hljs-keyword">else</span> <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span> (funct3 == <span class="hljs-number">2</span>)   <span class="hljs-comment">/* LR.W instruction */</span><br>                    &#123;<br>                        instname = <span class="hljs-string">&quot;lrw&quot;</span>;<br>                        instyype = LRW;<br>                    &#125;<br>                    <span class="hljs-keyword">else</span><br>                    &#123;<br>                        <span class="hljs-keyword">this</span>-&gt;panic(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;Unknown 32bit funct3 0x%x\n&quot;</span>, funct3);<br>                    &#125;<br>                    <span class="hljs-keyword">break</span>;<br>                <span class="hljs-keyword">case</span> <span class="hljs-number">0</span>x3:   <span class="hljs-comment">/* SC instruction */</span><br>                    <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span> (funct3 == <span class="hljs-number">3</span>)    <span class="hljs-comment">/* SC.D instruction */</span><br>                    &#123;<br>                        instname = <span class="hljs-string">&quot;scd&quot;</span>;<br>                        insttype = SCD;<br>                    &#125;<br>                    <span class="hljs-keyword">else</span> <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span> (funct3 == <span class="hljs-number">2</span>)   <span class="hljs-comment">/* SC.W instruction */</span><br>                    &#123;<br>                        instname = <span class="hljs-string">&quot;scw&quot;</span>;<br>                        instyype = SCW;<br>                    &#125;<br>                    <span class="hljs-keyword">else</span><br>                    &#123;<br>                        <span class="hljs-keyword">this</span>-&gt;panic(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;Unknown 32bit funct3 0x%x\n&quot;</span>, funct3);<br>                    &#125;<br>                    <span class="hljs-keyword">break</span>;<br>                <span class="hljs-keyword">default</span>:<br>                    <span class="hljs-keyword">this</span>-&gt;panic(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;Unknown 32bit funct5</span><br><span class="hljs-string">                        0x%x\n&quot;</span>, temp);<br>                &#125;<br>            &#125;<br>            ......<br>        &#125;<br>    &#125;<br>    ......<br>&#125;<br><br><span class="hljs-keyword">void</span> Simulator::excecute()<br>&#123;<br>    ......<br>    <span class="hljs-built_in">bool</span> _cas = <span class="hljs-literal">false</span>;  <span class="hljs-comment">/* To identify whether it is a LR or SC */</span><br><br>    <span class="hljs-keyword">switch</span> (inst)<br>    &#123;<br>        ......<br>        <span class="hljs-keyword">case</span> LRW:   <span class="hljs-comment">/* Datapath of LR.W instruction */</span><br>            readMem = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            writeReg = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            memLen = <span class="hljs-number">4</span>;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">out</span> = op1;<br>            readSignExt = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            _cas = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">break</span>;<br>        <span class="hljs-keyword">case</span> LRD:   <span class="hljs-comment">/* Datapath of LR.D instruction */</span><br>            readMem = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            writeReg = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            memLen = <span class="hljs-number">8</span>;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">out</span> = op1;<br>            readSignExt = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            _cas = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">break</span>;<br>        <span class="hljs-keyword">case</span> SCW:   <span class="hljs-comment">/* Datapath of SC.W instruction */</span><br>            writeReg = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            writeMem = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            memLen = <span class="hljs-number">4</span>;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">out</span> = op1;<br>            _cas = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            op2 = op2 &amp; <span class="hljs-number">0</span>xFFFFFFFF;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">break</span>;<br>        <span class="hljs-keyword">case</span> SCD:   <span class="hljs-comment">/* Datapath of SC.D instruction */</span><br>            writeReg = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            writeMem = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            memLen = <span class="hljs-number">8</span>;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">out</span> = op1;<br>            op2 = op2 &amp; <span class="hljs-number">0</span>xFFFFFFFF;<br>            _cas = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">break</span>;<br>        ......<br>    &#125;<br>    ......<br>    <span class="hljs-comment">/* Pass the information to the next stage */</span><br>    <span class="hljs-keyword">this</span>-&gt;eRegNew._cas = _cas;  <br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>这都是一些非常“顺其自然”的照猫画虎，接下去我们需要考虑一个合适的数据结构，并且将原子性质在memoryAccess中实现。我们之前讨论了（2019）V1版本的CAS指令要求，我选择了直接在Simulator类中声明私有变量，存储注册保留的地址，注册保留的字节数，以及注册保留的valid bit。</p><figure class="highlight lasso"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br><span class="line">11</span><br><span class="line">12</span><br><span class="line">13</span><br><span class="line">14</span><br><span class="line">15</span><br><span class="line">16</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs lasso">class Simulator<br>&#123;<br><span class="hljs-keyword">public</span>:<br>    <span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span><br><span class="hljs-keyword">private</span>:<br>    <span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span><br>    struct EReg<br>    &#123;<br>        <span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span><br>        bool _cas;<br>    &#125; eReg, eRegNew;<br>    <span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span><br>    uint32_t registry_addr; <span class="hljs-comment">/* Registry hold the first address */</span> <br>    uint32_t registry_num;  <span class="hljs-comment">/* Registry hold the number */</span><br>    bool registry_whe;      <span class="hljs-comment">/* Registry hold the valid bit */</span><br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>那么如何利用这些数据结构实现CAS也变得显而易见。</p><p>对于SC指令，我们注意到，任何涉及注册保留地址的存储行为都会使注册保留失效，所以我简单粗暴的在原先的store行为上加了一层地址判断。然后，针对SC指令，进行特殊的逻辑判断，查找对应地址是否注册保留，如果注册保留有效，那么向内存写入地址，返回0x0；如果注册保留失败，那么直接返回非0值。注意，无论是否是SC指令，任何存储行为都会使目标地址的注册保留失效。</p><p>对于LR指令，我们直接更新数据结构即可，设置目标地址的注册保留有效，从内存中读出数据，并且记录其字节数。正常的读内存指令不需要进行其他操作。我们可以注意到，因为LR实时维护了数据结构，所以只会保留最近的LR指令，满足了我们之前的讨论要求。</p><figure class="highlight xl"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br><span class="line">11</span><br><span class="line">12</span><br><span class="line">13</span><br><span class="line">14</span><br><span class="line">15</span><br><span class="line">16</span><br><span class="line">17</span><br><span class="line">18</span><br><span class="line">19</span><br><span class="line">20</span><br><span class="line">21</span><br><span class="line">22</span><br><span class="line">23</span><br><span class="line">24</span><br><span class="line">25</span><br><span class="line">26</span><br><span class="line">27</span><br><span class="line">28</span><br><span class="line">29</span><br><span class="line">30</span><br><span class="line">31</span><br><span class="line">32</span><br><span class="line">33</span><br><span class="line">34</span><br><span class="line">35</span><br><span class="line">36</span><br><span class="line">37</span><br><span class="line">38</span><br><span class="line">39</span><br><span class="line">40</span><br><span class="line">41</span><br><span class="line">42</span><br><span class="line">43</span><br><span class="line">44</span><br><span class="line">45</span><br><span class="line">46</span><br><span class="line">47</span><br><span class="line">48</span><br><span class="line">49</span><br><span class="line">50</span><br><span class="line">51</span><br><span class="line">52</span><br><span class="line">53</span><br><span class="line">54</span><br><span class="line">55</span><br><span class="line">56</span><br><span class="line">57</span><br><span class="line">58</span><br><span class="line">59</span><br><span class="line">60</span><br><span class="line">61</span><br><span class="line">62</span><br><span class="line">63</span><br><span class="line">64</span><br><span class="line">65</span><br><span class="line">66</span><br><span class="line">67</span><br><span class="line">68</span><br><span class="line">69</span><br><span class="line">70</span><br><span class="line">71</span><br><span class="line">72</span><br><span class="line">73</span><br><span class="line">74</span><br><span class="line">75</span><br><span class="line">76</span><br><span class="line">77</span><br><span class="line">78</span><br><span class="line">79</span><br><span class="line">80</span><br><span class="line">81</span><br><span class="line">82</span><br><span class="line">83</span><br><span class="line">84</span><br><span class="line">85</span><br><span class="line">86</span><br><span class="line">87</span><br><span class="line">88</span><br><span class="line">89</span><br><span class="line">90</span><br><span class="line">91</span><br><span class="line">92</span><br><span class="line">93</span><br><span class="line">94</span><br><span class="line">95</span><br><span class="line">96</span><br><span class="line">97</span><br><span class="line">98</span><br><span class="line">99</span><br><span class="line">100</span><br><span class="line">101</span><br><span class="line">102</span><br><span class="line">103</span><br><span class="line">104</span><br><span class="line">105</span><br><span class="line">106</span><br><span class="line">107</span><br><span class="line">108</span><br><span class="line">109</span><br><span class="line">110</span><br><span class="line">111</span><br><span class="line">112</span><br><span class="line">113</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs xl">void Simulator::memoryAccess()<br>&#123;<br>    ......<br>    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">bool</span> _cas = this-&gt;</span>eReg._cas;<br>    ......<br>    <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span> (writeMem)<br>    &#123;<br>        switch (memLen)<br>        &#123;<br>        case <span class="hljs-number">1</span>:<br>            <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">good</span> = this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">memory</span>-&gt;</span>setByte(out, op2, &amp;cycles);<br>            <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">if</span> ((out &gt;= this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_addr</span>) &amp;&amp; (out &lt;= (this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_addr</span> + this-&gt;</span>registry_num))) <br>            &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* If there is any byte write to the reservation set */</span><br>                <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_whe = <span class="hljs-literal">false</span>;<br>            &#125;<br>            break;<br>        case <span class="hljs-number">2</span>:<br>            <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">good</span> = this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">memory</span>-&gt;</span>setShort(out, op2, &amp;cycles);<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">for</span> (uint32_t i = <span class="hljs-number">0</span>; i &lt; <span class="hljs-number">2</span>; i++) <br>            &#123;<br>                <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">if</span> (((out + i) &gt;= this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_addr</span>) &amp;&amp; ((out + i) &lt;= (this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_addr</span> + this-&gt;</span>registry_num)))<br>                &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* Any byte write to the reservation set */</span><br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_whe = <span class="hljs-literal">false</span>;<br>                &#125;<br>            &#125;<br>            break;<br>        case <span class="hljs-number">4</span>:<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span> (_cas)<br>            &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* If this is SC instruction */</span><br>                <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">if</span> (this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_whe</span> &amp;&amp; (this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_addr</span> == out) &amp;&amp; (this-&gt;</span>registry_num == <span class="hljs-number">4</span>))<br>                &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* Reservation set is valid the first address same the access length same */</span><br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">good</span> = this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">memory</span>-&gt;</span>setInt(out, op2, &amp;cycles);<br>                    out = <span class="hljs-number">0</span>;<br>                &#125;<br>                <span class="hljs-keyword">else</span><br>                &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* If failed return code 1 */</span><br>                    out = <span class="hljs-number">1</span>;<br>                &#125;<br>                <span class="hljs-comment">/* SC eliminate all reservation */</span><br>                <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_whe = <span class="hljs-literal">false</span>;<br>            &#125;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">else</span><br>            &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* If not, do basic store operation */</span><br>                <span class="hljs-keyword">for</span> (uint32_t i = <span class="hljs-number">0</span>; i &lt; <span class="hljs-number">4</span>; i++) <br>                &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* For all bytes */</span><br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">if</span> (((out + i) &gt;= this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_addr</span>) &amp;&amp; ((out + i) &lt;= (this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_addr</span> + this-&gt;</span>registry_num)))<br>                    &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* Any access to the bytes */</span><br>                        <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_whe = <span class="hljs-literal">false</span>;<br>                    &#125;<br>                &#125;<br>                <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">good</span> = this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">memory</span>-&gt;</span>setInt(out, op2, &amp;cycles);<br>            &#125;<br>            break;<br>        case <span class="hljs-number">8</span>:<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span> (_cas)<br>            &#123;<br>                <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">if</span> (this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_whe</span> &amp;&amp; (this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_addr</span> == out) &amp;&amp; (this-&gt;</span>registry_num == <span class="hljs-number">8</span>))<br>                &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* Reservation set is valid the first address same the access length same */</span><br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">good</span> = this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">memory</span>-&gt;</span>setLong(out, op2, &amp;cycles);<br>                    out = <span class="hljs-number">0</span>;<br>                &#125;<br>                <span class="hljs-keyword">else</span><br>                &#123;<br>                    out = <span class="hljs-number">1</span>;<br>                &#125;<br>                <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">tthis</span>-&gt;</span>registry_whe = <span class="hljs-literal">false</span>;<br>            &#125;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">else</span><br>            &#123;<br>                <span class="hljs-keyword">for</span> (uint32_t i = <span class="hljs-number">0</span>; i &lt; <span class="hljs-number">8</span>; i++) <br>                &#123;<br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">if</span> (((out + i) &gt;= this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_addr</span>) &amp;&amp; ((out + i) &lt;= (this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_addr</span> + this-&gt;</span>registry_num)))<br>                    &#123;<br>                        <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_whe = <span class="hljs-literal">false</span>;<br>                    &#125;<br>                &#125;<br>                <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">good</span> = this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">memory</span>-&gt;</span>setLong(out, op2, &amp;cycles);<br>            &#125;<br>        &#125;<br>    &#125;<br>    ......<br>    <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span> (readMem)<br>    &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* Handle with LR instruction */</span><br>        switch (memLen)<br>        &#123;<br>        ......<br>        case <span class="hljs-number">4</span>: <br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span>(readSignExt)<br>            &#123;<br>                <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span>(_cas)<br>                &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* LR.W instruction */</span><br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_whe = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;  <span class="hljs-comment">/* Valid */</span><br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_addr = out;  <span class="hljs-comment">/* Store */</span><br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_num = <span class="hljs-number">4</span>; <span class="hljs-comment">/* Length */</span><br>                &#125;<br>                <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">out</span> = (int64_t)this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">memory</span>-&gt;</span>getInt(out, &amp;cycles);<br>            &#125;<br>            ......<br>        case <span class="hljs-number">8</span>:<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span>(readSignExt)<br>            &#123;<br>                <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span>(_cas)<br>                &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* LR.W instruction */</span><br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_whe = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_addr = out;<br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_num = <span class="hljs-number">8</span>;<br>                &#125;<br>                <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">out</span> = (int64_t)this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">memory</span>-&gt;</span>getInt(out, &amp;cycles);<br>            &#125;<br>            ......<br>        &#125;<br>    &#125;<br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>好的，到这里我们完成了LR&#x2F;SC这两个指令，接下去我们就是封装一下写一个CAS函数即可，在这里我们直接使用C++的内联汇编</p><figure class="highlight wren"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br><span class="line">11</span><br><span class="line">12</span><br><span class="line">13</span><br><span class="line">14</span><br><span class="line">15</span><br><span class="line">16</span><br><span class="line">17</span><br><span class="line">18</span><br><span class="line">19</span><br><span class="line">20</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs wren">int <span class="hljs-title function_">CAS</span>(<span class="hljs-params">long</span> *<span class="hljs-params">dest</span>, <span class="hljs-params">long</span> <span class="hljs-params">new_value</span>, <span class="hljs-params">long</span> <span class="hljs-params">old_value</span>)<br>&#123;<br>    int <span class="hljs-variable">ret</span> <span class="hljs-operator">=</span> <span class="hljs-number">0</span>;<br><br>    <span class="hljs-comment">// <span class="hljs-doctag">TODO:</span> write your code here</span><br>    <span class="hljs-variable">__asm__</span> <span class="hljs-variable">__volatile__</span>(<br>        <span class="hljs-string">&quot;retry: lr.w  %0, %[output2]<span class="hljs-char escape_">\n</span>&quot;</span>             <span class="hljs-comment">/* Load value of addr */</span><br>        <span class="hljs-string">&quot;       bne   %0, %[input1], fail<span class="hljs-char escape_">\n</span>&quot;</span>        <span class="hljs-comment">/* Compare and check */</span><br>        <span class="hljs-string">&quot;       sc.w  %0, %[input2], %[output2]<span class="hljs-char escape_">\n</span>&quot;</span>  <span class="hljs-comment">/* Store new value */</span><br>        <span class="hljs-string">&quot;       bnez  %0, retry<span class="hljs-char escape_">\n</span>&quot;</span>                  <span class="hljs-comment">/* Whether atom operation succcess */</span><br>        <span class="hljs-string">&quot;       li    %[output1], 1<span class="hljs-char escape_">\n</span>&quot;</span>              <span class="hljs-comment">/* Return code 1 */</span><br>        <span class="hljs-string">&quot;       j     success<span class="hljs-char escape_">\n</span>&quot;</span>                    <span class="hljs-comment">/* Go on following */</span><br>        <span class="hljs-string">&quot;fail:  li    %[output1], 0<span class="hljs-char escape_">\n</span>&quot;</span>              <span class="hljs-comment">/* Return code 0 */</span><br>        <span class="hljs-string">&quot;success: <span class="hljs-char escape_">\n</span>&quot;</span><br>        : [<span class="hljs-variable">output1</span>] <span class="hljs-string">&quot;=&amp;r&quot;</span>(<span class="hljs-variable">ret</span>), [<span class="hljs-variable">output2</span>] <span class="hljs-string">&quot;+A&quot;</span>(<span class="hljs-operator">*</span><span class="hljs-variable">dest</span>)<br>        : [input1] <span class="hljs-string">&quot;rJ&quot;</span>(<span class="hljs-variable">old_value</span>), [input2] <span class="hljs-string">&quot;rJ&quot;</span>(<span class="hljs-variable">new_value</span>)<br>        : <span class="hljs-string">&quot;memory&quot;</span>);<br><br>    <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> <span class="hljs-variable">ret</span>;<br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>代码中的注释已经十分详尽，我不再额外啰嗦。</p><h2 id="4-3-测试"><a href="#4-3-测试" class="headerlink" title="4.3 测试"></a>4.3 测试</h2><p>那么接下去测试即可，将C++文件编译为RISCV汇编文件，注意这里使用<code>rv64ia</code>，因为LR&#x2F;SC指令是扩展指令。测试结果如下：<br><img src="/../img/riscv/result.png"><br>测试通过！</p><h2 id="4-4-思考（胡言乱语）"><a href="#4-4-思考（胡言乱语）" class="headerlink" title="4.4 思考（胡言乱语）"></a>4.4 思考（胡言乱语）</h2><p>严格来说官方提供的测试文件并不详尽，其也只检测了四字节LR&#x2F;SC指令的正确性，此外像多核情况，嵌套问题也被排除在此次Lab的考虑范围之外。或许我有空的时候会重新写一下两个指令，将这些问题考虑进去。（人生目标清单喜加一）</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Techniques</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>riscv</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  
</search>
