<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<search>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Amazon Aurora</title>
    <link href="/2023/12/10/Aurora/"/>
    <url>/2023/12/10/Aurora/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="Paper"><a href="#Paper" class="headerlink" title="Paper"></a>Paper</h2><p>Verbitski, A., Gupta, A., Saha, D., Brahmadesam, M., Gupta, K., Mittal, R., … &amp; Bao, X. (2017, May). Amazon aurora: Design considerations for high throughput cloud-native relational databases. In Proceedings of the 2017 ACM International Conference on Management of Data (pp. 1041-1052).</p><h2 id="1-How-to-Reach-Durability"><a href="#1-How-to-Reach-Durability" class="headerlink" title="1 How to Reach Durability"></a>1 How to Reach Durability</h2><h3 id="1-1-Quorum-Based-Voting-Protocol"><a href="#1-1-Quorum-Based-Voting-Protocol" class="headerlink" title="1.1 Quorum-Based Voting Protocol"></a>1.1 Quorum-Based Voting Protocol</h3><p>Suppose in a replicated system has $V$ copies, each one assigned a vote. A read or write operation must respectively obtain a read quorum of $V_{r}$ votes or a write quorum of $V_{w}$ votes. We need<br>$$ V_r + V_w &gt; V $$<br>$$ V_w &gt; V&#x2F;2 $$<br><img src="/../img/Aurora/Aurora%201.png" alt="Three copies in three AZs"><br>A common example of three copies: $ V_w \geq 2$, $ V_r \geq 2$. Data is unavailable if one AZ is unavailable and one other copy is unavailable.<br><img src="/../img/Aurora/Aurora%202.png" alt="Six copies in three AZs"><br>Six copies: $V_w \geq 4$, $V_r \geq 3$. Can read if one AZ fails and one more copy fails. Can write if one AZ fails.<br><strong>Available Zone(AZ)</strong>: a connected to other AZs through low latency links but is isolated for most faults. -&gt; fail independantly.</p><h3 id="1-2-Segmented-Storage"><a href="#1-2-Segmented-Storage" class="headerlink" title="1.2 Segmented Storage"></a>1.2 Segmented Storage</h3><p><strong>MTTF</strong>: mean time to failure<br><strong>MTTR</strong>: mean time to repair<br>Since MTTF is commonly hard to reduce, we focus on minimize MTTR to prevent double fault(which will lead to quorum failure). We do so by partitioning the database volume into small fixed <strong>Segment</strong>s, 10GB block, basic unit of failure and repair. These are each replicated 6 ways into <strong>Protection Groups(PGs)</strong> so that each PG consists of six 10 GB segments.</p><h2 id="2-How-to-Leverage-Smart-Storage"><a href="#2-How-to-Leverage-Smart-Storage" class="headerlink" title="2 How to Leverage Smart Storage"></a>2 How to Leverage Smart Storage</h2><h3 id="2-1-MySQL-Network-I-x2F-O-Limitation"><a href="#2-1-MySQL-Network-I-x2F-O-Limitation" class="headerlink" title="2.1 MySQL Network I&#x2F;O Limitation"></a>2.1 MySQL Network I&#x2F;O Limitation</h3><p><img src="/../img/Aurora/Aurora%203.png" alt="Network I/O in mirrored MySQL"></p><ol><li>(REDO) log: generated by InnoDB, is physical</li><li>Binlog: generated by MySQL and supportes other storage engines, can be either physical or logical, in order to support point-in-time restores</li><li>Data: the modified data pages</li><li>Double-write: to prevent torn pages</li><li>metadata(FRM)</li></ol><p>Step 1 &amp; 2: writes are issued to EBS, which in turn issues it to an AZ-local mirror, and the acknowledgement is received when both are done<br>Step 3: the write is staged to the standby instance using sync block-level software mirroring<br>Step 4 &amp; 5: writes are written to the standby EBS volume and associated mirror</p><p>Limitation 1: <strong>Steps 1, 3, 5 are sequential and sync</strong><br>Limitation 2: duplication in multi types of write</p><h3 id="2-2-Offloading-Redo-Processing-to-Storage"><a href="#2-2-Offloading-Redo-Processing-to-Storage" class="headerlink" title="2.2 Offloading Redo Processing to Storage"></a>2.2 Offloading Redo Processing to Storage</h3>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Paper Reading</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>Cloud-Native Database</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Logging (Aries)</title>
    <link href="/2023/10/02/Logging/"/>
    <url>/2023/10/02/Logging/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="1-Durability–Why-we-need-Logging"><a href="#1-Durability–Why-we-need-Logging" class="headerlink" title="1 Durability–Why we need Logging"></a>1 Durability–Why we need Logging</h2><p>Let’s first consider a NaiveDB,<br>-step 1: Admit one transaction T<br>-step 2: Execute T to completion<br>-step 3: <strong>Atomically</strong> flush T’s writes to disk<br>-step 4: Admit the next transaction</p><p>That’s easy. But what if, at some point, the disk&#x2F;memory&#x2F;CPU&#x2F;server crashed down, or I cut down the power? To avoid bad things happening, we need to make database <strong>Durability</strong>: Once a transaction commits, its effects must be persistent; the DBMS can tolerate systems failures.</p><p><strong>Durability</strong>: The database must recover to a valid state no matter when a crash occurs.</p><ol><li>Committed transactions should persist.</li><li>Uncommitted transactions should roll back.</li></ol><p><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%201.jpg" alt="example"></p><h2 id="2-WAL"><a href="#2-WAL" class="headerlink" title="2 WAL"></a>2 WAL</h2><p>To reach durability, we introduce a protocol, <strong>Write-Ahead Logging(WAL)</strong>: Flush the log record for an update before the corresponding data page gets to disk; Write all log records for a transaction before commits.</p><p>Before making any changes to the actual data or its structures(like a B+ tree), the system first writes those changes to a log. This log is sequentially written, making it fast to append data.</p><p>Why we use it?</p><ol><li><p><strong>Data Integrity and Durability</strong>: In case of a system crash or power failure, any transactions not permanently written to the data files can be recovered and completed using the log. This ensures that the database remains in a consistent state.</p></li><li><p><strong>Backup and Point-in-time Recovery</strong>: If you have a backup of a database and a subsequent WAL, you can restore the database to any point in time covered by the log. This can be useful for recovering from both catastrophic failures and human errors, like unintended data deletions.</p></li></ol><h2 id="3-Buffer-managerment-policies"><a href="#3-Buffer-managerment-policies" class="headerlink" title="3 Buffer managerment policies"></a>3 Buffer managerment policies</h2><h3 id="3-1-Steal"><a href="#3-1-Steal" class="headerlink" title="3.1 Steal?"></a>3.1 Steal?</h3><p><strong>No Steal</strong>: Dirty pages stay in DRAM until the transaction commits.<br><strong>Steal</strong>: Dirty pages can be flushed to disk before the transaction commits.</p><ol><li>Ad: other transactions can use the buffer slot in DRAM</li><li>Challenge: systems crashed after flushing dirty pages but before the transaction commits. &#x3D;&gt; <strong>Dirty data on disk!</strong></li><li>Solution: <strong>UNDO</strong> logging before each update</li></ol><h3 id="3-2-Force"><a href="#3-2-Force" class="headerlink" title="3.2 Force?"></a>3.2 Force?</h3><p><strong>Force</strong>: All dirty pages must be flushed when the transaction commits.<br><strong>No force</strong>: Dirty pages may stay in memory after the transaction commits.</p><ol><li>Ad: reduce #random IO(high!)</li><li>Challenge: system crashes after the transaction commits but before the dirty pages are flushed &#x3D;&gt; <strong>missing updates from committed transactions!</strong></li><li>Solution: <strong>REDO</strong> logging before each update.</li></ol><p>Notice: the reason choose logging, is that flushing logs can be much cheaper than flushing data pages. Log record can be much smaller than a data page; Logging incurs sequential IO; data page updates incur random IO.</p><h3 id="3-3-Policy-How-to-choose"><a href="#3-3-Policy-How-to-choose" class="headerlink" title="3.3 Policy: How to choose?"></a>3.3 Policy: How to choose?</h3><p>Let’s make a table,<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%202.jpg"></p><h4 id="3-3-1-Force-amp-amp-No-Steal"><a href="#3-3-1-Force-amp-amp-No-Steal" class="headerlink" title="3.3.1 Force &amp;&amp; No Steal"></a>3.3.1 Force &amp;&amp; No Steal</h4><p>We start with the easiest one.</p><p>It is the most strict policy. We do not write logs before the transaction is committed and force flushing logs to disk when the transaction is committed.</p><p>When the system crashes, every committed transactions must persist to disk and every uncommitted transactions must not persist on disk. So we do nothing, <strong>NO REDO nor NO UNDO</strong>. (Philip Bernstein, Vassos Hadzilacos, Nathan Goodman, Concurrency Control and Recovery in Database Systems, 1987)</p><h4 id="3-3-2-Force-amp-amp-Steal"><a href="#3-3-2-Force-amp-amp-Steal" class="headerlink" title="3.3.2 Force &amp;&amp; Steal"></a>3.3.2 Force &amp;&amp; Steal</h4><p>We allow system write logs before the transaction is committed, but force flushing logs to disk when the transaction is committed.</p><p>Log <strong>UNDO</strong> record before each update to database; Log <strong>COMMIT</strong> record when a transaction finishes execution. Modified data pages can be written to disk <strong>after the corresponding UNDO record but before the COMMIT record</strong>.</p><p>So we do <strong>UNDO</strong> only (NVM-based database), <strong>UNDO</strong> uncommitted transactions.</p><h4 id="3-3-3-No-Force-amp-amp-No-Steal"><a href="#3-3-3-No-Force-amp-amp-No-Steal" class="headerlink" title="3.3.3 No Force &amp;&amp; No Steal"></a>3.3.3 No Force &amp;&amp; No Steal</h4><p>We do not allow system write logs to disk before the transaction is committed, but do not force flushing logs to disk when the transaction is committed.</p><p>Log <strong>REDO</strong> record before each update to database. Log <strong>COMMIT</strong> record when a transaction finishes execution. Modified data pages can be written to disk <strong>after COMMIT record is logged</strong>.</p><p>So, we <strong>replay REDO logs</strong> for comitted transactions.</p><h4 id="3-3-4-No-force-amp-amp-Steal"><a href="#3-3-4-No-force-amp-amp-Steal" class="headerlink" title="3.3.4 No force &amp;&amp; Steal"></a>3.3.4 No force &amp;&amp; Steal</h4><p>We not only allow system write logs to dish before the transaction is committed, but also do not force flushing logs to dish when the transaction is committed. The most flexible!</p><p>Log combined <strong>REDO&#x2F;UNDO</strong> record before each update to database; Log <strong>COMMIT</strong> record when a transaction finishes execution; Modified data pages can be written to disk <strong>any time after the corresponding REDO&#x2F;UNDO records</strong>.</p><p>So, we <strong>UNDO uncommitted</strong> transactions and <strong>REDO</strong> committed transactions.</p><h3 id="3-4-ARIES–A-No-force-amp-amp-Steal-Procotol"><a href="#3-4-ARIES–A-No-force-amp-amp-Steal-Procotol" class="headerlink" title="3.4 ARIES–A No force &amp;&amp; Steal Procotol"></a>3.4 ARIES–A No force &amp;&amp; Steal Procotol</h3><p>Mohan, C., Haderle, D., Lindsay, B., Pirahesh, H., &amp; Schwarz, P. (1992). ARIES: A transaction recovery method supporting fine-granularity locking and partial rollbacks using write-ahead logging. ACM Transactions on Database Systems (TODS), 17(1), 94-162.</p><h4 id="3-4-1-Baseline-Design"><a href="#3-4-1-Baseline-Design" class="headerlink" title="3.4.1 Baseline Design"></a>3.4.1 Baseline Design</h4><p>Let’s start with an easiest thinking.</p><p>We want to forward scan of entire log: redo all records; keep a table for active transactions. We backward scan of entire log: undo uncommitted transactions. So we introduce data structures like this:</p><p><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%203.jpg" alt="Data Structure"></p><p>LSN here refers to Log Sequence Number, which can consider as a kind of unique ID.</p><ol><li><p>But it is inefficiency in the <strong>REDO</strong> process. Unnecessary to redo all records; Need to redo only records that are not reflected in data pages.</p></li><li><p>It is also inefficiency in the <strong>UNDO</strong> process. Unnecessary to scan the entire log; Need to undo only records of uncommitted transactions.</p></li><li><p>It also lack of checkpointing. Unnecessary to start from the beginning of log; Start with the first log record that is not reflected in data pages.</p></li></ol><p>Let’s optimized one by one.</p><h4 id="3-4-2-Optimize-REDO-process"><a href="#3-4-2-Optimize-REDO-process" class="headerlink" title="3.4.2 Optimize REDO process"></a>3.4.2 Optimize REDO process</h4><ol><li><strong>pageLSN</strong>: LSN of the log record that describes the latest update to the pate.</li><li>in <strong>REDO</strong> scan: Apply REDO only if <code>record.LSN &gt; page.page.LSN</code>.</li><li><strong>Write</strong>: update <code>pageLSN</code> (for the buffered page) for each write.</li></ol><p>The new data structure is like below:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%204.jpg" alt="Data Structure"></p><h4 id="3-4-3-Optimize-UNDO-process"><a href="#3-4-3-Optimize-UNDO-process" class="headerlink" title="3.4.3 Optimize UNDO process"></a>3.4.3 Optimize UNDO process</h4><ol><li><strong><code>prevLSN</code></strong>: preceding log record written by the same transaction.</li><li><strong><code>lastLSN</code></strong>: LSN of the last log record written by the transaction.</li><li><strong>UNDO</strong> scan: Follow <code>lastLSN</code> and <code>prevLSN</code> to undo records.</li><li><strong>REDO</strong> scan: update <code>lastLSN</code> in <code>Transaction Table</code> based on the last update of the transaction.</li></ol><p>The new data structure is like below:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%205.jpg" alt="Data Structure"></p><h4 id="3-4-4-Add-Checkpoint"><a href="#3-4-4-Add-Checkpoint" class="headerlink" title="3.4.4 Add Checkpoint"></a>3.4.4 Add Checkpoint</h4><ol><li><strong><code>pageID</code></strong>: ID of a dirty page</li><li><strong><code>recLSN</code></strong>: LSN of the first log record since when the page is dirty</li><li><strong>Fuzzy Checkpoing</strong>: log DPT and TT async.</li><li><strong>REDO</strong> scan: start from the smallest LSN in DP.</li></ol><h4 id="3-4-5-Compensation-Log-Record-CLR"><a href="#3-4-5-Compensation-Log-Record-CLR" class="headerlink" title="3.4.5 Compensation Log Record(CLR)"></a>3.4.5 Compensation Log Record(CLR)</h4><p>The action of applying <strong>UNDO</strong> leads to a CLR.</p><ol><li>In undo scan, do not reapply <strong>UNDO</strong> if CLR exists. Do not <strong>UNDO</strong> a <strong>UNDO</strong> operation</li><li><code>UndoNxtLSN</code>: LSN of the next record to be processed during the undo scan.</li></ol><p><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%206.jpg" alt="CLR"></p><p>This is because:</p><ol><li><strong>Avoid Infinite Loops</strong>: If the system kept reapplying the UNDO for a CLR, it would enter into an infinite loop. This is because when you undo a CLR, you’d create another CLR to compensate for that, and then undo that CLR, creating yet another CLR, and so on.</li><li><strong>CLR Represents an Undo</strong>: The very existence of a CLR for a log record indicates that the effects of the original log record have already been undone. Reapplying the UNDO would be redundant and unnecessary.</li><li><strong>Consistency &amp; Idempotence</strong>: One of the primary design goals of recovery algorithms like ARIES is to ensure that the recovery actions are idempotent. That means you can apply them multiple times and still achieve the same state. If you were to reapply the UNDO for a CLR, this idempotent property could be violated.</li></ol><p>The new data structure is like below:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%207.jpg" alt="Data Structure"></p><h4 id="3-4-6-ARIES-Big-Picture"><a href="#3-4-6-ARIES-Big-Picture" class="headerlink" title="3.4.6 ARIES-Big Picture"></a>3.4.6 ARIES-Big Picture</h4><p>Start from the last complete checkpoint.</p><ol><li><strong>Analysis phase</strong>:<br>1.1 rebuild transaction table (for undo phase): for each log record, if <code>update</code> or <code>CLR</code>, insert to transaction table if not exists; if <code>end</code>, delete from transaction table<br>1.2 rebuild dirty page table (for redo phase): if <code>update</code> or <code>CLR</code>, insert to dirty page table if not exists</li><li><strong>REDO phase</strong>:<br>redo transactions whose effects may not be persistent before the crash<br>2.1 From log record containing <strong>smallest <code>RecLSN</code></strong> in the dirty page table. Before this LSN, all redo records have been reflected in data pages on disk.<br>2.2 Can <strong>skip</strong> a redo record for the following cases where the corresponding page has already been flushed before the crash. The page is not in DPT; The page is in DPT but <code>redo_record.LSN</code> &lt; <code>DPT[page].recLSN</code>; After fetching the data page, <code>redo_record.LSN</code> &lt;&#x3D; <code>page.page_LSN</code>.</li><li><strong>UNDO phase</strong>:<br>undo transactions that did not commit before the crash<br>3.1 Choose largest <code>LastLSN</code> among transactions in the TT.<br>3.2 If the log record is an <code>update</code>, <strong>UNDO</strong> the update, write a <code>CLR</code>, add <code>record.prevLSN</code> to TT.<br>3.3 if the log record is an <code>CLR</code>, add <code>CLR.UndoNxtLsn</code> to TT.<br>3.4 If <code>prevLSN</code> and <code>UndoNxtLSN</code> are <code>NULL</code>, remove the transaction from TT.</li></ol><p><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%208.jpg"></p><h4 id="3-4-7-Example"><a href="#3-4-7-Example" class="headerlink" title="3.4.7 Example"></a>3.4.7 Example</h4><p>Let’s consider a situation<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%209.jpg"></p><p><strong>Analysis phase</strong> start at checkpoint<br>step 1:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2010.jpg"><br>step 2:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2011.jpg"><br>Step 3:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2012.jpg"><br>Step 4:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2013.jpg"><br>Step 5:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2014.jpg"></p><p><strong>REDO phase</strong> with given data pages<br>Step 1:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2015.jpg"><br>Step 2:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2016.jpg"><br>Step 3:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2017.jpg"><br>Step 4:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2018.jpg"><br>Step 5:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2019.jpg"></p><p><strong>UNDO phase</strong><br>Step 1:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2020.jpg"><br>Step 2:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2021.jpg"><br>Step 3:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2022.jpg"><br>Step 4:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2023.jpg"><br>Step 5:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2024.jpg"><br>Step 6:<br><img src="/../img/Logging/Logging%2025.jpg"></p><h2 id="4-Acknowledgement"><a href="#4-Acknowledgement" class="headerlink" title="4 Acknowledgement"></a>4 Acknowledgement</h2><p>Thanks UW-Madison COMP 564 Prof Xiangyao Yu!</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Paper Reading</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>database</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>COMP 571</title>
    <link href="/2023/09/30/COMP571/"/>
    <url>/2023/09/30/COMP571/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="Programming"><a href="#Programming" class="headerlink" title="Programming"></a><strong>Programming</strong></h2><h3 id="Week-1"><a href="#Week-1" class="headerlink" title="Week 1"></a>Week 1</h3><ol><li><p>HTML</p><ol><li>hyper-text markup language, defines the structure of the web, make up of a series of “elements” defined by “tags”. <strong>Each element can have a unique <code>id</code> attribute</strong>, used for CSS and JS. 比如访问图片，通过 getelementbyid&#x3D;””来访问</li><li>Document Object Model(DOM), <strong>HTML is a tree</strong>, while each element is a node.</li><li><code>html</code>: encapsulate entire html document, <code>head</code>: include metadata, such as CSS and JS scripts, <code>body</code>: main HTML contentw, <code>h1</code>: headers, <code>p</code>: paragraph text, <code>strong</code>, <code>em</code>: connotation, <code>a</code>: anchor text(links), <code>img</code>: images (with <code>alt</code> attribute), <code>br</code>: linebreak, <code>ul</code>, <code>ol</code>, <code>li</code>: lists, <code>table</code>, <code>threads</code>, <code>tbody</code>, <code>tr</code>, <code>th</code>, <code>td</code>: tables, <code>div</code>: divisions(sections), <code>form</code>: encapsulates many inputs, <code>label</code>: label an input (include <code>for</code> attribute), <code>input</code>: user input, <code>button</code>: buttons</li><li><strong>Modern web browers can interpret HTML, CSS, JS. JSX 不能编译解释！</strong></li></ol></li><li><p>CSS</p><ol><li>Cascading Sytle Sheets, defines the styles to be used, uses a cascading hierachy of selectors and decoration boxes consisting of key-value pairs</li><li><code> </code> applies to all HTML elements with a particular tag, <code>#</code> to particular id, <code>.</code> applies to particular class</li><li><img src="../img/COMP571/COMP 571 1.jpg" width="400" height="150"></li><li>CSS Inline:<br><img src="/../img/COMP571/COMP%20571%202.jpg"><br>CSS Internal:  <img src="../img/COMP571/COMP 571 3.jpg" width="200" height="180">  CSS External:Same as internal but with styling in an external file.</li><li>Not all browsers support all CSS.</li></ol></li><li><p>JavaScript</p><ol><li>A dynamic, loosely-typed language. The data type is inferred from the declaration and can be changed.</li><li>Variables are containers that hold data. Types: numbers, string, boolean, null, undefined, symbol, object(only stored in heap).</li><li>Variables can be declared with <code>var</code>, <code>let</code>, <code>const</code>.  <img src="../img/COMP571/COMP 571 4.jpg" width="300" height="100"></li><li>Query the data type at runtime using <code>typeof</code>.</li><li>Conditionals:<br>5.1 <code>if</code>, <code>else if</code>, <code>else</code> 5.2 <code>switch</code> statements 5.3 <code>evalExpr ? trueExpr : falseExpr</code></li><li><strong>Any value that is not <code>false</code>, <code>undefined</code>, <code>null</code>, <code>0</code>, <code>NaN</code>, <code>&quot;&quot;</code> returns <code>true</code></strong>.</li><li>Comaparison:  <img src="../img/COMP571/COMP 571 5.jpg" width="400" height="200">  Weak comparison do not care about type, `"5" == 5` returns `true`</li><li>Objects: unordered collections of data defined using key-value pairs. (attributes&#x2F;properties).<br><code>object.attribute</code> or <code>object[&quot;attribute&quot;]</code></li><li>Arrays: a varaible that contains multiple elements, do not have to be the same type</li><li><strong>console.log cannot monitor users’ usage of our application, only debug</strong></li></ol></li><li><p>DOM</p><ol><li>HTML is a tree, where each element is a node. We use JS to manipulate this tree.</li><li>Use <code>document</code> to reference the DOM</li></ol><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">let</span> title = <span class="hljs-variable language_">document</span>.<span class="hljs-title function_">getElementById</span>(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;articleTitle&quot;</span>);<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><ol start="3"><li>Add an action for some elememt when some event happens:</li></ol><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">title.<span class="hljs-property">textContent</span> = <span class="hljs-string">&quot;My Website!&quot;</span>;<br>loginBtn.<span class="hljs-title function_">addEventListener</span>(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;click&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-function">() =&gt;</span> &#123;<br>  <span class="hljs-title function_">alert</span>(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;You are advancing to the next part..&quot;</span>);<br>&#125;);<br><span class="hljs-keyword">for</span> (<span class="hljs-keyword">let</span> callout <span class="hljs-keyword">of</span> callouts) &#123;<br>  callout.<span class="hljs-property">style</span>.<span class="hljs-property">color</span> = <span class="hljs-string">&quot;red&quot;</span>;<br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li></ol><h3 id="Week-2"><a href="#Week-2" class="headerlink" title="Week 2"></a>Week 2</h3><ol><li><p>JSON</p><ol><li>A JS Object is executable code, JSON is a language-agnostic respresentation of an object. Cannot write comments in JSON.</li><li><code>JSON.parse</code> JSON String-&gt;JS object, <code>JSON.stringify</code> JS Object-&gt;JSON String</li><li>HTTP Request for JSON: <code>sync</code> and <code>async</code>(recommended). <code>XMLHttpRequest</code> (old) and <code>fetch</code> (new).</li><li>fetch():<br>&#96;fetch(url)</li></ol></li></ol><p>.then((response) &#x3D;&gt; response.json())<br>.then((data) &#x3D;&gt; {})<br>.catch((error) &#x3D;&gt; console.error(error));<code>      happens async,</code>then<code>and</code>catch&#96; take a <strong>callback</strong> function as an argument. A callback function is passed into another function as an argument, which is then invoked inside the outer function to complete a routine or action.</p><ol start="2"><li><p>Write clean code</p><ol><li><strong>imperative</strong>: <code>for (let obj of arr) &#123;&#125;</code>, <strong>declarative</strong>: <code>arr.forEach((obj) =&gt; &#123;&#125;)</code><br>prefer declarative programming,<br><code>forEach</code>, <code>map</code>, <code>filter</code>: used on arrays, take a call back as an argument, <code>slice</code>, <code>concat</code>, <code>some</code>, <code>every</code>, <code>reduce</code></li><li><code>Object.keys(obj)</code> get the keys of an object</li><li><code>setInterval(callback, interval)</code> perform a callback function every interval milliseconds<br><code>setTimeoue(callback, timeout)</code> perform a callback function in timeout milliseconds</li><li><code>slice(begI, endI)</code> returns a shallow copy with an optional beginning and ending index</li><li><code>concat</code> joins two arrays together</li><li><code>some(cb)</code> returns <code>true</code> if the callback returns true for some element of the array, <code>false</code> otherwise.</li></ol><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">[<span class="hljs-string">&quot;sam&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-string">&quot;jacob&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-string">&quot;jess&quot;</span>].<span class="hljs-title function_">some</span>(<span class="hljs-function">(<span class="hljs-params">p</span>) =&gt;</span> p === <span class="hljs-string">&quot;jess&quot;</span>); <span class="hljs-comment">//true!</span><br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><ol start="7"><li><code>every(cb)</code> returns <code>true</code> if the callback returns true for every element of the array, <code>false</code> otherwise.</li></ol><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">[<span class="hljs-string">&quot;sam&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-string">&quot;jacob&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-string">&quot;jess&quot;</span>].<span class="hljs-title function_">every</span>(<span class="hljs-function">(<span class="hljs-params">p</span>) =&gt;</span> p === <span class="hljs-string">&quot;jess&quot;</span>); <span class="hljs-comment">// false!</span><br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><ol start="8"><li><code>reduce(cb, start)</code>: takes a 2-para callback (previous and current values) and s starting value</li></ol><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">[<span class="hljs-number">2</span>, <span class="hljs-number">4</span>, -<span class="hljs-number">1.1</span>, <span class="hljs-number">7.2</span>].<span class="hljs-title function_">reduce</span>(<span class="hljs-function">(<span class="hljs-params">prev, curr</span>) =&gt;</span> prev + curr, <span class="hljs-number">1.2</span>); <span class="hljs-comment">//13.3</span><br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><ol start="9"><li><code>...</code> Spread Operator <code>const newCats = [...cats, &quot;darcy&quot;]</code>, also with objects, are both shallow copies.</li></ol><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> fruits = [<span class="hljs-string">&quot;apple&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-string">&quot;banana&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-string">&quot;apple&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-string">&quot;banana&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-string">&quot;apple&quot;</span>];<br><span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> countObj = fruits.<span class="hljs-title function_">reduce</span>(<span class="hljs-function">(<span class="hljs-params">acc, curr</span>) =&gt;</span> &#123;<br>  <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> &#123;<br>    ...acc,<br>    [curr]: (acc[curr] || <span class="hljs-number">0</span>) + <span class="hljs-number">1</span>,<br>  &#125;;<br>&#125;, &#123;&#125;);<br><span class="hljs-variable language_">console</span>.<span class="hljs-title function_">log</span>(countObj); <span class="hljs-comment">//Output: &#123;apple: 3, banana: 2, orange: 1&#125;</span><br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><ol start="10"><li><code>??</code> Null Coalescing Operator: if left-hand is null or undefined, use right-hand.</li></ol><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> <span class="hljs-variable constant_">IS_ENABLED</span> = env.<span class="hljs-property">IS_ENABLED</span> ?? <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li></ol><h4 id="Copy"><a href="#Copy" class="headerlink" title="Copy"></a>Copy</h4><ol><li>Why: using spread operator, copying a template object, passing an object to function where we do not want the object to be modified, data safety</li><li><strong>Reference Copy</strong>: <code>let A = B</code>, change A will also change B, same mem area, any changes made through <code>a</code> will also reflect in <code>b</code>. <strong>x&#x3D;y, x&#x3D;z, x 会变成 z 的地址，y 不会改变</strong></li><li><strong>Shallow Copy</strong>: <code>let A = &#123;...B&#125;</code>, creates a new object, but just copies refs to those inner object, changes to inner objects in a shallow copy can affect the original, and vice versa.</li><li><strong>Deep copy</strong>, through <code>JSON.parse()</code>, totally seperate mem.</li></ol><h4 id="Bootstrap"><a href="#Bootstrap" class="headerlink" title="Bootstrap"></a>Bootstrap</h4><ol><li><strong>Layouts</strong>: Containers are the most basic element of layouts<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">&lt;div <span class="hljs-keyword">class</span> = <span class="hljs-string">&quot;container&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</span><br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure>containers will contain rows and columns to form a grid<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">&lt;div <span class="hljs-keyword">class</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;container&quot;</span>&gt;<br>  <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">div</span> <span class="hljs-attr">class</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;row&quot;</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">    <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">div</span> <span class="hljs-attr">class</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;col-*&quot;</span>&gt;</span><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">div</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">  <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">div</span>&gt;</span></span><br>&lt;/div&gt;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li><strong>Responsive Design</strong>: adapts content to a variety of devices and screen sizes.<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">&lt;div <span class="hljs-keyword">class</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;col-12 col-sm-6 col-md-4&quot;</span>&gt;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li><strong>Content</strong>: includes basic HTML elements, typography, code, images, tables, figures<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">&lt;img src=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;...&quot;</span> <span class="hljs-keyword">class</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;img-fluid&quot;</span>&gt;<br>&lt;table class=&quot;table&quot;&gt;<br>   &lt;thead class=&quot;thead-dark&quot;&gt;<br>      &lt;tr&gt;<br>      ...<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li><strong>Components</strong>: include all other visual&#x2F;interactive elements that make up the design, buttons, forms, navbar, tooltips, etc.</li><li><strong>Utilities</strong>: not elements themselves, but modify&#x2F;control other elements</li></ol><h3 id="Week-3"><a href="#Week-3" class="headerlink" title="Week 3"></a>Week 3</h3><h4 id="React"><a href="#React" class="headerlink" title="React"></a>React</h4><ol><li>React: also called ReactJS, a JS library for building user interfaces</li><li>Why use?<br>2.1 <code>innerHTML</code> is bad(XSS injection attack)<br>2.2 efficient DOM updating: no longer access elements via <code>document.</code>, which will friendly in interactive pages<br>2.3 declarative programming: every component is a function</li><li><strong>Component</strong>: every thing is a component, a <strong>function</strong>, inheriting <code>props</code> and maintaining an internal <code>state</code>. Re-render when its <code>props</code> and <code>state</code> changes, or its parent re-renders. The <code>return</code> is what is displayed for a component.<br><strong>The return of a functional component is what component renders.</strong><br><strong>Can be written without using JSX</strong></li></ol><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">function</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">App</span>(<span class="hljs-params"></span>) &#123;<br>   <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> (<br>      &lt;div&gt;<br>         <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Welcome</span> <span class="hljs-attr">person</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#x27;Charlie&#x27;</span>&gt;</span><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">Welcome</span>&gt;</span></span><br>   );<br>&#125;<br><span class="hljs-keyword">function</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">Welcome</span>(<span class="hljs-params">props</span>) &#123;<br>   <span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> [name, setName] = <span class="hljs-title function_">useState</span>(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;asd&quot;</span>)<br>   <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">h1</span>&gt;</span>Welcome, &#123;props.person&#125;<span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">h1</span>&gt;</span></span><br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><ol start="4"><li><strong><code>useState</code> Hook</strong>: used to maintain state. Takes an initial value as an argument. Returns a pair of the read-only state value and a mutator function. Always use the mutator function to modify state. Mutator happens asynchronously, use <code>useEffect</code>.</li><li><strong><code>useEffect</code> Hook</strong>: used to perform an action on component load or state chagne. Takes a callback function and an array of state dependencies as arguments. Listen for changes!<figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-title function_">useEffect</span>(<span class="hljs-function">() =&gt;</span> &#123;<br>  <span class="hljs-title function_">alert</span>(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;You changed your name to &quot;</span> + name);<br>&#125;, [name]);<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li></ol><h3 id="Week-4"><a href="#Week-4" class="headerlink" title="Week 4"></a>Week 4</h3><ol><li><p><strong>Set State</strong>:<br><code>SetNum(4)</code>: overwriting the value<br><code>setNum(n =&gt; n+1)</code>: update the existing value</p></li><li><p>React will <strong>keep old state when hot reloading</strong>, choose overwrite to avoid duplicates upon saving solution.</p><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">function</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">AllHurricanes</span>(<span class="hljs-params"></span>) &#123;<br>  <span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> [hurricanes, setHurricanes] = <span class="hljs-title function_">useState</span>([]);<br>  <span class="hljs-title function_">useEffect</span>(<span class="hljs-function">() =&gt;</span> &#123;<br>    <span class="hljs-title function_">fetch</span>(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;http://...&quot;</span>)<br>      .<span class="hljs-title function_">then</span>((res = res.<span class="hljs-title function_">json</span>()))<br>      .<span class="hljs-title function_">then</span>(<span class="hljs-function">(<span class="hljs-params">data</span>) =&gt;</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">setHurricanes</span>(data));<br>  &#125;);<br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li><p>Displaying Arrays of Data<br>3.1 <code>map</code> each piece of data to JSX</p><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">&#123;hurricanes.<span class="hljs-title function_">map</span>(<span class="hljs-function">(<span class="hljs-params">hurr</span>) =&gt;</span> (<br>  <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Hurricane</span></span></span><br><span class="hljs-tag"><span class="language-xml">    <span class="hljs-attr">name</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;hurr.name&#125;...</span> // &lt;<span class="hljs-attr">Hurricane</span> &#123;<span class="hljs-attr">...hurr</span>&#125;/&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">  /&gt;</span><br>))&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>3.2 <code>key</code>: <strong>speed up rendering</strong>, always use a unique key for the <strong>parent-most</strong> element rendered in a list, needs to be unique among siblings, should usually not be the index of the item</p><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">hurricanes.<span class="hljs-title function_">map</span>(<span class="hljs-function">(<span class="hljs-params">hurr</span>) =&gt;</span> <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Hurricane</span> <span class="hljs-attr">key</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;hurr.id&#125;</span> &#123;<span class="hljs-attr">...hurr</span>&#125; /&gt;</span></span>);<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li><p>Responsive Design<br>4.1 use <strong>react-bootstrap</strong><br>4.2 use <code>Container</code>, <code>Row</code>, <code>Col</code> components, <code>xs</code>, <code>sm</code>, <code>md</code>, <code>lg</code>, <code>xl</code>, <code>xxl</code> are props, <strong>包着 container 和 row, 一共 12，除以长度就是个数</strong></p><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">&lt;<span class="hljs-title class_">Col</span> xs=&#123;<span class="hljs-number">12</span>&#125; md=&#123;<span class="hljs-number">6</span>&#125; lg=&#123;<span class="hljs-number">3</span>&#125;&gt;&lt;/<span class="hljs-title class_">Col</span>&gt;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li><p><strong>Pagination</strong>: also available in <code>react-bootstrap</code>, handling large sums of data, use a state variable to track which page is active, use with <code>slice</code> to only show the item on the current page.</p></li><li><p><strong>Text input</strong>: HTML <code>input</code> tag, or <code>Form.Control</code> in React-bootstrap<br>6.1 in a controlled way useing its <code>value</code> and tracking <code>onChange</code> events<br>6.2 in an uncontrolled manner using <code>useRef</code></p></li></ol><h3 id="Week-5"><a href="#Week-5" class="headerlink" title="Week 5"></a>Week 5</h3><ol><li><strong>React Fragment</strong>:<br>A JSX component can only return one thing. Sometimes we use <code>&lt;&gt;&lt;/&gt;</code> instead of <code>&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</code>, which is a React Fragment, a virtual separator not represented in the real DOM</li></ol><h4 id="State-Management"><a href="#State-Management" class="headerlink" title="State Management"></a>State Management</h4><p>How do we talk back to our parent? How do siblings talk to each other?</p><ol><li>Passing <strong>Callbacks</strong></li><li><code>useContext</code>: a useful hook for managing state across web apps with large component hierarchies.<br>2.1 <strong>Create and export a context*</strong><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> <span class="hljs-title class_">MydataContext</span> = <span class="hljs-title function_">createContext</span>([]);<br><span class="hljs-keyword">export</span> <span class="hljs-keyword">default</span> <span class="hljs-title class_">MyDataContext</span>;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure>2.2 <strong>Provide the context with some value</strong><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">function</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">ParentComponent</span>(<span class="hljs-params"></span>) &#123;<br>   <span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> [data, setData] = <span class="hljs-title function_">useState</span>([<span class="hljs-string">&quot;...&quot;</span>, ...]);<br>   <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> (<br>      <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">MyDataContext.Provider</span> <span class="hljs-attr">value</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;data&#125;</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">         <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">SomeChildComponent</span> /&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">         <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">SomeOtherChildComponent</span> /&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">MyDataContext.Provider</span>&gt;</span></span><br>   )<br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure>2.3 <strong>Use the context in a child component</strong><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">function</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">SomeChildComponent</span>(<span class="hljs-params"></span>) &#123;<br>   <span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> data = <span class="hljs-title function_">useContext</span>(<span class="hljs-title class_">MyDataContext</span>);<br>   <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> (...);<br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li>Cookies, Session, Local: these exist in browser, persist even after a page refesh   <img src="../img/COMP571/cookies 1.png" width="500" height="200">1. **cookies**: can be set programmatically, but typically set by through a `Set-Cookie` header. `document.cookie='lang-en'`2. **Session**: set programmatically via `sessionStorage`, typically used with form data. `sessionStorage.setIrem('name', 'cole')`3. **Local**: set programmatically via localStorage, typucally used with long-lasting data. `localStorage.getItem('lastLogin')`</li><li><code>sessionStorage</code> &amp; <code>localStorage</code>:<br>4.1 <strong>only store strings</strong>, Use <code>JSON.parse</code> and <code>JSON.stringify</code><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-variable language_">sessionStorage</span>.<span class="hljs-title function_">setItem</span>(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;nums&quot;</span>, <span class="hljs-title class_">JSON</span>.<span class="hljs-title function_">stringify</span>([<span class="hljs-number">2</span>, <span class="hljs-number">6</span>, <span class="hljs-number">19</span>]));<br><span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> storedNums = <span class="hljs-title class_">JSON</span>.<span class="hljs-title function_">parse</span>(<span class="hljs-variable language_">sessionStorage</span>.<span class="hljs-title function_">getItem</span>(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;nums&quot;</span>));<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li>Third Party Libraries: Redux, Recoil, MobX, XState</li><li><strong>Persist long-term? Server-side storage with <code>PUT</code>, <code>POST</code>, <code>DELETE</code></strong></li></ol><h4 id="Navigation-w-x2F-React-Router"><a href="#Navigation-w-x2F-React-Router" class="headerlink" title="Navigation w&#x2F; React Router"></a>Navigation w&#x2F; React Router</h4><ol><li><p>Types of Routers:<br>1.1 <code>BrowserRouter</code>: typically<br>1.2 <code>MemoryRouter</code>: same as <code>BrowserRouter</code>, but the <strong>path is hidden</strong> from the browser in memory<br>1.3 <code>HashRouter</code>: support for older browsers<br>1.4 <code>StaticRouter</code>: used for server-side rendering<br>1.5 <code>NativeRouter</code>: not! use <code>react-navigation</code> instread!</p></li><li><p>Routing: using a <code>Router</code>, <code>Routes</code>, and <code>Route</code>!</p><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">&lt;<span class="hljs-title class_">BrowserRouter</span>&gt;<br>  <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Routes</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">    <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Route</span> <span class="hljs-attr">path</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;/&quot;</span> <span class="hljs-attr">element</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;</span>&lt;<span class="hljs-attr">Layout</span> /&gt;</span>&#125;&gt;</span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Route</span> <span class="hljs-attr">index</span> <span class="hljs-attr">element</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;</span>&lt;<span class="hljs-attr">Home</span> /&gt;</span>&#125; /&gt;</span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Route</span> <span class="hljs-attr">path</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;about-us&quot;</span> <span class="hljs-attr">element</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;</span>&lt;<span class="hljs-attr">AboutUs</span> /&gt;</span>&#125; /&gt;</span><br><span class="language-xml">    <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">Route</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">  <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">Routes</span>&gt;</span></span><br>&lt;/<span class="hljs-title class_">BrowserRouter</span>&gt;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li><p><strong>Browser <code>outlet</code></strong>: shows the component returned by the child route</p></li><li><p><code>useNavigate</code>: useful for programmatic navigation</p><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br><span class="line">11</span><br><span class="line">12</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">export</span> <span class="hljs-keyword">default</span> <span class="hljs-keyword">function</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">OtherInfo</span>(<span class="hljs-params"></span>) &#123;<br>  <span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> navigate = <span class="hljs-title function_">useNavigate</span>();<br>  <span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">handleclick</span> = (<span class="hljs-params"></span>) =&gt; &#123;<br>    <span class="hljs-title function_">navigate</span>(<span class="hljs-string">&quot; / home &quot;</span>);<br>  &#125;;<br>  <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> (<br>    <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">div</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">h2</span>&gt;</span>0ther Info!<span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">h2</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Button</span> <span class="hljs-attr">onClick</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;handleclick&#125;</span>&gt;</span>Back to Home<span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">Button</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">    <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">div</span>&gt;</span></span><br>  );<br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>navigation for a <code>BrowserRouter</code> is done via URLs</p><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js">&lt;&gt;<br>  <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Navbar</span> <span class="hljs-attr">bg</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;dark&quot;</span> <span class="hljs-attr">variant</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;dark &quot;</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">    <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Nav</span> <span class="hljs-attr">className</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;me-auto&quot;</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Nav.Link</span> <span class="hljs-attr">as</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;Link&#125;</span> <span class="hljs-attr">to</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;/ &quot;</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">        Home</span><br><span class="language-xml">      <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">Nav.Link</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">    <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">Nav</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">  <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">Navbar</span>&gt;</span></span><br>  <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">Outlet</span> /&gt;</span></span> <span class="hljs-comment">// shows the component returned by the child route</span><br>&lt;/&gt;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li></ol><h3 id="Week-6"><a href="#Week-6" class="headerlink" title="Week 6"></a>Week 6</h3><ol><li><p>CRUD operations:Create-&gt;POST, Read-&gt;GET, Update-&gt;PUT, Delete-&gt;DELETE</p></li><li><p>HTTP request:<strong>从上到下, [request Line(http&#x2F;1.1), request headers]&lt;-request message header, a blank line seperate header and body, request message body</strong></p><figure class="highlight plaintext"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs URL">https://www.example.com/packers/AaronRodgers/stats?all=true&amp;since=2010<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p><code>AaronRodgers</code> is a path parameter, <code>all</code>, <code>since</code> are query parameters<br>for JSON body, need an additional HTTP header, <strong><code>Content-Type: application/json</code>切记！</strong><br>100s: Informational, 200s: Successful, 300s: Redirection, 400s: Client Error, 500s: Server Error<br>200: OK, 304: Not Modified, 400: Bad Request, 401: Unauthorized, 404: Not Found, 409: Conflict, 413: Request Entity Too Large, 500: Internal Server Error</p></li><li><p><code>fetch</code>: POST, PUT, DELETE</p></li><li><p><strong>Handling Text Input</strong>: using HTML <code>input</code> tag or the React-Bootstrap <code>Form.Control</code> component.<br>4.1 in a controlled way using its <code>value</code> and tracking <code>onChange</code> events.<br>4.2 in an <strong>uncontrolled</strong> manner using <code>useRef</code></p><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> inputVal = <span class="hljs-title function_">useRef</span>();<br><span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> (<br>  <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">div</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">    <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">label</span> <span class="hljs-attr">htmlFor</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;myInput&quot;</span>&gt;</span>Type something here!<span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">label</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">    <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">input</span> <span class="hljs-attr">id</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&quot;myInput&quot;</span> <span class="hljs-attr">ref</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;inputVal&#125;</span>&gt;</span><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">input</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">  <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">div</span>&gt;</span></span><br>);<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>The value of a ref can be retrieved via its <code>current</code> property, <code>inputVal,current.value</code>.<br>React generally recommends controlled components. Controlled components can cause many re-renders, however uncontrolled components give you no control over the <code>onChange</code> property.<br>4.3 Best practise: if using react-bootstrap components, <strong>be sure each <code>Form.Control</code> has an <code>id</code> associated with the <code>htmlFor</code> of a <code>Form.label</code></strong>.</p></li><li><p><strong>Credentialed Requests</strong>: for requests for logging in, must include credentials. Return a session for the user, is typically stored in an http-only cookie, not accessible by JavaScript. Must explictly include credentials to every endpoint affecting authorization.</p><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-title function_">fetch</span>(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;https://example.com/api/submit&quot;</span>, &#123;<br>  <span class="hljs-attr">method</span>: <span class="hljs-string">&quot;POST&quot;</span>,<br>  <span class="hljs-attr">credentials</span>: <span class="hljs-string">&quot;include&quot;</span>,<br>&#125;);<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure></li><li><p>Memoization: Storing the result so you can use it next time instead of calculating the same thing again and again<br>6.1 <code>useCallback</code>: to <strong>memoize functions</strong></p><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">function</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">MyApp</span>(<span class="hljs-params"></span>) &#123;<br>  <span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">myComplicatedFunction</span> = (<span class="hljs-params"></span>) =&gt; &#123;...&#125;;<br>  <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">   <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">buttom</span> <span class="hljs-attr">onClick</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;myComplicatedFunction&#125;</span>&gt;</span>Click Me<span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">button</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">   <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/&gt;</span></span><br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>We create the function <code>myComplicatedFunction</code> on every render! (Like, if parent render, the children has to render too)</p><figure class="highlight js"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs js"><span class="hljs-keyword">function</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">MyApp</span>(<span class="hljs-params"></span>) &#123;<br>   <span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> myComplicatedFunction = <span class="hljs-title function_">useCallback</span>(<span class="hljs-function">() =&gt;</span> &#123;...&#125;, []);<br>   <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> <span class="language-xml"><span class="hljs-tag">&lt;&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">   <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;<span class="hljs-name">buttom</span> <span class="hljs-attr">onClick</span>=<span class="hljs-string">&#123;myComplicatedFunction&#125;</span>&gt;</span>Click Me<span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/<span class="hljs-name">button</span>&gt;</span></span><br><span class="language-xml">   <span class="hljs-tag">&lt;/&gt;</span></span><br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>Takes a callback function to <code>memorize</code> and an optinal list of dependencies. (when to re-‘memoize’)<br>6.2 <code>useMemo</code>: same as <code>useCallback</code>, except <strong>memorizes the value</strong> of a callback。<br>6.3 <code>memo</code>-ized Components: used for creating purely functional components. Given the same props, the function renders the same output.</p></li></ol><h3 id="Week-7"><a href="#Week-7" class="headerlink" title="Week 7"></a>Week 7</h3><ol><li><strong>Legacy React Apps</strong>: class-based and had “lifecycle methods”</li><li><strong>Reuse Logic</strong>: custom react hooks, (while custom components for re-use UI elements)</li><li><strong>React displays on the webpage using JSX, which transpiled into JS, CSS, and HTML, we deliver HTML, CSS, JS(not React!)</strong>.</li><li>Concerns in Production<ol><li>Reliability: Manual testing, automated testing(Jest, React Testing Library), Static analysis(TypeScript, ESLint)</li><li>Performance: “bundle size”, specifically?(perf, profiler), broadly?(Google Lighthouse)</li><li>Monitoring: Logging(not console.log, use Sentry, Datadog), Cloud tools(DownDetector, Cloud tools)</li><li>Business Value of Delivery: Money? new feature? Analysis method(A&#x2F;b test, customer survey) Commercial Tools(Pendo)</li></ol></li><li><strong>Node is the runtime engine, NPM is the package manager</strong></li><li><code>npm ls -all</code>, all vulnerabilities</li></ol><h2 id="Design-Thinking"><a href="#Design-Thinking" class="headerlink" title="Design Thinking"></a>Design Thinking</h2><h3 id="Week-1-DT"><a href="#Week-1-DT" class="headerlink" title="Week 1 DT"></a>Week 1 DT</h3><h4 id="six-phases-DT"><a href="#six-phases-DT" class="headerlink" title="six phases DT"></a>six phases DT</h4><ol><li>An <strong>approach</strong>: a hands-on, suer-centric approach to inovative problem solving<br>A <strong>process</strong>: six phases. Emphathiz, define, ideate, prototype, test, implement</li><li><strong>Emphathize</strong>: conduct research to develop an understanding of your users.<br>method: <strong>Think-Aloud</strong><br>1.1 <strong>Identify</strong> representative users. 1.2 Ask users to <strong>perform representative tasks</strong>. 1.3 <strong>Observe and record</strong> what they say and do, noting obstacles, pain points, and failures<br><strong>performing a contextual inqury with a representative user</strong><br>Write down notes to board? <strong>Adobe XD</strong></li><li><strong>Define</strong>: Combine all your data and derive where your users’ problems exist.<br>gather, analyze, recommend<br>method: <strong>affinity diagramming</strong>, organizing data into clusters based on “affinity”<br>2.1 Start with an initial set of categories 2.2 Sort notes into these categories 2.3 Add subcategories&#x2F;consolidate as needed 2.4 Present each category 2.5 Rank categories in severity, combining importance, prevalence, frequency</li><li><strong>Ideate</strong>: Generate a range of crazy, creative ideas. Both indicidually or collaboratively, focus on <strong>creative</strong>, <strong>fast-moving</strong>, <strong>collaboration</strong><br>indea creation -&gt; critiquing<ol><li>defer judgement, encourage wild ideas, build on the ideas of others, stay focused on the topic, one conversation at a time, be visual, go for quantity</li><li><strong>Conceptual design</strong>, an abstract characterization of the context, use, or experience with an envisioned design solution that highlights the main premise of the solution</li><li><strong>Sketching ideas</strong>: a sketach is a quick and rough drawing that gives a general outline of an idea. 画草图 low-fidelity, aided by annotations 质量不优先<br><strong>more effective than words, quick and inexpensice, disposable, can be plentiful</strong></li><li><strong>Storyboarding ideas</strong>: <strong>a sequence of visual frames</strong> that illustrate user interaction with the envisioned system, capturing social, environmental, and technical factors that shape user experience.</li></ol></li></ol><h3 id="Week-2-Visual-Design"><a href="#Week-2-Visual-Design" class="headerlink" title="Week 2 Visual Design"></a>Week 2 Visual Design</h3><ol><li><p>Elements of Design</p><ol><li><p>Elements of design provide us with the tools for design wheras the priciples of design dictate how these tools should be use.</p></li><li><p><strong>Space</strong>: the canvas on which visual elements are placed. <strong>Positive</strong>: where the subject is positioned&#x2F;<strong>Negative</strong>: the space surrounding the subject. Negative space can be used as positive.</p></li><li><p><strong>Line</strong>: the most primal design element that can divide space, call attention to, organize, and make up other elements</p></li><li><p><strong>Shape</strong>: Space outlined by a contour. <strong>Organic</strong>, 树叶子形状</p></li><li><p>Size: (scale), is the relative extent of the design elements such as shapes and lines</p></li><li><p><strong>Pattern</strong>: systematic duplication of other design elements such as shapes and lines.</p></li><li><p><strong>Texture</strong>: Tactile and visual quality of a shape make up of different colors, materials, and different structures.</p></li><li><p><strong>Value</strong>: The intensity in which a design element is expressed.<br>Visual Hierarchy: a visual design principle which designers use to show the importance of each page contents by manipulating these characters.</p></li></ol></li><li><p>Principles of Design</p><ol><li><strong>Focal Point</strong>: is where the design directs the attention of the viewer first.</li><li><strong>Contract</strong>: is the juxtaposition of design elements that strikingly differ from each other to guide user attention and action.</li><li><strong>Balance</strong>: the organization of design elements on a canvas to provide a sense of visual balance or imbalance. Can be achieved through <strong>symmetry</strong> or <strong>asymmetry</strong>.</li><li><strong>Movement</strong>: the organization of design elements in a way that suggests a particular flow on the canvas to direct the user’s attention.</li><li><strong>Rhythm</strong>: patterned use of design elements in a way that <strong>communicates movement or order</strong>.</li><li><strong>Perspective</strong>: creating a sense of horizon and movement along the <strong>depth</strong> axis of canvas.</li><li><strong>Unity</strong>: <strong>reflects the holistic consistency</strong> in the use of design elements.(一致性)</li></ol></li><li><p>Key Components for UX Design</p><ol><li><p><strong>type</strong>: <strong>printed letters</strong> and characters of language.(艺术字) paras: style, caps, weight</p><ol><li><strong>front</strong>: the style in which the type is created</li><li><strong>typeface</strong>: a front familty that includes fonts of different variations that follow the same style:<br>(1) Old style: have “serifs” at the tips of a glyph that taper closer to the tip<br>(2) Modern &amp; slab-serlif: have very thin or very thick serifs<br>(3) Sans-serif: lack the serif at the tips of the glyphs, and their strokes follow uniform weight(粗细一致)<br>(4) script: simulate cursive writing where glyphs connect with each other at the downstroke<br>(5) decorative: designed specifically to convey a particular context or elicit a particular feeling</li><li><strong>glypy</strong>: a particular character<br>Type alone can be used to achieve design priciples, such as hierachy and movement.<br>For good typography, become familiar with leading, traching, kerning, widows, orphans, rags, rivers.</li></ol></li><li><p>color: human visual perception of light reflecting from an object<br>creates emphasis-&gt;organizes content-&gt;evokes emotion<br>primary: G B Y, secondary(pruple, green, orange), tertiary</p></li><li><p>images: photographs, illustrations, 3D art… that convey rich information or context</p></li></ol></li></ol><h3 id="Week-3-Web-Design"><a href="#Week-3-Web-Design" class="headerlink" title="Week 3 Web Design"></a>Week 3 Web Design</h3><ol><li><p><strong>Designing for the Desktop</strong>，WIMP Paradigm: Windows, icons, menus, pointer</p><ol><li><strong>Windows</strong>: resizable containers of individual applications. <strong>Primary windows</strong> contain elements for the main functionality of the application(canvas), <strong>secondary</strong> support main windows through modal panes(can be docked, stacked, and floating) -&gt; <strong>dialogue box</strong><br><strong>Organization</strong>: windows can be organized in a way that overlaps several windows or tiles them across the screen<br><strong>Structures</strong>: windows bring together dedicated panes in different configurations</li><li><strong>Menus</strong>: menus list all the functions of an application, lists serve educational and reference purposes.<br>toolbars, palettes, sidebars, tooltips facilitate access to frequently used functions.<br>Tool Palettes provide advanced controls for a particular function rather than frequently accessed functions.</li><li><strong>Pointing</strong>: pointing on an application canvas enables a range of advanced capabilities for direct manipulation.</li></ol></li><li><p><strong>Designing for the web</strong></p><ol><li><strong>Desktop applications</strong>: <strong>dynamic</strong>, <strong>persistent</strong> screens and supporting components that enable users to perform complex tasks.<br><strong>Webpages</strong>: interconnected pages with aids that help users <strong>navigate</strong> and access a loarge body of content.</li><li>Web applications: single-page applications(<strong>SPAs</strong>) provide the functions of a desktop application on a webpage following the conventions of desktop applications.</li><li><strong>Primary Navigation aids</strong>页眉: take the form of menus&#x2F;menubars and reflect the major areas or sections of a website<br><strong>Secondary navigation</strong>页脚 aids provide comprehensice links to specific content on the site as fat navigation, left-hand navigation, footer navigation.</li><li><strong>Get home</strong>: breadcrumbs and hierarchical lists can get back to previous pages ot other pages.</li><li><strong>Orgamizing page content</strong>:<br>5.1 <strong>The fold</strong>: dividing line between the area that is visible when a page first loads and the remainder of the page.<br>5.2 <strong>fitting it all in</strong>: large volumes of content is either broken into discrete pages through pagination or incrementally loaded through infinite scroll.</li><li><strong>Search</strong>: an alternative to page navigation, provides users with listings of content based on a search query.<br><strong>Faceted search</strong> helps users narrow down a search once results are returned based on a simple query by providing functions to sort and filter the results.(过滤筛选结果)</li></ol></li><li><p><strong>Layout</strong>, arrangement of visual elements on a canvas</p><ol><li><strong>Creating a focal point</strong>: aka, center of visual interest, where the design directs the attention of the viewer first. Successful use locks attention to the focal point and gently guides it to its next destination.</li><li><strong>Following the golden proportion</strong></li><li><strong>Using the rule of thirds</strong>: an approximation of the golden ratio (easy and more flexible) 3*3 grid</li><li><strong>Effectively using grids</strong>: grids serve as a visual framework for organizing elements in an orderly and balanced fashion.</li><li><strong>Integrating type</strong>: the use of headlines or blocks of text to guide the user’s attention to messages.</li><li><strong>Placing imagery</strong>: the use of imagery to create a focal point or movement on the canvas. place on top, not bottom, direction should be toward next focal point, never flip images, do not interrupt headlines, do not wrap text around images.</li><li><strong>using negative space</strong>: balance</li><li><strong>Grouping using gestalt theory</strong>: visual perception principles that predict <strong>how users will perceive</strong> design elememnts. Proximity, Similarity, Continuity, Closure</li><li><strong>Creating visual hierarchy</strong>: using relative positioning and sizing to communicate what design elements are more important and should be looked at first.(文字辅助，应该先看什么，也可以从字体大小看出，先看大的字体)</li><li><strong>Exploiting visual scan patterns</strong>: designing layouts that exploiting common eye-scanning patterns， <strong>F-pattern</strong>, <strong>Z-pattern</strong></li><li><strong>Creating contrast and emphasis</strong>: using contrast and emphasis to establish visual hierarchy by manipulating features of design elements, including position, size, color, typographic.</li></ol></li><li><p><strong>Design patterns</strong><br>类似于一个成熟的框架 pros: reducing design time and effort, improving the quality of design solutions, establishing familiarity across systems, providing a baseline or state of the art<br>cons: Not every design problem will warrant a pattern, patterns may not exist for new design spaces</p></li></ol><h3 id="Week-4-Interaction-Design"><a href="#Week-4-Interaction-Design" class="headerlink" title="Week 4 Interaction Design"></a>Week 4 Interaction Design</h3><ol><li>defining behaviors for a system that engages the full spectrum of its user’s perception, cognition, and movements. Closer and more complex relationship to user behavior and context. (on navigation models)</li><li><strong>Five Dimensions</strong>: <strong>Words</strong>, <strong>Visual representaions</strong>, <strong>physical objects and space</strong>, <strong>time</strong>, <strong>behavior</strong></li><li><strong>Information architecture</strong>: the design of the organizing principle of an interactive systems<br>3.1 <strong>Show one single thing</strong>: supports a specific activity, eliminating other distractions. Content, supporting tools<br>3.2 <strong>Show a list or set of things</strong>: provides rows or grids of items of the same kind that provide links to components that focus on that item. applied hierarchically<br>3.3 <strong>provide tools to create a thing</strong>: supporting user creation of new contents, a canvas<br>3.4 <strong>Facilitate a task</strong>: provides collections of components or controls that help users perform specific actions-&gt;change setting<br>Combining structure: use some of above, SPAs</li><li><strong>Interaction Design Paradigm</strong>: an archetypal solution or an approach to solving design problems<ol><li>Implementation-<strong>centric</strong>: design maps directly to how system functions are implemented (飞机仪表), pros: easy to build, easy to debug &#x2F;&#x2F; cons: requires learning how the function work, require skills, cannot perform high-level actions</li><li><strong>Metahorical</strong>: following a real-world metaphor that users are expected to be familiar with, pros 1. can be applied at different level of abstraction 2. mixed metaphor bring together models from different domains in single design. -<strong>Global Metaphor</strong>, provides a single, overarching framework for all the petahors in the system(Magic Cap), pros: work well in expert interfaces &#x2F;&#x2F; cons: inability to sacle, lack of familiar read-world system for entirely new capabilities…</li><li><strong>Idiomatic</strong>: building dedicated highly expressive interaction capabilities that users must learn<br>Develop Idioms: 1. Primitives: atomic action(point, click) 2. Compounds: complex actions(double-click) 3. Idioms: high level elements(deleting test)</li></ol></li><li><strong>Affordances</strong> 亲和力: The perceived properties of a design elelment that give clues about how to interact with it. Enable users to intuively recognize actions that are possible with interface elements. Can be hidden and false.<br><strong>False affordances</strong>: an action that is perceived by the user but in face does not work as expected. 比如一个按钮啥也不干<br><strong>Hidden affordances</strong>: is not too obvious(下拉界面)<br><strong>perceptible affordances</strong>: an object’s characteristics imply an action,最容易感知又最符合逻辑的</li><li><strong>Principles of Navigation</strong>:<ol><li><strong>Wayfinding</strong>: user behavior where navigation across components follows a particular workflow or supports user goals. 比如箭头 <strong>1. signage, 2. Environmental clues 3. Maps(site maps)</strong></li><li><strong>Cost</strong>: the time and effort required by users to navigate between components. <strong>1. Minimize factors that increase cost of navigation: context switch, errors, delays 2. Minimize travel time by minimizing number of steps and context switches</strong></li><li><strong>aids</strong>: design elements that aid users in navigating through content. types: <strong>1. Global navigation aids, menus, tabs, sidebars 2. Utility navigation aids, sign in, help, print 3. Associative&#x2F;in-line navigation aids, related links</strong></li></ol></li><li><strong>Navigation models</strong>: commonly used patterns of navigation through interactive applications<ol><li><strong>Hub &amp; spoke</strong>: involves a central hub, a home screen, that provides transitions to and from serveral specialized components. (一个主屏幕，访问其他)</li><li><strong>fully connected</strong>: a central component&#x2F;page is connected all other components that are also linked to each other. 两个屏幕的时候开销最小</li><li><strong>Multi-level</strong>: involves main components that are fully connected with each other and sub-components that are only connected among themselves. (子图)</li><li><strong>stepwise</strong>: follows a sequential or branching navigation that represents step-by&#x3D;step process, e.g. checking out on an e-commerce site.</li><li><strong>Pyramid</strong>: similar to the stepwise, but at each step, the user can navigate to the hub and back</li><li><strong>Pan and zoom</strong>: provides users with the ability to continuously navigate across a large space of content, map, list, written document</li><li><strong>Flat navigation</strong>: involves a central workspace that is always visible and functions that do not require context switches or navigation. Adobe 很多工具栏</li><li><strong>Modal panel</strong>: follows the flat navigation model except for modal dialogs that are temporarily overlaid on the cancas to help the user perform specific functions.</li><li><strong>Clear entry points</strong>: complex applications invlove navigational models with clear entry points that guide the user to frequently used or temporary functions without having to go through the hierarchical structure or a step-by-step process.</li><li><strong>Bookmarks</strong>: allow users to conveniently navigate to a point of his choice, anytime he wants, even if its deep inside a navigational structure. These give people a way to avoid traversing many links to get ot a desired page or state.</li><li><strong>Escape hatch</strong>: provides users with the ability to go back to the main component&#x2F;page in a complex structure without having to trace steps back.(可以方便返回主页)</li></ol></li></ol><h3 id="Week-5-Accessible-Design"><a href="#Week-5-Accessible-Design" class="headerlink" title="Week 5 Accessible Design"></a>Week 5 Accessible Design</h3><ol><li><strong>Usability</strong>: The effectiveness, efficiency, and satisfaction with which a specified set of users can achieve a specified set of tasks in a particular environment.</li><li><strong>Disability</strong>: <strong>impairment</strong>, <strong>activity limitation</strong>, <strong>participation restrictions</strong>.</li><li>Impairment:<ol><li><strong>Sensory impairment</strong>: Involves impairment in <strong>one or more senses</strong>, loss of vision or hearing.</li><li><strong>Physical impairment</strong>: Involves loss of function to <strong>one or more parts of the body</strong>, e.g., congenitally or a!er stroke or spinal-cord injury.</li><li><strong>Cognitive impairment</strong>: ncludes cognitive deficits, such as learning<br>impairment or <strong>loss of memory&#x2F;cognitive</strong> function due to aging or conditions such as Alzheimer’s disease.</li></ol></li><li><strong>Common impairment</strong> :<ol><li><strong>visual</strong>: Impairments in vision, including low vision, blindness, and color blindness.</li><li><strong>motor, mobility</strong>: Muscular or skeletal impairments in the hands or arms that affect user input as well as impairments that affect mobility, where users are in a wheelchair or bedridden.</li><li><strong>auditory</strong>: Deficits that affect hearing at different levels of severity, including deafness.</li><li><strong>serzures</strong>: Neurological impairments, such as photosensitive epilepsy, that result in sensitivity to light, motion, and flickering on screen, which might trigger seizures.</li><li><strong>cognitive, learning</strong>: Congenital, developmental, and traumatic<br>(e.g., traumatic brain injury) conditions that result in cognitive or learning challenges.</li></ol></li><li>Types of impairment: permanent, temporary, situational</li><li><strong>Accessibility</strong>: The usability of a product, service, environment, or facility by people with the widest range of capabilities.</li><li>Two way to address accessibility: accessible design, assistive tech.</li><li><strong>Accessible Design</strong>:<ol><li><strong>Medical Model</strong>: personal attribute, any restriction or loakc of ability to perform an acticity</li><li><strong>Social Model</strong>: context dependent, people are disabled by barriers in society, not by their impairment or difference, <strong>context dependent</strong>.<br><strong>Ability + Context</strong> &#x3D; <strong>disability</strong></li></ol></li><li><strong>Universal Design</strong>: The design of products and environments to be usable by all people, to the greatest extent possible, without the need for adaptation or specialized design.</li><li>UD Principle:<ol><li><strong>Equitable use</strong>: The design is useful and marketable to people with diverse abilities.</li><li><strong>Flexibility in use</strong>: accommodates a wide range of individual preferences and abilities.</li><li><strong>Simple and Intuitive use</strong>: Use of the design is easy to understand, regardless of the user’s experience, knowledge, language skills, or current concentration level.</li><li><strong>Perceptibale information</strong>: communicates necessary information effectively to the user, regardless of ambient conditions or the user’s sensory abilities.</li><li><strong>Tolerance for Error</strong>: minimizes hazards and the adverse consequences of accidental or unintended actions.</li><li><strong>Low Physical Effort</strong>: can be used efficiently and comfortably and with a minimum of fatigue.</li><li><strong>Size and Space for Approach and use</strong>: Appropriate size and space is provided for approach, reach, manipulation, and use regardless of user’s body size, posture, or mobility.</li></ol></li><li><strong>UD Assistive Tech</strong>: specialized tools that close accessibility gaps<br>Screen readers, screen magnification, text readers, braille for the web, alternative input devices, head&#x2F;mouth wands&#x2F;pointers, motion&#x2F;eye tracking, single-switch, speech input, alternative &amp; Augmentative communication</li><li>The expert-review-based type of usability evaluation is best described as testing with users who represent the target population of the design solution. FAAAAALSE</li></ol>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Courses</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>course notes</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>COMP 320</title>
    <link href="/2023/09/28/COMP320/"/>
    <url>/2023/09/28/COMP320/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>（我也不知道为什么要做 COMP 320 的 Notes，这感觉就像在我这个年纪学习如何上厕所）</p><h2 id="Repoducibility"><a href="#Repoducibility" class="headerlink" title="Repoducibility"></a>Repoducibility</h2><ol><li>Each process owns address space. (one huge list)</li><li>Multiple lists start at different address in address space; normally, append is faster than pop, since pop need to move all next items forward 4 bytes. (? Really)</li><li>Use ASCII to store strings, use specific ISA to store codes.</li><li>A CPU can only run programs that use instructions it understands, interpreters&#x2F;compiler make it sense to run the same code on different machines.</li><li>OS: allocate and abstract resources</li><li>commits: explicit snapshots&#x2F;checkpoints; explicit commit messages (who, what, when, why)</li><li>Tag “good” commits to create releases.</li><li>git:<br>8.1 HEAD: wherever you currently are (one and only one)<br>8.2 tag: label tied to a specific commit number<br>8.3 branch: label tied to end of chain (moves upon new commits)<br>8.4 detached HEAD: refers to a situation where the HEAD pointer (which usually points to a branch reference) directly points to a specific commit, rather than pointing to the latest commit of a branch. In simpler terms, when you’re working in a normal branch (say, “master” or “main”), the HEAD points to the name of that branch, and that branch name points to the latest commit. Any new commits you make will advance the branch to point to the newer commit, and HEAD follows along because it’s pointing to the branch name.</li><li><code>time.time()</code> returns seconds since 1970</li></ol><h2 id="Performance"><a href="#Performance" class="headerlink" title="Performance"></a>Performance</h2><ol><li>Affect performance<br>1.1: Speed of CPU<br>1.2: Speed of Interpretation<br>1.3: Algorithm<br>1.4: Input size</li><li>Complexity analysis only cares about “big” inputs.<br><img src="/../img/COMP320/COMP320%20Performance%201.jpg"></li><li>A step is any unit of work with boudned execution time. (“bounded” does not mean “fixed”)</li><li>Big O:<br>4.1 Goal: categorize functions by how fast they grow. Do not care about scale. Do not care about small inputs. Care about shape of the curve. Find some multiple of a general function that is an upper bound<br><img src="/../img/COMP320/COMP320%20Performance%202.jpg"><br><img src="/../img/COMP320/COMP320%20Performance%203.jpg"></li><li>O(1): x &#x3D; L[0], x &#x3D; len(L), L.append(x), L.pop(-1)<br>O(N): L.insert(0, x), L.pop(0), x &#x3D; max(L), L2.extend(L1), x &#x3D; sum(L), found &#x3D; X in L</li><li><img src="/../img/COMP320/COMP320%20Performance%204.jpg"></li></ol><h2 id="Object-Oriented-Programming"><a href="#Object-Oriented-Programming" class="headerlink" title="Object Oriented Programming"></a>Object Oriented Programming</h2><ol><li><code>Dog.speak(fido, 5)</code>, not an example of type-based dispatch.</li><li>Special Methods: (implicity)<br>2.1 Not all <code>__some__</code> is special methods<br>2.2 <code>__str__</code>, <code>__repr__</code>, control how an object looks when we print it or see it in <code>Out[N]</code>.<br>2.3 <code>__repr_html__</code>, generate HTML to create more visual representaitons of objects in Jupyter.<br>2.5 <code>__eq__</code>, <code>__lt__</code>, define how &#x3D;&#x3D; behaves for two different objects, sorting(<code>__lt__</code>)<br>2.6 <code>__len__</code>, <code>__getitem__</code>, build our own sequences that we <code>index</code>, <code>slice</code>, and <code>loop</code> over.<br>2.7 <code>__enter__</code>, <code>__exit__</code>, context managers, (like automatically close file)</li><li>Inheritance: method inheritance, method resolution order, overriding methods, constructor, calling overidden methods, abstrace base classes</li><li>Every class in python implicitly inherits from the build-in <code>object</code> class if no other explicitly specified.</li></ol><h2 id="Web"><a href="#Web" class="headerlink" title="Web"></a>Web</h2><ol><li><p><code>WebDriver.get(u)</code> loads the web page with URL. <code>WebDriver.find_element(a, b)</code> returns the first WebElement which has attribute <code>a</code> being <code>b</code>. <code>WebDriver.find_elements(a, b)</code> returns a list of WebElements. <code>a</code> can be <code>id</code>: unique, <code>name</code>: mulitple elements can have the same name, <code>tag name</code>: by its tag. Get all the links element: <code>driver.find_elements(&quot;tag name&quot;, &quot;a&quot;)</code>, <code>tanle</code> 是 table 不是 td, 获取 link 以后获得内部的 attibute, <code>.get_attribute(&quot;attribute_name&quot;)</code></p></li><li><p>Send value to a variable <code>text</code> as input, <code>text.send_keys(&quot;2023)</code></p></li><li><p><code>ol</code>, <code>ul</code>, ordered or unordered list, <code>select</code>, drop-down list</p></li><li><p>Tables can be scraped by <code>find_element(&quot;tag name&quot;, &quot;table&quot;)</code> and iterate over <code>find_elements(&quot;tag name&quot;, &quot;tr&quot;)</code> and <code>find_elements(&quot;tag name&quot;, &quot;td&quot;)</code><br><code>i</code>th cell of <code>j</code> th row? <code>element.find_elements(&quot;tag name&quot;, &quot;tr&quot;)[i - 1].find_elements(&quot;tag name&quot;, &quot;td&quot;)[j - 1].text</code>. 第一个元素可以忽略 index</p></li><li><p>对于已经获得的<code>element</code>, 通过<code>.attribute</code>访问内部元素，对于<code>text</code>内容, <code>element.text</code>,比如 <code>&lt;a href=&quot;page.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;link&lt;\a&gt;</code> 获取<code>link</code>, <code>elememt.clear</code>清空</p></li><li><p>for <code>static</code> pages (without JavaScript modifications), <code>pandas.read_html</code> can return a list of DataFrames, one for each table, on the web page.</p></li><li><p><code>WebDriver.save_screenshot(&quot;file.png)</code> saves a screenshot of the web page to a file with name <code>file.png</code>. Firefox has the option to take screenshot of the full page using <code>WebDriver.save_full_screenshot(&quot;file.png&quot;)</code>. a screenshot of a specific element can be save using <code>WebElement.screenshot(&quot;file.png&quot;)</code>.</p></li><li><p>Polling:</p><ol><li>Use <code>time.sleep(s)</code> to wait s seconds, and use it inside a while loop to wait for an event to happen, before accessing or interacting with the updated elements.</li><li>Avoid infinite loop.</li><li><code>selenium.webdriver.support</code> has implicit and explicit waits, so that the driver keeps polling until a certain condition is met or a certain time has passed.</li></ol></li><li><p>Robots Exclusion:</p><ol><li>Some websites disallow web crawling. The rules are specified in a <code>robots.txt</code>.</li><li><code>urllib.robotparser</code> can be used to check whether a website allows scraping</li><li><code>RobotFileParser.can_fetch(useragent, url)</code> returns True if the useragent (for example, “*“) is allowed to fetch url</li></ol></li><li><p>Access Links:</p><ol><li><code>WebDriver.find_elements(&quot;tag_name&quot;, &quot;a&quot;)</code> finds all the hyperlinks on the page.</li><li>Use <code>url = WebElement.get_attribute(&quot;href&quot;)</code> to get the URL of the hyperlink, then use <code>WebDriver.get(url)</code> to load that page.</li></ol></li><li><p>Infinite Graph Search:</p><ol><li>If the pages are nodes, and links on one page to another page are edges, the digraph formed by pages will possibly have infinite depth and may contain cycles.</li><li>To find a specific (goal) page, or to discover reachable pages from the initial page, breadth first search should be used (since depth first search may not terminate on trees with infinite depth).</li><li>Since there are cycles, a list of visited pages should be kept.</li></ol></li><li><p>Search Heuristics:</p><ol><li>Searching the nodes in the order according to the heuristic is called best first greedy search. (GBS) 取 h 最小</li><li>A search, estimate of how close the current node is to the goal in the search tree. the current distance from the initial node plus the heuristic</li><li>A heuristic that always underestimates the true distance is called an admissible heuristic. A*</li></ol></li><li><p>Priority Queue:</p><ol><li>For GBS search, use a Priority Queue with the priority based on the heuristic.</li><li>For A search, use a Priority Queue with the priority based on current distance plus the heuristic.</li></ol></li><li><p>Give an example of a goal node that is reachable (finite edges away) from the initial node, but the following method cannot find the goal node. Assume the nodes are ${G, 0, 1, 2, …}$ where 0 is the initial node and is the goal node, and each node has finite number of children.<br>BFS, A: impossible, 必定可以找到<br>DFS，GBS：优先度高的那各分支无穷远</p></li><li><p>Flask:</p><ol><li>Flask is a simpler web framework of Django. Django is a more popular package.</li><li>Flask will be used to create or modify web pages. It can be useful for collecting visitor data when interacting with the web pages and displaying them on the web pages.</li><li><code>app = flask.Flask(...)</code>, root url: <code>@app.route(&quot;/&quot;)</code>, other: <code>@app.route(&quot;/abc&quot;)</code>, run: <code>app.run(host=&quot;0.0.0.0&quot;, debug=False, threaded=False)</code></li><li>Binding functions:<figure class="highlight python"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs python"><span class="hljs-meta">@app.route(<span class="hljs-params"><span class="hljs-string">&quot;/index&quot;</span></span>)</span><br><span class="hljs-keyword">def</span> <span class="hljs-title function_">index</span>()<br>   <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> <span class="hljs-string">&quot;Hello World!&quot;</span><br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure>binds the index function to the page IP address&#x2F;index, meaning it will display a web page that says “Hello World”. “Hello World” can be replaced by any text or HTML string. HTML string can be read from existing HTML files then modified. It can also be generated by packages such as pandas. <code>pandas.read_csv(&quot;data.csv&quot;).to_html()</code></li></ol></li><li><p>Process query string inside a flask application: <code>flask.request.args</code></p></li><li><p>Binding Multiple Path:</p><ol><li>To bind multiple paths, variable rules can be added, <code>@app.route(&quot;/index/&lt;x&gt;&quot;) def index(x) return f&quot;Hello &#123;x&#125;&quot;</code> will display a web page that says “Hello World” when the path IP address&#x2F;index&#x2F;World is used.</li><li><code>&lt;int:x&gt;</code> for int, <code>&lt;float:x&gt;</code> for float, <code>&lt;path:x&gt;</code> for string but allows <code>/</code></li></ol></li><li><p>Redirectling Pages:</p><ol><li><code>return flask.redirect(url)</code> redirects the current path to another with URL url</li><li><code>return flask.redirect(flask.url_for(&quot;index&quot;))</code> redirects the current path to another which binds to the function <code>index()</code></li><li><code>return flask.redirect(flask.url_for(&quot;index&quot;, x = &quot;World&quot;))</code> redirects the current path to another which binds to the <code>function index(&quot;World&quot;)</code></li></ol></li><li><p>Collecting Vistor Information:</p><ol><li><code>flask.request.remote_addr</code> can be used to find the remote IP address of the visitor -&gt; sercive provider, location</li><li><code>flask.request.user_agent.string</code> can be used to find the user agent of the visitor. -&gt; browser, os, device information</li></ol></li><li><p>Rate Limiting:</p><ol><li>Prevent web scraping, 429, Too Many Requests</li><li>In this case, the visitor’s IP address and visit time can be stored in a list: in case the next visit time is too close to the previous one, the visitor can be redirected to another page, or more commonly, responded with a error message, for example, <code>return flask.Response(&quot;...&quot;, status = 429, headers = &#123;&quot;Retry-After&quot;: &quot;60&quot;&#125;)</code> tells the visitor to retry after 60 seconds.</li><li>100s: Informational, 200s: Successful, 300s: Redirection, 400s: Client Error, 500s: Server Error 200: OK, 304: Not Modified, 400: Bad Request, 401: Unauthorized, 404: Not Found, 409: Conflict, 413: Request Entity Too Large, 500: Internal Server Error， 405：Method not allowed(比如尝试 get 只允许 Put 的), 501: Not implemented(没有这个函数)</li></ol></li><li><p>AB Testing:</p><ol><li>Two or more versions of the same page can be displayed to the visitor randomly to compare which one is better. The two versions are called control (version A) and treatment (version B) in statistics.</li><li>The comparison is often based on click-through rates (CTR), <strong>metric</strong>, which is computed as the number of clicks on a specific link on the page divided by the number of times the page is displayed to the visitor.</li><li>CTR is also used for advertisement, computed as the number of clicks on the ad divided by the number of times the ad is shown to the visitor.</li><li>Having a large sample size will have small p-value.</li><li>When introduce a new version “B”, might be terrible but still want to evaluate it, start with “0” of B, then slowly increase</li><li><code>fisher_exact()</code> 算出来的，大于 thresold 就两者没有显著差异</li></ol></li><li><p>Displaying Pages:</p><ol><li>The choice of which page to display can be random, for example, <code>if random.random() &lt; 0.5: return &quot;Version A&quot; else return &quot;Version B&quot;</code></li><li>It can also be displayed in a fixed ordering, for example, suppose count is a global variable to keep track of the number of visitors, then <code>if count % 2 == 0: return &quot;Version A&quot; else return &quot;Version B&quot; count = count + 1</code> would alternate between the two versions.</li></ol></li><li><p>Tracking Visitors:</p><ol><li>IP address or user agent information can be used to figure out which version of the page is displayed to which visitors</li><li>Cookies can be used too, use <code>flask.request.cookies.get(key, default)</code> to get a cookie (and returns default if no such cookies exist), and <code>flask.Response.set_cookie(key, value)</code> to set a cookie. Cookies are stored on the visitors’ computer as text files.</li><li>Query strings can be used to figure out which version of a page the visitor came from, it is the string after “?” at the end of a URL</li></ol></li><li><p>Query Strings:</p><ol><li><code>&quot;index?x=1&amp;y=2&quot;</code> is a URL specifying the path “index” with the query string <code>x=1 and y=2</code>. Use <code>flask.request.args</code> to get a dictionary of key-value pairs of the query string.</li><li>To perform AB testing of a page with two versions, both contain a link to index: on version A, the URL can be <code>&lt;a href=&quot;index?from=A&quot;&gt;Link&lt;\a&gt;</code>, and on version B, the same URL can be <code>&lt;a href=&quot;index?from=B&quot;&gt;Link&lt;\a&gt;</code>. If version A URL is used, <code>request.args[&quot;from&quot;]</code> would be “A” and if version B URL is used <code>request.args[&quot;from&quot;]</code> would be “B”</li></ol></li><li><p>Two Armed Bandit Example: The pages represented by boxes have fixed but possibly different average values between 0 and 1. Click on one of them to view a random realization of the value from the box (i.e. a random number from a distribution with the fixed average). The goal is to maximize the total value (or minimize the regret) given a fixed number of clicks. Which box has the largest mean reward? 类似于大数定理，经验平均数在 N 无穷大的时候趋近于真实平均</p></li><li><p>Multi-Armed Bandit:</p><ol><li>This design can lead to a large “regret”, for example, if displaying bad version is costly. In other settings such as drug or vaccine trials and stock selection, experimenting with bad alternatives can be costly.</li><li>The problem of optimal experimentation vs exploitation is studied in reinforcement learning as the multi-armed bandit problem</li></ol></li><li><p>Upper Confidence Bound:</p><ol><li>a no-regret algorithm that minimizes the loss from experimentation</li><li>After every version is displayed once, the algorithm keeps track of the average value (for example click-through rate) from each version, say $\hat{\mu}<em>{A}$, $\hat{\mu}</em>{B}$ and computes the UCBs $\hat{\mu}<em>{A} + c\sqrt{\frac{2log(n)}{n</em>{A}}}$ and $\hat{\mu}<em>{B} + c\sqrt{\frac{2log(n)}{n</em>{B}}}$, where $n$ is the total number of visitors, $n_{A}$ is the number of visitors of version A, $n_{B}$ is the number of visitors of version B, and $c$ is a constant, and always picks the version with a higher UCB.</li></ol></li><li><p>Live Plots on Flask Sites:</p><ol><li>A function that returns an image response can be used for <code>@app.route(&quot;/plot.png&quot;)</code> or <code>@app.route(&quot;/plot.svg&quot;)</code>. SVG: Scalable Vector Graphics, represented by a list of geometric shapes such as points, lines, curves</li><li>An image response can be created using <code>flask.Response(image, headers=&#123;&quot;Content-Type&quot;: &quot;image/png&quot;&#125;)</code> or <code>flask.Response(image, headers=&#123;&quot;Content-Type&quot;: &quot;image/svg+xml&quot;&#125;)</code>, where the image is a bytes object and can be obtained using <code>io.BytesIO.getvalue()</code> where <code>io.BytesIO</code> creates a “fake” file to store the image.</li><li>On the web page, display the image as <code>&lt;img src=&quot;plot.png&quot;&gt;</code> or <code>&lt;img src=&quot;plot.svg&quot;&gt;</code></li></ol></li><li><p>Plotting Low Dimensional Data Sets:</p><ol><li>One to three dimensional data items can be directly plotted as points (positions) in a 2D or 3D plot.</li><li>For data items with more than three dimensions (“dimensions” will be called “features” in machine learning), visualizing them effectively could help with exploring patterns in the dataset. Summary statistics such as mean, variance, covariance etc might not be sufficient to find patterns in the dataset.</li><li>For item dimensions that are discrete (categorical), plotting them as positions may not be ideal since positions imply ordering, and the categories may not have an ordering.</li></ol></li></ol><table><thead><tr><th>Encoding</th><th>Continuous</th><th>Ordinal 顺序？</th><th>Discrete (Categorical)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Position</td><td>Yes</td><td>Yes</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>Size</td><td>Yes</td><td>Yes</td><td>No</td></tr><tr><td>Shape</td><td>No</td><td>No</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>Value</td><td>Yes</td><td>Yes</td><td>No</td></tr><tr><td>Color</td><td>No</td><td>No</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>Orientation</td><td>Yes</td><td>Yes</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>Texture</td><td>No</td><td>No</td><td>Yes</td></tr></tbody></table><ol start="27"><li>Seaborn plots:<ol><li>one of the data visualization libraries that can make plots for exploring the datasets with a few dimension.</li><li>Suppose the columns are indexed by $c1, c2, …$, then <code>seaborn.relplot(data = ..., x = &quot;c1&quot;, y = &quot;c2&quot;, hue = &quot;c3&quot;, size = &quot;c4&quot;, style = &quot;c5&quot;</code>visualizes the relationship between the columns by encoding c1 by x-position, c2 by y-position, c3 by color hue if the feature is discrete, and by color value if it is continuous, c4 by size, c5 by shape (for example, o’s and x’s for points, solid and dotted for lines) if the feature is discrete.</li></ol></li><li>Multiple Plots of Seaborn:<ol><li>For discrete dimensions with a small numbers of categories, multiple plots can be made, one for each category.</li><li><code>seaborn.relplot(data = ..., ..., col = &quot;c6&quot;, row = &quot;c7&quot;)</code> produces multiple columns of plots one for each category of c6, and multiple rows of plots one for each category of c7.</li><li><code>seaborn.pairplot</code> produces a scatter plot for each pair of columns (features) which could be useful for exploring relationships between pairs of continuous features too. 查找两个 feature 之间的关系</li><li>Chernoff Face: used to display small low dimensional datasets. The shape, size, placement and orientation of eyeys, ears, mouth and nose are visual encodings.</li></ol></li><li>Plotting High Dimensional Data Sets<ol><li>To figure out the most important dimensions, which are not necessarily one of the original dimensions, unsupervised machine learning techniques can be used. 降维 PCA</li></ol></li></ol><h2 id="Graph"><a href="#Graph" class="headerlink" title="Graph"></a>Graph</h2><ol><li>Layouts:<ol><li><strong>Circular layout</strong> and <strong>arc (chord) layout</strong> are simple for the computer, but difficult for humans to understand the shape of the graph.</li><li><strong>Force-Directed Placement (FDP)</strong> treats nodes as points and edges as springs and tries to minimize energy. It is also called spring model layout.</li></ol></li><li>Tree Diagrams:<ol><li>Trees are special graphs for which each node has one parent, and there are more ways to visualize a tree</li><li>Can be plotted “manully” using <code>matplotlib</code></li></ol></li><li>Plotting Primitives: 基本图形<ol><li><code>matplotlib.patches</code> contain primitive geometries such as <code>Circle</code>, <code>Ellipse</code>, <code>Polygon</code>, <code>Rectangle</code>, <code>RegularPolygon</code> and <code>ConnectionPatch</code>, <code>PathPatch</code>, <code>FancyArrowPatch</code></li><li><code>matplotlib.text</code> can be used to draw text; it can render math equations using TeX too</li></ol></li><li>Plotting Graphs:<ol><li>画点: A node (indexed i) at $(x,y)$ can be represented by a closed shape such as a circle with radius $r$, for example, <code>matplotlib.patches.Circle((x, y), r)</code>, and <code>matplotlib.text(x, y, &quot;i&quot;)</code>.</li><li>画边: An edge from a node at $(x_1, y_1)$ to a node at $(x_2, y_2)$ can be represented by a path (line or curve, with or without arrow), for example, <code>matplotlib.patches.FancyArrowPatch((x1, y1), (x2, y2))</code>, or if the nodes are on different subplots with axes <code>ax[0]</code>, <code>ax[1]</code>, <code>matplotlib.patches.ConnectionPath((x1, y1), (x2, y2), &quot;data&quot;, axesA = ax[0], axesB = ax[1])</code></li><li>To specify the layout of a graph, a list of positions of the nodes are required (sometimes parameters for the curve of the edges need to be specified too).</li></ol></li><li>Ways to Specify Curves:<ol><li>A curve (with arrow) from $(x_1, y_1)$ to $(x_2, y_2)$ can be specified by the (1) out-angle and in-angle, (2) curvature of the curve, (3) Bezier control points</li><li><code>FancyArrowPatch((x1, y1), (x2, y2), connectionstyle=ConnectionStyle.Angle3(angleA = a, angleB = b))</code> plots a quadratic Bezier curve starting from $(x_1, y_1)$ going out at an angle $a$ and going in at an angle $b$ to $(x_2, y_2)$.</li><li><code>FancyArrowPatch((x1, y1), (x2, y2), connectionstyle=ConnectionStyle.Arc3(rad = r))</code> plots a quadratic Bezier curve from $(x_1, y_1)$ to $(x_2, y_2)$ that arcs towards a point at distance r times the length of the line from the line connecting $(x_1, y_1)$ and $(x_2, y_2)$.</li></ol></li><li>Bezier Curves:<ol><li>Beizer curves are smooth curves specified by control points that may or may not be on the curves themselves. The curve connects the first control point and the last control point. The vectors from the first control point to the second control point, and from the last control point to the second-to-last control point, are <strong>tangent vectors</strong> to the curve.</li><li>The curves can be constructed by recursively interpolating the line segments between the control points.</li><li><code>PathPatch(Path([(x1, y1), (x2, y2), (x3, y3)], [Path.MOVETO, Path.CURVE3, Path.CURVE3]))</code> draws a Bezier curve from $(x_1, y_1)$ to $(x_3, y_3)$ with a control point $(x_2, y_2)$.</li></ol></li><li>Coordinate Systems:<ol><li>There are four main coordinate systems: <strong>data</strong>, <strong>axes</strong>, <strong>figure</strong>, and <strong>display</strong></li><li>The primitive geometries can be specified using any of them by specifying the <code>transform</code> argument, for example for a figure <code>fig</code> and axis <code>ax</code>, <code>Circle((x, y), r, transform = ax.transData)</code>, <code>Circle((x, y), r, transform = ax.transAxes)</code>, <code>Circle((x, y), r, transform = fig.transFigure)</code>, or <code>Circle((x, y), r, transform = fig.dpi_scale_trans)</code>.</li><li>How to draw a quadratic Bezier curve with control points (0, 0), (1, 0), (1, 1)?<br>This curve has the same shape as the curve drawn in the “Curve Example”: in particular, the start angle is 0 degrees (measured from the positive x-axis direction) and the end angle is 270 degrees or -90 degrees, and the distance of the line segment connecting the midpoint between (0, 0) and (1, 1) (which is (1&#x2F;2, 1&#x2F;2)) and the middle control point (which is (1, 0)) is half of the length of the line segment connecting (0, 0) and (1, 1), or $\sqrt{(1-\frac{1}{1})^2 + (0-\frac{1}{2})^2} &#x3D; \frac{1}{2}\sqrt{(1-0)^2+(1-0)^2}$<br>Therefore, use any path patch with connectionstyle <code>ConnectionStyle.Angle3(0, -90)</code> or <code>ConnectionStyle.Arc3(1/2)</code> to plot the curve.</li></ol></li></ol><table><thead><tr><th>Coordinate System</th><th>Bottom Left</th><th>Top Right</th><th>Transform</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Data</td><td>based on data</td><td>based on data</td><td><code>ax.transData</code> (default)</td></tr><tr><td>Axes</td><td>(0, 0)</td><td>(1, 1)</td><td><code>ax.transAxes</code></td></tr><tr><td>Figure</td><td>(0, 0)</td><td>(1, 1)</td><td><code>fig.transFigure</code></td></tr><tr><td>Display</td><td>(0, 0)</td><td>(w, h) in inches</td><td><code>fig.dpi_scale_trans</code></td></tr></tbody></table><h2 id="Map"><a href="#Map" class="headerlink" title="Map"></a>Map</h2><ol><li><p>Map Projections:</p><ol><li>Positions on a map are usually specified by a longitude and a latitude. It is often used in Geographic Coordinate Systems (GCS)</li><li>They are angles in degrees specifying a position on a sphere</li><li>It is difficult to compute areas and distances with angles, so when plotting positions on maps, it is easier to use meters, or Coordinate Reference Systems (CRS)</li></ol></li><li><p>Regions on Maps and Polygons</p><ol><li>A region on a map can be represented by one or many polygons. A polygon is specified by a list of points connected by line segments.</li><li>Information about the polygons are stored in <code>shp</code>, <code>shx</code> and <code>dbf</code> files</li></ol></li><li><p>GeoPandas:</p><ol><li><code>GeoPandas</code> package can read shape files into <code>DataFrames</code> and matplotlib can be used to plot them. <code>GeoSeries</code> can do everything a <code>Series</code> can do, and more</li><li><code>geopandas.read_file(...)</code> can be used to read a <code>zip</code> file containing <code>shp</code>, shx and dbf files, and output a <code>GeoDataFrame</code>, which a pandas DataFrame with a column specifying the geometry of the item.</li><li><code>GeoDataFrame.plot()</code> can be used to plot the <code>polygons</code>.</li></ol></li><li><p>Conversion from GCS to CRS</p><ol><li><code>GeoDataFrame.crs</code> checks the coordinate system used in the data frame.</li><li><code>GeoDataFrame.to_crs(&quot;epsg:326??&quot;)</code> or GeoDataFrame.to_crs(“epsg:326??) can be used to convert from degree-based coordinate system to meter-based coordinate system.</li></ol></li><li><p>Creating Polygons:</p><ol><li>Polygons can be created manually from the vertices using <code>shapely</code> too</li><li><code>Point(x, y)</code> creates a point at $(x,y)$</li><li><code>LineString([x1, y1], [x2, y2])</code> or <code>LineString(Point(x1, y1), Point(x2, y2))</code> creates a line from $(x_1, y_1)$ to $(x_2, y_2)$.</li><li><code>Polygon([[x1, y1], [x2, y2], ...])</code> or <code>Polygon([Point(x1, y1), Point(x2, y2), ...])</code> creates a polygon connecting the vertices $(x_1, y_!), (x_2, y_2)$</li><li><code>box(xmin, ymin, xmax, ymax)</code> is another way to create a rectangular Polygon</li></ol></li><li><p>Polygon Properties:</p><ol><li><code>Polygon.area</code> or <code>MultiPolygon.area</code> computes the area of the polygon</li><li><code>Polygon.centroid</code> computes the centroid (center) of the polygon (using meter)</li><li><code>Polygon.buffer(r)</code> computes the geometry containing all points within a <code>r</code> distance from the polygon. If <code>Point.buffer(r)</code> is used, the resulting geometry is a circle with radius <code>r</code> around the point, and Point.buffer(r, cap_style &#x3D; 3) is a square with “radius” <code>r</code> around the point</li></ol></li><li><p>Polygon Manipulation:</p><ol><li>Union and intersections of polygons are still polygons.</li><li><code>geopandas.overlay(x, y, how = &quot;intersection&quot;)</code> computes the polygons that is the intersection of polygons x and y, if <code>GeoDataFrame</code> has geometry <code>x</code>, <code>GeoDataFrame.intersection(y)</code> computes the same intersection. <code>intersects</code> 返回是否相交(bool), <code>intersection</code> 返回一个相交集合(polygon). <code>y</code> 可以是一个 Window, 返回指定范围内的 polygon</li><li><code>box()</code> 返回 polygon.Ploygon 类型</li><li><code>geopandas.overlay(x, y, how = &quot;union&quot;)</code> computes the polygons that is the union of polygons x and y, Doc, if GeoDataFrame has geometry x, <code>GeoDataFrame.union(y)</code> computes the same union</li><li><code>GeoDataFrame.unary_union</code> is the single combined <code>MultiPolygon</code> of all polygons in the data frame</li><li><code>GeoDataFrame.convex_hull</code> computes the convex hull (smallest convex polygon that contains the original polygon)</li></ol></li><li><p>Geocoding:</p><ol><li><code>geopy</code> provide <code>geocoding</code> services to convert a <strong>text</strong> address into a <code>Point</code> geometry that specifies the longitude and latitude of the location</li><li><code>geopandas.tools.geocode(address)</code> returns a <code>Point</code> object with the <code>coordinate</code> for the address</li></ol></li></ol><h2 id="Regular-Expressions"><a href="#Regular-Expressions" class="headerlink" title="Regular Expressions"></a>Regular Expressions</h2><ol><li>Regular Expressions (Regex) is a small language for describing patterns to search for and it is used in many different programming languages</li><li>Python <code>re</code> package has <code>re.findall(regex, string)</code> and <code>re.sub(regex, replace, string)</code> to find and replace parts of string using the pattern regex</li><li>parentheses <code>()</code> are used to create capture groups. 在最后显示出来的时候会变成 tuple, 有一个括号就有一个 element，包裹嵌套括号</li><li>Raw Strings:<ol><li>Python uses escape characters to represent special characters.</li><li>Raw strings <code>r&quot;...&quot;</code> starts with r and do not convert escape characters into special characters.</li></ol></li></ol><table><thead><tr><th>Code</th><th>Character</th><th>Note</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><code>\&quot;</code></td><td>double quote</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td><code>\&#39;</code></td><td>single quote</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td><code>\\</code></td><td>backslash</td><td><code>&quot;\\\&quot;&quot;</code> displays <code>\&quot;</code></td></tr><tr><td><code>\n</code></td><td>new line</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td><code>\r</code></td><td>carriage return</td><td>(not used often)</td></tr><tr><td><code>\t</code></td><td>tab</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td><code>\b</code></td><td>backspace</td><td>(similar to left arrow key)</td></tr></tbody></table><ol start="4"><li><p>Meta Characters<br><code>+？</code> exactly one</p><table><thead><tr><th>Meta character</th><th>Meaning</th><th>Example</th><th>Meaning</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><code>.</code></td><td>any character except for \n</td><td><code>-</code></td><td><code>-</code></td></tr><tr><td><code>[]</code></td><td>any character inside brackets</td><td><code>[abc]</code></td><td>a or b or c</td></tr><tr><td><code>[^ ]</code></td><td>any character not inside brackets</td><td><code>[^abc]</code></td><td>not one of a, b, c</td></tr><tr><td><code>*</code></td><td>zero or more of last symbol</td><td><code>a*</code></td><td>zero or more a</td></tr><tr><td><code>+</code></td><td>one or more of last symbol</td><td><code>a+</code></td><td>one or more a</td></tr><tr><td><code>?</code></td><td>zero or one of last symbol</td><td><code>a?</code></td><td>zero or one a</td></tr><tr><td><code>&#123; &#125;</code></td><td>exact number of last symbol</td><td><code>a&#123;3&#125;</code></td><td>exactly aaa</td></tr><tr><td><code>&#123; , &#125;</code></td><td>number of last symbol in range</td><td><code>a&#123;1,3&#125;</code></td><td>a or aa or aaa</td></tr><tr><td><code>|</code></td><td>either before or after bar</td><td><code>ab|bc</code></td><td>either ab or bc</td></tr><tr><td><code>\</code></td><td>escapes next metacharacter</td><td><code>\?</code></td><td>literal ?</td></tr><tr><td><code>^</code></td><td>beginning of line</td><td><code>^a</code></td><td>begins with a</td></tr><tr><td><code>$</code></td><td>end of line</td><td><code>a$</code></td><td>ends with a</td></tr></tbody></table></li><li><p>Shorthand<br><code>\s</code>能都指代所有空格，包括 tab，回车</p><table><thead><tr><th>Shorthand</th><th>Meaning</th><th>Bracket Form</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><code>\d</code></td><td>digit</td><td><code>[0-9]</code></td></tr><tr><td><code>\D</code></td><td>not digit</td><td><code>[^0-9]</code></td></tr><tr><td><code>\w</code></td><td>alphanumeric character</td><td><code>[a-zA-Z0-9_]</code></td></tr><tr><td><code>\W</code></td><td>not alphanumeric character</td><td><code>[^a-zA-Z0-9_]</code></td></tr><tr><td><code>\s</code></td><td>white space</td><td><code>[\t\n\f\r\p&#123;Z&#125;]</code></td></tr><tr><td><code>\S</code></td><td>not white space</td><td><code>[^\t\n\f\r\p&#123;Z&#125;]</code></td></tr></tbody></table></li><li><p>Capture Group</p><ol><li><code>re.findall</code> can return a list of substrings or list of tuples of substrings using capturing groups inside <code>(...)</code>, for example, the regex <code>...(x)...(y)...(z)...</code> returns a list of tuples with three elements matching <code>x</code>, <code>y</code>, <code>z</code>.</li><li><code>re.sub</code> can replaces the matches by another string, the captured groups can be used in the replacement string by <code>\g&lt;1&gt;</code>, <code>\g&lt;2&gt;</code>, <code>\g&lt;3&gt;</code>, …, for example, replace <code>...(x)...(y)...(z)...</code> by <code>\g&lt;2&gt;\g&lt;3&gt;\g&lt;1&gt;</code> will return yxz</li></ol></li><li><p>Additional<br><img src="/../img/COMP320/COMP%20320%20Additional%201.png" alt="Alt text"></p></li></ol><h2 id="Words"><a href="#Words" class="headerlink" title="Words"></a>Words</h2><ol><li><p>Supervised: use the data to figure out the relationship between the features and labels of the items, and apply the relationship to predict the label of a new item. (classification if discrete, regression if continuous)</p></li><li><p>Unsupervised: use the data to find patterns and put items into groups. (clustering if discrete, dimensionality reduction if continuous)</p></li><li><p>Feature representation: items need to be represented by vector of numbers, for categories(one-hot encoding), images and text require additional preprocessing.</p></li><li><p>Tokenization: A text document needs to be split into words. Split the string by space and punctuation, sometimes regular expression rules can be used. Remove stop words: “the”, “of”, “a”, “with”, … Stemming and lemmatization: “looks”, “looked”, “looking” to “look”. <code>nltk</code> has functions to do these, <code>nltk.corpus.stopwords.words(&quot;english&quot;)</code> to get a list of stop words in English, and <code>nltk.stem.WordNetLemmatizer().lemmatize(word)</code> to lemmatize the token word.</p></li><li><p>Vocabulary: A word token is an occurrence of a word. A word type is a unique word as a dictionary entry. A vocabulary is a list of word types, typically 10000 or more word types. Sometimes <code>&lt;s&gt;</code> (start of sentence), <code>&lt;/s&gt;</code> (end of sentence), and <code>&lt;unk&gt;</code> (out of vocabulary words) are included in the vocabulary. A corpus is a larger collection of text. A document is a unit of text item.</p></li><li><p>Bag of words features represent documents as an unordered collection of words. Each document is represented by a row containing the number of occurrences of each word type in the vocabulary. For word type $j$ and $i$ document, the feature is $c(i,j)$, the number of times word $j$ appears in document $i$.</p></li><li><p>TF-IDF features:</p><ol><li>adjust for the fact that some words appear more frequently in all documents.</li><li>The term frequency of word type $j$ in document $i$ is defined as $tf(i,j)&#x3D;\frac{c(i,j)}{\sum_{j’}c(i,j’)}$ where $c(i,j)$ is the number of times word $j$ appears in the document $j$, and $\sum_{j’}c(i,j’)$ is the total number of words in document $i$.</li><li>The inverse document frequency of word type $j$ in document $i$ is defined as $idf(i,j)&#x3D;log(\frac{n+1}{n(j)+1})$ where $n(j)$ is the number of documents containing word $j$, and $n$ is the total number of documents.</li><li>For word type $j$ and document $i$, the feature is $tf(i,j)*idf(i,j)$.</li><li><code>sklearn.feature_extraction.text.CountVectorizer</code> can be used to convert text documents to a bag of words matrix. <code>sklearn.feature_extraction.text.TfidfVectorizer</code> can be used to convert text documents to a bag of words matrix</li></ol></li></ol><h2 id="Image"><a href="#Image" class="headerlink" title="Image"></a>Image</h2><ol><li>Image Pixel Intensity Features: Gray scale images have pixels valued from 0 to 255 (integers, 0 being black, 255 being white), or from 0 to 1 (real values, 0 being black, 1 being white). These pixel values are called pixel intensities. The pixel value matrices can be flattened into a vector (i.e. $k$ pixel by $k$ pixel image can be written as a list of $k^2$ numbers and used as input features.</li><li>Image Preprocessing: <code>scikit-image</code> can be used for basic image processing tasks. <code>skimage.io.imread</code> (read image from file), <code>skimage.io.imshow</code> (show image). The images are stored as <code>numpy.array</code>, which can be flattened using <code>numpy.ndarray.flatten</code>.</li><li>Color Images:<ol><li>RGB color images have color pixels represented by three numbers Red, Green, Blue, each valued from 0 to 255 or 0 to 1.</li><li>Intensity can be computed as $I &#x3D; \frac{1}{3}(R+G+B)$. Other perceptual luminance-preserving conversion can be done too, $I &#x3D; 0.2125R+0.7154G+0.0721B$.</li><li><code>skimage.color.rgb2gray</code></li></ol></li><li>Convolution:<ol><li>Convolution between an image and a filter (sometimes called kernel) is the dot product of every region of an image and the filter (sometimes flipped).</li><li><code>skimage.filters</code> has a list of special filters.<table><thead><tr><th>Name</th><th>Example</th><th>Use</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Identity</td><td><code>[0 0 0]</code><br><code>[0 1 0]</code><br><code>[0 0 0]</code></td><td>nothing</td></tr><tr><td>Gaussian</td><td><code>[0.0625 0.125 0.0625]</code><br><code>[0.125 0.25 0.125]</code><br><code>[0.0625 0.125 0.0625]</code></td><td>blur</td></tr><tr><td>X gradient</td><td><code>[0 0 0]</code><br><code>[1 0 -1]</code><br><code>[0 0 0]</code></td><td>vertical edges</td></tr><tr><td>Left (Right) Sobel</td><td><code>[1 0 -1]</code><br><code>[2 0 -2]</code><br><code>[1 0 -1]</code></td><td>vertical edges (blurred)</td></tr><tr><td>Y gradient</td><td><code>[0 1 0]</code><br><code>[0 0 0]</code><br><code>[0 -1 0]</code></td><td>vertical edges</td></tr><tr><td>Top (Bottom) Sobel</td><td><code>[1 2 1]</code><br><code>[0 0 0]</code><br><code>[-1 -2 -1]</code></td><td>vertical edges (blurred)</td></tr></tbody></table></li><li>Image Gradient Features: One popular face recognition algorithms uses HOG (Histogram of Gradients) features.<ol><li>Compute the X and Y gradient for each pixel (either X or Y gradient filters or Sobel filters)</li><li>Compute a histogram for pixel gradients in each of the 8 orientations for every 16 by 16 pixel regions (8 numbers for every 16 x 16 region)</li><li>Concatenate the histograms to use as the feature vector</li><li><code>skimage.feature.hog</code> computes the HOG features</li></ol></li></ol></li></ol><h2 id="Classification"><a href="#Classification" class="headerlink" title="Classification"></a>Classification</h2><ol><li><p>Binary Classification: For binary classification, the labels are binary, either 0 or 1, but the output of the classifier $\hat{f}(x)$ can be a number between 0 and 1. $\hat{f}(x)$ usually represents the probability that the label is 1, and it is sometimes called the activation value. 通常来说，小于 0.5 就是 0， 大于 0.5 就是 1</p></li><li><p>Confusion Matrix: A confusion matrix contains the counts of items with every label-prediction combinations, in case of binary classifications, it is a 2 by 2 matrix with the following entries:<br>(1) number of item labeled 1 and predicted to be 1 (true positive: TP),<br>(2) number of item labeled 1 and predicted to be 0 (false negative: FN),<br>(3) number of item labeled 0 and predicted to be 1 (false positive: FP),<br>(4) number of item labeled 0 and predicted to be 0 (true negative: TN).</p><table><thead><tr><th>Count</th><th>Predict 1</th><th>Predict 0</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Label 1</td><td>TP</td><td>FN</td></tr><tr><td>Label 0</td><td>FP</td><td>TN</td></tr></tbody></table><p>Precision is the positive value, or $p&#x3D;\frac{TP}{TP+FP}$<br>Recall is the true positive, $r&#x3D;\frac{TP}{TP+FN}$<br>F-measure is $\frac{2<em>p</em>r}{p+r}$</p></li><li><p>Multi-class Classification</p><ol><li>Class Probiities: If there are $k$ classes, the classifier could output $k$ numbers between 0 and 1, and sum up to 1, to represent the probability that the item belongs to each class, sometimes called activation values. If a deterministic prediction is required, the classifier can predict the label with the largest probability.</li><li>One-vs-one Classifiers: If there are $k$ classes, then $\frac{1}{2}k(k-1)$ binary classifiers will be trained, 1 vs 2, 1 vs 3, 2 vs 3, … The prediction can be the label that receives the largest number of votes from the one-vs-one binary classifiers.</li><li>One-vs-all Classifiers: If there are $k$ classes, then $k$ binary classifiers will be trained, 1 vs not 1, 2 vs not 2, 3 vs not 3, …</li></ol></li><li><p>Multi-class Confusion Matrix</p><table><thead><tr><th>Count</th><th>Predict 0</th><th>Predict 1</th><th>Predict 2</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Class 0</td><td>$c_{y&#x3D;0,j&#x3D;0}$</td><td>$c_{y&#x3D;0,j&#x3D;1}$</td><td>$c_{y&#x3D;0,j&#x3D;2}$</td></tr><tr><td>Class 1</td><td>$c_{y&#x3D;1,j&#x3D;0}$</td><td>$c_{y&#x3D;1,j&#x3D;1}$</td><td>$c_{y&#x3D;1,j&#x3D;2}$</td></tr><tr><td>Class 2</td><td>$c_{y&#x3D;2,j&#x3D;0}$</td><td>$c_{y&#x3D;2,j&#x3D;1}$</td><td>$c_{y&#x3D;2,j&#x3D;2}$</td></tr></tbody></table><p>Precision of class $i$, is $\frac{c_{ii}}{\sum_{j}c_{ji}}$<br>Recall of class $i$, is $\frac{c_{ii}}{\sum_{j}c_{ij}}$</p></li><li><p>Conversation from Probabilities to Predictions</p><ol><li>Probability predictions are given in a matrix, where row $i$ is the probability prediction for item $i$, and column $j$ is the predicted probability that item $i$ has label $j$.</li><li>Given an $n<em>m$ probability prediction matrix <code>p</code>, <code>p.max(axis = 1)</code> computes the $n</em>1$ vector of maximum probabilities, one for each row, and <code>p.argmax(axis = 1)</code> computes the column indices of those maximum probabilities, which also corresponds to the predicted labels of the items.</li><li><code>p.max(axis = 0)</code> and <code>p.argmax(axis = 0)</code> would compute max and argmax along the columns.</li></ol></li></ol>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Courses</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>course notes</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>ECE 252</title>
    <link href="/2023/09/19/EE252/"/>
    <url>/2023/09/19/EE252/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="Week-1"><a href="#Week-1" class="headerlink" title="Week 1"></a><strong><em><em>Week 1</em></em></strong></h2><h3 id="Universal-Compute"><a href="#Universal-Compute" class="headerlink" title="Universal Compute"></a><strong>Universal Compute</strong></h3><ol><li>Turing Machine: any computable computation can be implemented by some machine</li><li>Universal Turing Machine: A programmable computer is effectively a Universal Turing Machine (minus infinite memory).</li><li>A computer can compute anything that’s possible to compute given enough memory and time.</li><li>Design trade-off: Time, Cost, Power&#x2F;Energy.</li></ol><h3 id="Complexity"><a href="#Complexity" class="headerlink" title="Complexity"></a><strong>Complexity</strong></h3><ol><li>1st transistor -&gt; Bell Labs, 1st IC -&gt; Jack Kilby(MSEE’50), 1st microprocessor -&gt; Intel</li><li>Moore’s Law: number of transistors on a microchip doubles approximately every two years(24 month). -&gt; Cost halves every two years.</li></ol><h3 id="Abstraction"><a href="#Abstraction" class="headerlink" title="Abstraction"></a><strong>Abstraction</strong></h3><ol><li>Use abstraction to manage complexity.</li><li>The ISA lies at the software&#x2F;hardware boundary.</li><li>Problem Statement –Software Design–&gt; Algorithm –Programming–&gt; Program –Compilation–&gt; ISA –Processor Design–&gt; Microarchitecture –Logic&#x2F;Circuit Design–&gt; Logic Circuits –Implement&amp;Fabricate–&gt; Devices</li></ol><h3 id="Electral-Infomation"><a href="#Electral-Infomation" class="headerlink" title="Electral Infomation"></a><strong>Electral Infomation</strong></h3><ol><li>Analog: continuous range of values</li><li>Digital: discrete set of values (almost all eletronic device)</li><li>In reality, the voltage levels are actually ranges of voltages.</li><li>Voltage &#x3D; Current * Resistance</li><li>Any data processed by a digital computer is represented by sequences of 1s and 0s</li></ol><h2 id="Week-2"><a href="#Week-2" class="headerlink" title="Week 2"></a><strong><em>Week 2</em></strong></h2><h3 id="Number-representation"><a href="#Number-representation" class="headerlink" title="Number representation"></a><strong>Number representation</strong></h3><ol><li>demical-10, Binary-2, Octal-8, Hexademical-16</li><li>least-significant, right most; most-significant, left-most</li><li>$D_{N-1}\cdots D_{1}D_{0}&#x3D;D_{N-1}*r^{N-1} + \cdots + D_{1}<em>r^1 + D_0</em>r^0$</li><li>Each position represents a power of base; Digital value says how many of that power of base.</li><li>A value is a particular quantity, a number is a way to represent a value. Same “number”, different value.</li></ol><h3 id="Base-conversion"><a href="#Base-conversion" class="headerlink" title="Base conversion"></a><strong>Base conversion</strong></h3><ol><li>Binary &lt;-&gt; Hex: directly substitute a hex digit for a 4-bit binary number.</li><li>Binary &lt;-&gt; Octal: directly substitute a octual digit for a 3-bit binary number.</li><li>Octal &lt;-&gt; Hex: use binary as an intermediate form.</li></ol><h3 id="Arithmetic"><a href="#Arithmetic" class="headerlink" title="Arithmetic"></a><strong>Arithmetic</strong></h3><ol><li>Substraction using borrowing: If necessary, bowrrow the base’s value from one position higher</li><li>Multiple by power of base, shifts number to the left. Divide by power of base, shifts numbers to the right.</li></ol><h3 id="Signed-Numbers"><a href="#Signed-Numbers" class="headerlink" title="Signed Numbers"></a><strong>Signed Numbers</strong></h3><ol><li>Signed-Magnitude: The most significant bit is the sign, the remaining bits are the numbers magnitude.</li><li>2’s Complement representation: positive numbers start with 0, negative numbers start with 1 ($-2^N$).</li><li>Fast Negation: complement each bit and the add 1.</li><li>Addition: works the way it does for unsigned binary number except the carry-out is not meaningful.</li><li>Substraction: add the negation of the value we wish to subtract</li><li>Operand&#x2F;Result bitwidths match: operands and results must have the same number of bits for the math to work correctly.</li></ol><h3 id="Sign-Extention"><a href="#Sign-Extention" class="headerlink" title="Sign Extention"></a><strong>Sign Extention</strong></h3><ol><li>Extend 2’s complement number: for positive: zero-extension; for negative: one-extension</li><li>Negative 1 in 2’s complement: $-1\cdots1$</li><li>Unsigned number: $[0, 2^n -1]$, signed number: $[-(2^{n-1}-1), 2^{n-1}-1]$, 2’s-complement number: $[-2^{n-1}, 2^{n-1}-1]$</li><li>Overflow: The result cannot be correctly represented in the required number of bits.</li><li>lf adding two negative 2’s-complement numbers overflows, the sign of the result will appear to be non-negative.</li><li>lf the result of adding two positive 2’s-complement numbers appears to be positive, then the operation did not overflow.</li><li>lf adding two unsigned numbers overflows , the result will appear to be<br>smaller than it should be.</li></ol><h2 id="Week-3"><a href="#Week-3" class="headerlink" title="Week 3"></a><strong><em>Week 3</em></strong></h2><h3 id="Fixed-Float"><a href="#Fixed-Float" class="headerlink" title="Fixed Float"></a><strong>Fixed Float</strong></h3><ol><li>Radix point: separates the integer portion from the fractional portion of the numebr</li><li>when the format defines a “fixed” position for the radix point within the number’s digits</li><li><img src="/../img/EE252/EE252%201.jpg"></li><li>Shifting right by $N$ bits is equivalent to dividing by $2^N$</li><li>location of radix is not visible, not encoded in the number, must told. We never know the meaning of a binary number just by looking at it.</li></ol><h3 id="Floating-Float"><a href="#Floating-Float" class="headerlink" title="Floating Float"></a><strong>Floating Float</strong></h3><ol><li><img src="/../img/EE252/EE252%202.jpg" alt="IEEE 32-bit"></li><li><img src="/../img/EE252/EE252%203.jpg" alt="Comparison"></li><li>Precision: number of significant digits. No need to transform 10.</li></ol><h3 id="ASCII"><a href="#ASCII" class="headerlink" title="ASCII"></a><strong>ASCII</strong></h3><ol><li>7 bits to represent 128 different characters.</li><li>UTF-8, 16, 32</li></ol><h2 id="Week-4"><a href="#Week-4" class="headerlink" title="Week 4"></a><strong><em>Week 4</em></strong></h2><h3 id="Logic-Functions"><a href="#Logic-Functions" class="headerlink" title="Logic Functions"></a><strong>Logic Functions</strong></h3><ol><li>AND: result is true if all operands are true</li><li>OR: result is true if any operand is true</li><li>NOT: result is the opposite of the operand value</li><li><img src="/../img/EE252/EE252%204.png" alt="Symbols"></li><li>XOR: the result of a two-operand OR is true if both operands are true, the odd function</li><li>A bitwise operation computes each bit of an N-bit result based on the value in the correponding position of the N-bit operands.</li></ol><h3 id="Combiational-Logical"><a href="#Combiational-Logical" class="headerlink" title="Combiational Logical"></a><strong>Combiational Logical</strong></h3><ol><li><img src="/../img/EE252/EE252%205.png" alt="Transistors"></li><li><img src="/../img/EE252/EE252%206.png" alt="Logic Gates"></li><li>Waveforms: a waveform is a visual way to represent signal values over time.</li><li>Logic circuits are at a higher level of abstraction. Each transistor acts like a switch.</li><li>NOT gate use 2 transisters.</li></ol><h3 id="Combinational-Blocks"><a href="#Combinational-Blocks" class="headerlink" title="Combinational Blocks"></a><strong>Combinational Blocks</strong></h3><ol><li>Decoder: converts an n-bit input code word into a unique m-bit ouput value, where $m&#x3D;2^n$.</li><li>Exactly one output can be true at any given time.</li><li><img src="/../img/EE252/EE252%207.png" alt="Decoder"></li><li>Multiplexers: based on the select input, choose one of the data inputs to drive the output</li><li><img src="/../img/EE252/EE252%208.png" alt="Muxes"></li><li>Full adder: at every position, determine 2-bit sum of adding each addend’s bit in that position plus a carry-in. A full adder performs addition for single bit position.</li><li><img src="/../img/EE252/EE252%209.png" alt="Full Adder"></li><li>Ripple Carry Adder: serires of full adders, where each full adder performs the addition for a single bit position.</li></ol><h2 id="Week-5"><a href="#Week-5" class="headerlink" title="Week 5"></a><strong><em>Week 5</em></strong></h2><h3 id="Sequence-Logic"><a href="#Sequence-Logic" class="headerlink" title="Sequence Logic"></a><strong>Sequence Logic</strong></h3><ol><li>Before, are all combinational logic. Circuit outputs only depend on current input values.</li><li>A circuit’s current state is the binary number that is currently stored in the circuit’s flip-flops.</li><li>Sequence logic: circuit outputs depend on both current input values and past stored values.</li><li>D flip-flop: output is always equal to the value it is storing<br><img src="/../img/EE252/Week5%201.png" alt="Full Adder"></li><li>D flip-flop updates when the clock transitions from 0 to 1 (rising edge)</li><li>FSM (finite state machine): any circuit built from flip-flops is FSM</li><li>State Diagram:<ol><li>state is represented by a circle, the circle also indicate the output in that state.</li><li>state transitions represented by an arrow from one state to another. Labeled with the input condition.</li></ol></li></ol><h3 id="FSM"><a href="#FSM" class="headerlink" title="FSM"></a><strong>FSM</strong></h3><ol><li>sequential circuits.</li><li>track of which state it is currently in</li><li>The FSM contains one flip-flop per bit of state</li><li>depends both upon the current state and the inputs, the next state is a function of the current state and current input values.</li><li>Start state &lt;-&gt; reset state</li><li>Some state machines do not have an input, or the input does not affect a particular state transition, this type of transition is an unconditional transition.</li><li>“X” means shorthand for “any value of”</li><li>The output will be the current state output.</li></ol><h3 id="Registers-Memory"><a href="#Registers-Memory" class="headerlink" title="Registers Memory"></a><strong>Registers Memory</strong></h3><ol><li>A register is a group of flip-flops used to stire multi-bit binary values.</li><li>Write-Enable: whether take the input to store</li><li>Address: M bits, $2^M$ locations to access.</li><li>Each location stores a single N-bit word: data size, # bits per location</li><li>Capacity &#x3D; (# locations) * (data size)</li><li>Address selects which register supplies data out using Mut.</li><li>Address selects which register may be written to using decoder. Selected register will only be written if WE&#x3D;1</li></ol><h2 id="Week-6"><a href="#Week-6" class="headerlink" title="Week 6"></a><strong><em>Week 6</em></strong></h2><ol><li>ALU(arithmetic logic unit), a set of logic structures that perform a set of different possible computations on the inputs.</li><li>A set of multiplexers that choose which result to send to the ALU output.</li><li>The register file: a small memory located near the ALU<br>write port: used to write operation’s result to register file: DR(DA), DD(DD), write<br>read port: used to get operands from register file: SR(SA), SD, BMUX, output</li><li>Conceptual Compute Model: Memory, Control Unit, Processing Unit</li><li>Control Unit: fetches instructions one by one from memory, two special unit PC(program counter), IR(instruction register). Memory read using address in PC, put the returned value into IR, then increment the PC.</li><li>von Neumann Compute Model, holds both the program and any data needed by the program(memory)</li><li>Instruction: small step of a program is encoded into a binary word called an instruction. (ISA)</li><li>FETCH: Read an instruction from mem, put into IR and increase PC<br>-&gt; DECODE: determine what the instruction meaning (opcode, field)<br>-&gt; EVALUATE ADDRESS<br>-&gt; FECTCH OPERANDS: get the operands<br>-&gt; EXECUTE: ALU<br>-&gt; STORE RESULT: write back to register<br>repeat forever, not all phases are required for all instruction(后四个)</li><li>Some processors group different stage together</li></ol><h2 id="Week-7"><a href="#Week-7" class="headerlink" title="Week 7"></a><strong><em>Week 7</em></strong></h2><ol><li>LC-3: 8 general-purpose registers, 16 bit</li><li>N, Z, P: three branch bit reg</li><li>address calculation method depends on the memory addressing mode.</li><li>Mem both holds ins and data</li></ol>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Courses</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>course notes</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>美东游记-波士顿</title>
    <link href="/2023/09/01/life_experience_2/"/>
    <url>/2023/09/01/life_experience_2/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>正如之前的安排，8 月中旬去了美国东海岸旅游了一趟。路线是芝加哥-&gt;波士顿-&gt;纽约-&gt;华盛顿（主要是去 UMD）。一路风尘，回来安顿下来之后写一些随感。</p><p>在开始之前，我突然想起了余秋雨的《文化苦旅》，是初中的时候班主任推荐的。说实在我并不觉得《文化苦旅》的文笔有多好，指类似于《生活在树上》给人眼花缭乱的感觉，也不觉得其有多朴实，指类似于《骆驼祥子》给人过于“地道”的感觉。《文化苦旅》就像是普通人写的一本普通游记，平淡的记录一路上发生所有的事情，辅以一些历史资料和个人感悟。唯一令人印象深刻的是余秋雨（似乎？）一路跨国欧亚大陆的长途旅行。假使我有这份财富和运气，将来我也要这么走一趟（笑）。</p><p>那，就万物起始，从 7 天呆在波士顿的旅行开始。</p><p>抵达波士顿的第一天，借宿在 Y 同学的家里。不远就是 MIT 的校区。MIT 给我的第一印象就是和 Skd 很像，校园不大，各楼之间都有走廊相连接，专业设置也大体是理工科。当然 MIT 的学术成就和影响是 Skd 万万望尘莫及的。（人，要有理想，万一一百年后 Skd 也能成为东方 MIT 呢）</p><p>7 天的空闲时间我基本呆在 MIT 的 Hayden Library。是一个坐落在 Charies River 旁的小型图书馆，其四周都是落地窗，24H 开放（工作时间对公众开放）。借了 Y 同学的校园卡，得以在里面搬砖敲代码。我着实喜欢这样的图书馆，从窗口望出去，草坪，河水，和远处的 CBD 构成绝妙的图像平衡。<br><img src="/../img/life_experience_2/IMG_library.JPG" alt="Hayden Library"></p><p>来波士顿的首要目标就是炫意大利小镇的龙虾意面，这家店叫 The Daily Catch。店不大，开在拥挤的街道上，有点苍蝇馆子的味道。来之前有所听闻其名声和巨长的排队人数，我便早上 10 点就从 Hayden Library 出发，但到那儿依然排了半个小时的队伍。</p><p>我没有具体看菜单，毕竟是奔着龙虾来的（大体还是一些经典的意大利菜，龙虾意面标注在菜单的正中央，大写加粗）。原本是打算和 Y 同学一起吃，但是 Y 同学沉迷 research，只好点了一人份的龙虾意面。<br><img src="/../img/life_experience_2/IMG_1146.JPG" alt="The Daily Catch"><br><img src="/../img/life_experience_2/IMG_1147.JPG" alt="Lobster Noodles"><br>说实话，分量确实很大（将近 70 刀！），也满足了我关在 Madison 半年对于美食的极高期待。店里面都是三三两两的游客，邻桌是带父母来波士顿旅游的华侨。我独自一人在店中狂炫龙虾，倒也是一种奇特的经历。</p><p>来波士顿之前有所听闻 MFA 的莫奈藏品。对于我这种毫无艺术细胞的人来说，印象派画家，尤其是莫奈，通过其更加通俗易懂的表达形式，相比于抽象派更能吸引我。说起来我和莫奈的渊源也有些奇妙，小学的时候在某本杂志上看到过对于莫奈画的赏析，讲的是《日出·印象》；那个时候惊叹于真的有人可以画出早晨港口那种烟雾朦胧的感觉。</p><p>不过可惜的是 MFA 只收藏了莫奈的《睡莲》等练习画，没能看到《日出》，也没能看到《草地上的午餐》，着实有点可惜。后来去纽约的时候，大都会博物馆的整个欧洲艺术展区都在维护，此躺美东旅行没有看到对于我来说的莫奈的代表作，实在是可惜。<br><img src="/../img/life_experience_2/IMG_1161.JPG" alt="Les Meules"><br><img src="/../img/life_experience_2/IMG_1155.JPG" alt="La Japonaise"></p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Gossip</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>traveling</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Calvin</title>
    <link href="/2023/08/02/Calvin/"/>
    <url>/2023/08/02/Calvin/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id=""><a href="#" class="headerlink" title=""></a></h2>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Paper Reading</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>database</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>近期随感</title>
    <link href="/2023/07/09/life_experience_1/"/>
    <url>/2023/07/09/life_experience_1/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>恍惚间，已经是 23 年 8 月 1 号了。抵美的第八个月。</p><p>上次更新博客已经是一个月前，看来当初还颇有自知之明。简单梳理一下这个月发生的事情。</p><p>大部分同期交换的同学已经回国，作为留守人员，承担着送人和薅羊毛的责任和权利，虽然后者偏多。处在异国他乡，尤其是在麦屯这种独立日都看不到烟花的乡村，感到寂寞是常有的事。好在麦迪逊风光确实不错，大部分时间也很安全，我赖以四处走动。贴上几幅随手所拍。<br><img src="/../img/life_experience_1/IMG_0985.JPG" alt="Lake Mendota (near Memorial Union)"><br><img src="/../img/life_experience_1/IMG_0996.JPG" alt="Memorial Union"><br><img src="/../img/life_experience_1/IMG_1011.JPG" alt="Lake Mendota"><br><img src="/../img/life_experience_1/IMG_1025.JPG" alt="Place near my house"><br><img src="/../img/life_experience_1/IMG_1039.JPG" alt="Mills Concert Hall"><br><img src="/../img/life_experience_1/IMG_1060.JPG" alt="Just Keep Swimming!"><br><img src="/../img/life_experience_1/IMG_1079.JPG" alt="Washburn Observatory"><br><img src="/../img/life_experience_1/IMG_1088.JPG" alt="Way to McDonald&#39;s!"><br>不得不承认，麦迪逊的夏天确实如当地人口中那样美好。其夏日白天因为高纬度而漫长，即使忙碌到 8 点也可以踩着夕阳去湖边听免费的音乐会。气温又刚刚好，差不多等于上海的春秋季，适合穿着短袖套一件外衣出门。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Gossip</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>emo</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Hello World ?</title>
    <link href="/2023/07/03/hello-world/"/>
    <url>/2023/07/03/hello-world/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>欢迎来到我的博客!</p><p>因为在主页上挂着Hexo的Introduction着实是有些奇怪，所以先写一点文字，一是让博客里有一些电子垃圾，二是留一些以后可以怀念的文字。</p><p>当然我并不能确保特定的更新频率，而且维护博客大概也会上我的人生必做清单（这个清单上已经有如下事项：读完紫龙书，读完C++大部头，完成Sencondary Market Project的前后端分离），当然了，也很难想象会有人特地来赏光我的博客。所以，我对于这个博客的定义更倾向于是一点点的个人介绍，大量的生活经历分享和不知所云的灌水文字。</p><p>或许不久以后因为申请会陆续挂上个人简历和项目链接，不过相比全是paper的大佬博客，这儿不过是“存在主义”罢了，仅供commitee或者prof一笑。</p><p>好了，回归正题。</p><p>既然是作为可以怀念的文字，我先写写为何突发奇想创建自己的博客。我现位于UW-Madison，WISC，作为交换生在北美虚度光阴。上学期初寻找系统方向的Prof能够接纳我进组做一些项目<del>带带我水文章</del>，觉得需要创建一个个人网站来贴点CV和toy project。不曾想Prof Xiangyao Yu欣然接受我的申请，并且与我合作了一个项目<del>我觉得大概是CAII写的RISCV Simulator起了作用</del>，导致筹划到一半的个人网站不了了之。到了暑假，不堪项目的推进，托福和GRE，还有几个toy competition的压力，便乘机做个博客，写点不用debug多线程的文字，贴点四处晃荡的图片，以期在满屏error和low performance的大山下苟延残喘。</p><p>对于博客的内容，我想有一部分会是对过往岁月的“追忆”，我对此有充足的理由。首先，根据幸存者偏差的乱用，我们往往会注意到不如以前的事务，比如Madison的中餐让我开始可以接受博海一楼的自选菜。此外，随着心智和年龄的增长，我往往会对过往的人和物有更多的理解和思考，并且自责于当时的错误做法，遗憾于产生的bad ending，留下这些思考可以作为一面明镜，警醒我现在的所作所为，毕竟人往往会进入同一条河流。当然了，更多的其实还是像林海音之于《城南旧事》，曹雪芹之于《红楼梦》，对于自己曾经岁月的无限追忆，因为其美好，其蕴含的无限可能。</p><p>还有一部分会是一些技术的留档，<del>f**k you, CSDN</del>虽然我觉得其实如果自己真要用了使用chatgpt会更方便（GPT-4已经能帮我调多线程Bug了，我哭死）。考虑到之后回国可能的TGW问题，或是一些刁钻的环境问题，或是一些第三方库古怪的调用，我还是会不定期将一些技术整理成文档上传。</p><p>当然了，肯定还有一部分是关于美食，旅游等生活方面的分享，毕竟我已经没有了高中从医救济苍生的伟大理想，Just enjoy the fking world!之后8月中旬会飞往波士顿和旧金山，十分期待某人请客的龙虾。</p><p>最后，创建博客还基于一点点个人的想法，大刘说过“给岁月以文明，给时光以生命”，仅以此给这个宇宙和这片时间一点点来自Zhenghong Yu的痕迹。</p><p>Welcome to my blog!</p><p>Since it’s extraordinary to have Hexo’s Introduction on the homepage, I will write a little bit of text first to keep some e-waste in the blog and leave some text I can remember later.</p><p>Of course, I can’t ensure a specific update frequency, and maintaining the blog would probably be on my life’s must-do list (which already includes the following: finish reading the Purple Dragon book, finish reading the bulk of C++, and finish separating the front and back ends of the Secondary Market Project), and of course, it’s hard to imagine that anyone would specifically come to my blog. So, my definition of this blog is a personal introduction, more of life experience sharing and watered-down words.</p><p>Maybe I’ll put up a CV and links to my toy projects later for my application. Still, compared to a blog full of papers, this is just an “existentialist” blog, just for the committee or prof to have a laugh.</p><p>Okay, back to business.</p><p>Since this is meant to be a nostalgic text, I’ll start by writing about why I suddenly wanted to start my own blog. I am currently located at UW-Madison, WISC, and spend my time in North America as an exchange student. At the beginning of last semester, I was looking for a Prof in the Systems field to take me on as a member of his group to do some projects <del>bring me up to water papers</del> and thought I needed to create a personal website to post some CVs and toy projects. To my surprise, Prof Xiangyao Yu readily accepted my application and collaborated with me on a project<del>It was probably the RISCV Simulator by CAII that did the trick</del>. And caused the half-planned personal website to fall through. In the summer, I was overwhelmed by the project, the TOEFL and GRE, and the pressure of a few toy competitions, so I took the opportunity to make a blog, write some text without debugging multiple threads, and post some pictures that wander around, to survive under the mountain of errors and low performance.</p><p>I think part of the blog’s content will be a “reminiscence” of the past, and I have good reasons for this. By the indiscriminate use of survivorship bias, we tend to notice things that are not as good as they used to be, such as Madison’s Chinese food, which has made the self-chosen dishes on the ground floor of Bohai acceptable to me. In addition, as my mind and age grow, I tend to understand and think more about people and things from the past, blame myself for the mistakes I made at the time, and regret the bad endings that resulted. Leaving these reflections as a clear mirror to remind me of what I do now; after all, people tend to enter the same river. Of course, it is more like Lin Haiyin’s “Old Stories from the South of the City” or Cao Xueqin’s “Dream of the Red Chamber,” the endless remembrance of my former years of its beauty and the infinite possibilities.</p><p>There will also be a part of it that will be some technical documents, <del>f**k you, CSDN</del>. Though it would be more convenient to use chatgpt if I really had to use this (GPT-4 has been able to help me tune multi-threaded bugs, lmao). Considering the possible TGW problems, tricky environment problems, or weird calls to third-party libraries, I will occasionally upload some techniques.</p><p>Of course, I’m sure there will be some food, travel, and other aspects of life to share; after all, I no longer have the great ambition to be a doctor in high school; I just want to enjoy the fking world!</p><p>Finally, the blog is also based on a bit of personal thought; as Liu said, “Give years to civilization, give time to live,” so this is just a way to give this universe and, this time, a little trace from Zhenghong Yu.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Introduction</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>introduction</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>RISCV-Simulator Part1</title>
    <link href="/2023/07/03/RISCV-Simulator/"/>
    <url>/2023/07/03/RISCV-Simulator/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="1-开源声明"><a href="#1-开源声明" class="headerlink" title="1 开源声明"></a>1 开源声明</h1><p>该项目是上海科技大学 CS211 Advancing Computer Architecture 课程设计，引用北京大学 hehao 写的 RISCV 平台（<a href="https://github.com/hehao98/RISCV-Simulator">https://github.com/hehao98/RISCV-Simulator</a> ）。</p><h1 id="2-平台安装与测试"><a href="#2-平台安装与测试" class="headerlink" title="2 平台安装与测试"></a>2 平台安装与测试</h1><p>其实整个平台的简介，安装和运行原作者已经有了详尽的文档（<a href="https://hehao98.github.io/posts/2019/03/riscv-simulator/">https://hehao98.github.io/posts/2019/03/riscv-simulator/</a> ）。个人推荐是直接阅读原文。项目本体应该没有显著的 bug（我并不敢打包票，因为我自己就发现了一个并且提了 issue，然而作者表示 3 年前写的，已经忘光了 lmao），个人测试在大部分 linux 发行版上面都可以正常运行。</p><h1 id="3-项目框架介绍和-Lab-总览"><a href="#3-项目框架介绍和-Lab-总览" class="headerlink" title="3 项目框架介绍和 Lab 总览"></a>3 项目框架介绍和 Lab 总览</h1><p>（其实想吐槽一下整个平台有屎山的味道，但是转念一想，毕竟不是人人都是 pintos 这种历经了数十年打磨的项目，也就心平气和了）<br>项目结构其实很简单，在 4 个 Lab 中基本只需要关注<code>\src</code>即可，文件名基本说明了其功能，详细情况我将在具体的 Lab 分析中谈及。<code>\test</code>放置测试文件，需要编译为 RISCV 放置在<code>\riscv-elf</code>中运行。<br>Lab 0 主要是实现原子指令。Lab 1 涉及实现不同 policy 的 Cache。Lab 2 实现基于感知机的分支预测。Lab 3 实现多核 CPU。<br>在 Part 1 中，我将分析 Lab 0 和其具体实现。</p><h1 id="4-Lab-0"><a href="#4-Lab-0" class="headerlink" title="4 Lab 0"></a>4 Lab 0</h1><p>Lab 0 相对来说是四个项目中最简单的一个（合理，毕竟谁也不想一上来就写多线程），而且我不幸的发现，这是唯一一个我不需要回去看代码就能开些 blog 的 Lab 了。</p><h2 id="4-1-文档分析"><a href="#4-1-文档分析" class="headerlink" title="4.1 文档分析"></a>4.1 文档分析</h2><p>首先我们通读 Lab 要求文档（<a href="https://github.com/HarukiMoriarty/CS211-AdvancingCA-Shanghaitech/blob/main/Lab/Lab0/CS211-Lab0.pdf">https://github.com/HarukiMoriarty/CS211-AdvancingCA-Shanghaitech/blob/main/Lab/Lab0/CS211-Lab0.pdf</a> ）。显然，我们需要实现两个原子指令，<code>Load Reserved(LR)</code>和<code>Store Conditional(SC)</code>。</p><p>我们先简短介绍一下原子指令。原子指令是一种重要的并发工具，保证其执行过程中不会被其他进程或线程中断，从而确保数据的一致性和操作的完整性。</p><p>RISCV 的原子指令不止 LR&#x2F;SC，同样存在一批以“AMO”为前缀的原子指令，Lab 0 中我们仅考虑 LR&#x2F;SC。在这时我们便遇到了第一个问题，在不同版本 RISCV 文档中，对于 LR&#x2F;SC 的实现要求是不同的，特指功能要求（因为 structure 是一样的）。我选择了 V1 版本（Volume 1, Unprivileged Specification version 20191213）。有兴趣的大佬可以参考 21 年的新版本(v2)，对于 LR&#x2F;SC 指令的要求更为宽松。</p><p>我们首先展示 LR&#x2F;SC 指令结构（没啥好分析的，直接上图）<br><img src="/../img/riscv/instruction%20structure.png"><br>LR&#x2F;SC 都是 32 位指令，opcode 为<code>0X2F</code>；funct5 为<code>0x3</code>；对于 8B 数据，funct3 为<code>0x3</code>，对于 4B 数据，funct3 为<code>0x2</code>；本次 Lab 不考虑数据对齐。</p><p>然后我们分析其基本功能，LR 指令从 rs1 处获得数据地址，从 rd 处获得符号位扩展，并且对这个地址进行注册保留。SC 指令从 rs1 处获得数据地址，从 rs2 处获得数据，当且仅当该地址注册保留依旧有效（valid）时成功执行，将数据从 rs2 写入内存，向 rd 中写入 0；如果执行失败，则仅向 rd 中写入非 0 值。根据 V1 版本推测，我倾向于无论成功与否，LR&#x2F;SC 指令的执行都会清除指向地址的注册保留。</p><p>我们考虑更多，如果（指令流上）同时存在多个嵌套 LR-SC 指令对怎么办？这不仅仅包括，单一核(hart)执行了嵌套的 LR-SC 指令，也包括多个核同时对一个地址进行 LR-SC 指令。V1 采取了更为保守的策略，只允许 SC 追踪最近的，同一个核的 LR 指令。</p><p>我在这里附上原文，An SC can only pair with the most recent LR in program order. An SC may succeed only if no store from another hart to the reservation set can be observed to have occurred between the LR and the SC, and if there is no other SC between the LR and itself in program order. An SC may succeed only if no write from a device other than a hart to the bytes accessed by the LR instruction can be observed to have occurred between the LR and SC. Note this LR might have had a different effective address and data size, but reserved the SC’s address as part of the reservation set.</p><p>很绕，我进行简要概括，即，在当前核 LR 到 SC 的程序流中，不能出现额外的 LR&#x2F;SC 指令，不能出现其他核访问保留注册地址的操作，不能出现本核对于注册保留地址进行写操作，并且 SC 指令观察到保留注册依然有效，才能成功执行。</p><p>这其实极大的简化了 Lab 的难度，在一开始我和马老师的讨论中考虑了更为复杂的情况，也是 21 版 V2 中所考虑的，允许一些只读指令在注册保留的地址上操作，并且允许 LR&#x2F;SC 指令的嵌套。V1 近乎苛刻的要求反而是让人感觉相当奇怪的（不过，先正确，再效率）。这一点其实可以另外写一篇文章讨论。</p><h2 id="4-2-框架分析与设计实现"><a href="#4-2-框架分析与设计实现" class="headerlink" title="4.2 框架分析与设计实现"></a>4.2 框架分析与设计实现</h2><p>本 Lab 只需要动<code>/src/Simulator</code>即可。</p><p>我们先总览 Simulator，其本质上就是实现了 CPU 的五级流水，将他们实现为具体的五个函数，fetch，decode，excute，memoryAccess，和 writeBack，简明易懂。</p><p>我们不妨先将 LR&#x2F;SC 指令的解码和信息传递完成。</p><figure class="highlight lasso"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br><span class="line">11</span><br><span class="line">12</span><br><span class="line">13</span><br><span class="line">14</span><br><span class="line">15</span><br><span class="line">16</span><br><span class="line">17</span><br><span class="line">18</span><br><span class="line">19</span><br><span class="line">20</span><br><span class="line">21</span><br><span class="line">22</span><br><span class="line">23</span><br><span class="line">24</span><br><span class="line">25</span><br><span class="line">26</span><br><span class="line">27</span><br><span class="line">28</span><br><span class="line">29</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs lasso"><span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span><br>namespace RISCV<br>&#123;<br>    <span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span><br>    enum Inst<br>    &#123;<br>        <span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span><br>        LRW = <span class="hljs-number">54</span>,   <span class="hljs-comment">/* add encode lr.w instruction as 54 */</span><br>        LRD = <span class="hljs-number">55</span>,   <span class="hljs-comment">/* add encode lr.d instruction as 55 */</span><br>        SCW = <span class="hljs-number">56</span>,   <span class="hljs-comment">/* add encode sc.w instruction as 56 */</span><br>        SCD = <span class="hljs-number">57</span>,   <span class="hljs-comment">/* add encode sc.d instruction as 57 */</span><br>        <span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span><br>    &#125;;<br>    <span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span><br>    <span class="hljs-comment">/* add LR SC instruction with opcode 0X2F */</span><br>    const int OP_CAS = <span class="hljs-number">0x2F</span>;<br>    <span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span><br>    <span class="hljs-keyword">inline</span> bool isReadMem(Inst inst)<br>    &#123;<br>        <span class="hljs-comment">/* As LR and SC both need memory access and write back to</span><br><span class="hljs-comment">        reg, so we need to handle with harzard in pipline */</span><br>        <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span> (<span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span> || inst == LRW || inst == LRD<br>            || inst == SCW || inst == SCD)<br>        &#123;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>        &#125;<br>        <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> <span class="hljs-literal">false</span>;<br>    &#125;<br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>我们首先在头文件 Inst 数据结构中加上四个 LR&#x2F;SC 指令的代号数字，然后将其列入内存操作指令中。</p><figure class="highlight d"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br><span class="line">11</span><br><span class="line">12</span><br><span class="line">13</span><br><span class="line">14</span><br><span class="line">15</span><br><span class="line">16</span><br><span class="line">17</span><br><span class="line">18</span><br><span class="line">19</span><br><span class="line">20</span><br><span class="line">21</span><br><span class="line">22</span><br><span class="line">23</span><br><span class="line">24</span><br><span class="line">25</span><br><span class="line">26</span><br><span class="line">27</span><br><span class="line">28</span><br><span class="line">29</span><br><span class="line">30</span><br><span class="line">31</span><br><span class="line">32</span><br><span class="line">33</span><br><span class="line">34</span><br><span class="line">35</span><br><span class="line">36</span><br><span class="line">37</span><br><span class="line">38</span><br><span class="line">39</span><br><span class="line">40</span><br><span class="line">41</span><br><span class="line">42</span><br><span class="line">43</span><br><span class="line">44</span><br><span class="line">45</span><br><span class="line">46</span><br><span class="line">47</span><br><span class="line">48</span><br><span class="line">49</span><br><span class="line">50</span><br><span class="line">51</span><br><span class="line">52</span><br><span class="line">53</span><br><span class="line">54</span><br><span class="line">55</span><br><span class="line">56</span><br><span class="line">57</span><br><span class="line">58</span><br><span class="line">59</span><br><span class="line">60</span><br><span class="line">61</span><br><span class="line">62</span><br><span class="line">63</span><br><span class="line">64</span><br><span class="line">65</span><br><span class="line">66</span><br><span class="line">67</span><br><span class="line">68</span><br><span class="line">69</span><br><span class="line">70</span><br><span class="line">71</span><br><span class="line">72</span><br><span class="line">73</span><br><span class="line">74</span><br><span class="line">75</span><br><span class="line">76</span><br><span class="line">77</span><br><span class="line">78</span><br><span class="line">79</span><br><span class="line">80</span><br><span class="line">81</span><br><span class="line">82</span><br><span class="line">83</span><br><span class="line">84</span><br><span class="line">85</span><br><span class="line">86</span><br><span class="line">87</span><br><span class="line">88</span><br><span class="line">89</span><br><span class="line">90</span><br><span class="line">91</span><br><span class="line">92</span><br><span class="line">93</span><br><span class="line">94</span><br><span class="line">95</span><br><span class="line">96</span><br><span class="line">97</span><br><span class="line">98</span><br><span class="line">99</span><br><span class="line">100</span><br><span class="line">101</span><br><span class="line">102</span><br><span class="line">103</span><br><span class="line">104</span><br><span class="line">105</span><br><span class="line">106</span><br><span class="line">107</span><br><span class="line">108</span><br><span class="line">109</span><br><span class="line">110</span><br><span class="line">111</span><br><span class="line">112</span><br><span class="line">113</span><br><span class="line">114</span><br><span class="line">115</span><br><span class="line">116</span><br><span class="line">117</span><br><span class="line">118</span><br><span class="line">119</span><br><span class="line">120</span><br><span class="line">121</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs d">......<br>namespace RISCV<br>&#123;<br>    ......<br>    <span class="hljs-keyword">const</span> <span class="hljs-built_in">char</span> *INSTNAME[]&#123; <span class="hljs-comment">/* add instruction name */</span><br>        ......,<span class="hljs-string">&quot;lrw&quot;</span>,<span class="hljs-string">&quot;lrd&quot;</span>,<span class="hljs-string">&quot;scw&quot;</span>,<span class="hljs-string">&quot;scd&quot;</span>&#125;;<br>&#125;<br>......<br><span class="hljs-keyword">void</span> Simulator::decode()<br>&#123;<br>    ......<br>    <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span> (<span class="hljs-keyword">this</span>-&gt;fReg.len == <span class="hljs-number">4</span>) <span class="hljs-comment">// 32 bit instruction</span><br>    &#123;<br>        ......<br>        <span class="hljs-keyword">switch</span> (opcode)<br>        &#123;<br>            ......<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">case</span> OP_CAS: <span class="hljs-comment">/* add OP_CAS handler */</span><br>            &#123;<br>                <span class="hljs-comment">/* read data in reg[rs1] which store the address */</span><br>                op1 = <span class="hljs-keyword">this</span>-&gt;reg[rs1];<br>                <span class="hljs-comment">/* read data in reg[rs2] which is no mean in LR,</span><br><span class="hljs-comment">                    store the old_value in SC */</span><br>                op2 = <span class="hljs-keyword">this</span>-&gt;reg[rs2];<br>                reg1 = rs1;<br>                reg2 = rs2;<br>                dest = rd;  <span class="hljs-comment">/* The reg which should be write back */</span><br><br>                <span class="hljs-comment">/* Get the funct5 */</span><br>                uint32_t  temp = (inst &gt;&gt; <span class="hljs-number">27</span>) &amp; <span class="hljs-number">0</span>x1F;<br>                <span class="hljs-keyword">switch</span> (temp)<br>                &#123;<br>                <span class="hljs-keyword">case</span> <span class="hljs-number">0</span>x2:   <span class="hljs-comment">/* LR instruction */</span><br>                    <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span> (funct3 == <span class="hljs-number">3</span>)    <span class="hljs-comment">/* LR.D instruction */</span><br>                    &#123;<br>                        instname = <span class="hljs-string">&quot;lrd&quot;</span>;<br>                        insttype = LRD;<br>                    &#125;<br>                    <span class="hljs-keyword">else</span> <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span> (funct3 == <span class="hljs-number">2</span>)   <span class="hljs-comment">/* LR.W instruction */</span><br>                    &#123;<br>                        instname = <span class="hljs-string">&quot;lrw&quot;</span>;<br>                        instyype = LRW;<br>                    &#125;<br>                    <span class="hljs-keyword">else</span><br>                    &#123;<br>                        <span class="hljs-keyword">this</span>-&gt;panic(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;Unknown 32bit funct3 0x%x\n&quot;</span>, funct3);<br>                    &#125;<br>                    <span class="hljs-keyword">break</span>;<br>                <span class="hljs-keyword">case</span> <span class="hljs-number">0</span>x3:   <span class="hljs-comment">/* SC instruction */</span><br>                    <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span> (funct3 == <span class="hljs-number">3</span>)    <span class="hljs-comment">/* SC.D instruction */</span><br>                    &#123;<br>                        instname = <span class="hljs-string">&quot;scd&quot;</span>;<br>                        insttype = SCD;<br>                    &#125;<br>                    <span class="hljs-keyword">else</span> <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span> (funct3 == <span class="hljs-number">2</span>)   <span class="hljs-comment">/* SC.W instruction */</span><br>                    &#123;<br>                        instname = <span class="hljs-string">&quot;scw&quot;</span>;<br>                        instyype = SCW;<br>                    &#125;<br>                    <span class="hljs-keyword">else</span><br>                    &#123;<br>                        <span class="hljs-keyword">this</span>-&gt;panic(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;Unknown 32bit funct3 0x%x\n&quot;</span>, funct3);<br>                    &#125;<br>                    <span class="hljs-keyword">break</span>;<br>                <span class="hljs-keyword">default</span>:<br>                    <span class="hljs-keyword">this</span>-&gt;panic(<span class="hljs-string">&quot;Unknown 32bit funct5</span><br><span class="hljs-string">                        0x%x\n&quot;</span>, temp);<br>                &#125;<br>            &#125;<br>            ......<br>        &#125;<br>    &#125;<br>    ......<br>&#125;<br><br><span class="hljs-keyword">void</span> Simulator::excecute()<br>&#123;<br>    ......<br>    <span class="hljs-built_in">bool</span> _cas = <span class="hljs-literal">false</span>;  <span class="hljs-comment">/* To identify whether it is a LR or SC */</span><br><br>    <span class="hljs-keyword">switch</span> (inst)<br>    &#123;<br>        ......<br>        <span class="hljs-keyword">case</span> LRW:   <span class="hljs-comment">/* Datapath of LR.W instruction */</span><br>            readMem = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            writeReg = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            memLen = <span class="hljs-number">4</span>;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">out</span> = op1;<br>            readSignExt = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            _cas = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">break</span>;<br>        <span class="hljs-keyword">case</span> LRD:   <span class="hljs-comment">/* Datapath of LR.D instruction */</span><br>            readMem = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            writeReg = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            memLen = <span class="hljs-number">8</span>;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">out</span> = op1;<br>            readSignExt = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            _cas = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">break</span>;<br>        <span class="hljs-keyword">case</span> SCW:   <span class="hljs-comment">/* Datapath of SC.W instruction */</span><br>            writeReg = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            writeMem = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            memLen = <span class="hljs-number">4</span>;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">out</span> = op1;<br>            _cas = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            op2 = op2 &amp; <span class="hljs-number">0</span>xFFFFFFFF;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">break</span>;<br>        <span class="hljs-keyword">case</span> SCD:   <span class="hljs-comment">/* Datapath of SC.D instruction */</span><br>            writeReg = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            writeMem = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            memLen = <span class="hljs-number">8</span>;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">out</span> = op1;<br>            op2 = op2 &amp; <span class="hljs-number">0</span>xFFFFFFFF;<br>            _cas = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">break</span>;<br>        ......<br>    &#125;<br>    ......<br>    <span class="hljs-comment">/* Pass the information to the next stage */</span><br>    <span class="hljs-keyword">this</span>-&gt;eRegNew._cas = _cas;<br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>这都是一些非常“顺其自然”的照猫画虎，接下去我们需要考虑一个合适的数据结构，并且将原子性质在 memoryAccess 中实现。我们之前讨论了（2019）V1 版本的 CAS 指令要求，我选择了直接在 Simulator 类中声明私有变量，存储注册保留的地址，注册保留的字节数，以及注册保留的 valid bit。</p><figure class="highlight lasso"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br><span class="line">11</span><br><span class="line">12</span><br><span class="line">13</span><br><span class="line">14</span><br><span class="line">15</span><br><span class="line">16</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs lasso">class Simulator<br>&#123;<br><span class="hljs-keyword">public</span>:<br>    <span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span><br><span class="hljs-keyword">private</span>:<br>    <span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span><br>    struct EReg<br>    &#123;<br>        <span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span><br>        bool _cas;<br>    &#125; eReg, eRegNew;<br>    <span class="hljs-params">...</span><span class="hljs-params">...</span><br>    uint32_t registry_addr; <span class="hljs-comment">/* Registry hold the first address */</span><br>    uint32_t registry_num;  <span class="hljs-comment">/* Registry hold the number */</span><br>    bool registry_whe;      <span class="hljs-comment">/* Registry hold the valid bit */</span><br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>那么如何利用这些数据结构实现 CAS 也变得显而易见。</p><p>对于 SC 指令，我们注意到，任何涉及注册保留地址的存储行为都会使注册保留失效，所以我简单粗暴的在原先的 store 行为上加了一层地址判断。然后，针对 SC 指令，进行特殊的逻辑判断，查找对应地址是否注册保留，如果注册保留有效，那么向内存写入地址，返回 0x0；如果注册保留失败，那么直接返回非 0 值。注意，无论是否是 SC 指令，任何存储行为都会使目标地址的注册保留失效。</p><p>对于 LR 指令，我们直接更新数据结构即可，设置目标地址的注册保留有效，从内存中读出数据，并且记录其字节数。正常的读内存指令不需要进行其他操作。我们可以注意到，因为 LR 实时维护了数据结构，所以只会保留最近的 LR 指令，满足了我们之前的讨论要求。</p><figure class="highlight xl"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br><span class="line">11</span><br><span class="line">12</span><br><span class="line">13</span><br><span class="line">14</span><br><span class="line">15</span><br><span class="line">16</span><br><span class="line">17</span><br><span class="line">18</span><br><span class="line">19</span><br><span class="line">20</span><br><span class="line">21</span><br><span class="line">22</span><br><span class="line">23</span><br><span class="line">24</span><br><span class="line">25</span><br><span class="line">26</span><br><span class="line">27</span><br><span class="line">28</span><br><span class="line">29</span><br><span class="line">30</span><br><span class="line">31</span><br><span class="line">32</span><br><span class="line">33</span><br><span class="line">34</span><br><span class="line">35</span><br><span class="line">36</span><br><span class="line">37</span><br><span class="line">38</span><br><span class="line">39</span><br><span class="line">40</span><br><span class="line">41</span><br><span class="line">42</span><br><span class="line">43</span><br><span class="line">44</span><br><span class="line">45</span><br><span class="line">46</span><br><span class="line">47</span><br><span class="line">48</span><br><span class="line">49</span><br><span class="line">50</span><br><span class="line">51</span><br><span class="line">52</span><br><span class="line">53</span><br><span class="line">54</span><br><span class="line">55</span><br><span class="line">56</span><br><span class="line">57</span><br><span class="line">58</span><br><span class="line">59</span><br><span class="line">60</span><br><span class="line">61</span><br><span class="line">62</span><br><span class="line">63</span><br><span class="line">64</span><br><span class="line">65</span><br><span class="line">66</span><br><span class="line">67</span><br><span class="line">68</span><br><span class="line">69</span><br><span class="line">70</span><br><span class="line">71</span><br><span class="line">72</span><br><span class="line">73</span><br><span class="line">74</span><br><span class="line">75</span><br><span class="line">76</span><br><span class="line">77</span><br><span class="line">78</span><br><span class="line">79</span><br><span class="line">80</span><br><span class="line">81</span><br><span class="line">82</span><br><span class="line">83</span><br><span class="line">84</span><br><span class="line">85</span><br><span class="line">86</span><br><span class="line">87</span><br><span class="line">88</span><br><span class="line">89</span><br><span class="line">90</span><br><span class="line">91</span><br><span class="line">92</span><br><span class="line">93</span><br><span class="line">94</span><br><span class="line">95</span><br><span class="line">96</span><br><span class="line">97</span><br><span class="line">98</span><br><span class="line">99</span><br><span class="line">100</span><br><span class="line">101</span><br><span class="line">102</span><br><span class="line">103</span><br><span class="line">104</span><br><span class="line">105</span><br><span class="line">106</span><br><span class="line">107</span><br><span class="line">108</span><br><span class="line">109</span><br><span class="line">110</span><br><span class="line">111</span><br><span class="line">112</span><br><span class="line">113</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs xl">void Simulator::memoryAccess()<br>&#123;<br>    ......<br>    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">bool</span> _cas = this-&gt;</span>eReg._cas;<br>    ......<br>    <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span> (writeMem)<br>    &#123;<br>        switch (memLen)<br>        &#123;<br>        case <span class="hljs-number">1</span>:<br>            <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">good</span> = this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">memory</span>-&gt;</span>setByte(out, op2, &amp;cycles);<br>            <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">if</span> ((out &gt;= this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_addr</span>) &amp;&amp; (out &lt;= (this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_addr</span> + this-&gt;</span>registry_num)))<br>            &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* If there is any byte write to the reservation set */</span><br>                <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_whe = <span class="hljs-literal">false</span>;<br>            &#125;<br>            break;<br>        case <span class="hljs-number">2</span>:<br>            <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">good</span> = this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">memory</span>-&gt;</span>setShort(out, op2, &amp;cycles);<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">for</span> (uint32_t i = <span class="hljs-number">0</span>; i &lt; <span class="hljs-number">2</span>; i++)<br>            &#123;<br>                <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">if</span> (((out + i) &gt;= this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_addr</span>) &amp;&amp; ((out + i) &lt;= (this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_addr</span> + this-&gt;</span>registry_num)))<br>                &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* Any byte write to the reservation set */</span><br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_whe = <span class="hljs-literal">false</span>;<br>                &#125;<br>            &#125;<br>            break;<br>        case <span class="hljs-number">4</span>:<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span> (_cas)<br>            &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* If this is SC instruction */</span><br>                <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">if</span> (this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_whe</span> &amp;&amp; (this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_addr</span> == out) &amp;&amp; (this-&gt;</span>registry_num == <span class="hljs-number">4</span>))<br>                &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* Reservation set is valid the first address same the access length same */</span><br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">good</span> = this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">memory</span>-&gt;</span>setInt(out, op2, &amp;cycles);<br>                    out = <span class="hljs-number">0</span>;<br>                &#125;<br>                <span class="hljs-keyword">else</span><br>                &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* If failed return code 1 */</span><br>                    out = <span class="hljs-number">1</span>;<br>                &#125;<br>                <span class="hljs-comment">/* SC eliminate all reservation */</span><br>                <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_whe = <span class="hljs-literal">false</span>;<br>            &#125;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">else</span><br>            &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* If not, do basic store operation */</span><br>                <span class="hljs-keyword">for</span> (uint32_t i = <span class="hljs-number">0</span>; i &lt; <span class="hljs-number">4</span>; i++)<br>                &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* For all bytes */</span><br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">if</span> (((out + i) &gt;= this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_addr</span>) &amp;&amp; ((out + i) &lt;= (this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_addr</span> + this-&gt;</span>registry_num)))<br>                    &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* Any access to the bytes */</span><br>                        <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_whe = <span class="hljs-literal">false</span>;<br>                    &#125;<br>                &#125;<br>                <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">good</span> = this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">memory</span>-&gt;</span>setInt(out, op2, &amp;cycles);<br>            &#125;<br>            break;<br>        case <span class="hljs-number">8</span>:<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span> (_cas)<br>            &#123;<br>                <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">if</span> (this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_whe</span> &amp;&amp; (this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_addr</span> == out) &amp;&amp; (this-&gt;</span>registry_num == <span class="hljs-number">8</span>))<br>                &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* Reservation set is valid the first address same the access length same */</span><br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">good</span> = this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">memory</span>-&gt;</span>setLong(out, op2, &amp;cycles);<br>                    out = <span class="hljs-number">0</span>;<br>                &#125;<br>                <span class="hljs-keyword">else</span><br>                &#123;<br>                    out = <span class="hljs-number">1</span>;<br>                &#125;<br>                <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">tthis</span>-&gt;</span>registry_whe = <span class="hljs-literal">false</span>;<br>            &#125;<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">else</span><br>            &#123;<br>                <span class="hljs-keyword">for</span> (uint32_t i = <span class="hljs-number">0</span>; i &lt; <span class="hljs-number">8</span>; i++)<br>                &#123;<br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">if</span> (((out + i) &gt;= this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_addr</span>) &amp;&amp; ((out + i) &lt;= (this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">registry_addr</span> + this-&gt;</span>registry_num)))<br>                    &#123;<br>                        <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_whe = <span class="hljs-literal">false</span>;<br>                    &#125;<br>                &#125;<br>                <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">good</span> = this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">memory</span>-&gt;</span>setLong(out, op2, &amp;cycles);<br>            &#125;<br>        &#125;<br>    &#125;<br>    ......<br>    <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span> (readMem)<br>    &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* Handle with LR instruction */</span><br>        switch (memLen)<br>        &#123;<br>        ......<br>        case <span class="hljs-number">4</span>:<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span>(readSignExt)<br>            &#123;<br>                <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span>(_cas)<br>                &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* LR.W instruction */</span><br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_whe = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;  <span class="hljs-comment">/* Valid */</span><br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_addr = out;  <span class="hljs-comment">/* Store */</span><br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_num = <span class="hljs-number">4</span>; <span class="hljs-comment">/* Length */</span><br>                &#125;<br>                <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">out</span> = (int64_t)this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">memory</span>-&gt;</span>getInt(out, &amp;cycles);<br>            &#125;<br>            ......<br>        case <span class="hljs-number">8</span>:<br>            <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span>(readSignExt)<br>            &#123;<br>                <span class="hljs-keyword">if</span>(_cas)<br>                &#123;   <span class="hljs-comment">/* LR.W instruction */</span><br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_whe = <span class="hljs-literal">true</span>;<br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_addr = out;<br>                    <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">this</span>-&gt;</span>registry_num = <span class="hljs-number">8</span>;<br>                &#125;<br>                <span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">out</span> = (int64_t)this-&gt;</span><span class="hljs-function"><span class="hljs-title">memory</span>-&gt;</span>getInt(out, &amp;cycles);<br>            &#125;<br>            ......<br>        &#125;<br>    &#125;<br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>好的，到这里我们完成了 LR&#x2F;SC 这两个指令，接下去我们就是封装一下写一个 CAS 函数即可，在这里我们直接使用 C++的内联汇编</p><figure class="highlight wren"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br><span class="line">6</span><br><span class="line">7</span><br><span class="line">8</span><br><span class="line">9</span><br><span class="line">10</span><br><span class="line">11</span><br><span class="line">12</span><br><span class="line">13</span><br><span class="line">14</span><br><span class="line">15</span><br><span class="line">16</span><br><span class="line">17</span><br><span class="line">18</span><br><span class="line">19</span><br><span class="line">20</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="hljs wren">int <span class="hljs-title function_">CAS</span>(<span class="hljs-params">long</span> *<span class="hljs-params">dest</span>, <span class="hljs-params">long</span> <span class="hljs-params">new_value</span>, <span class="hljs-params">long</span> <span class="hljs-params">old_value</span>)<br>&#123;<br>    int <span class="hljs-variable">ret</span> <span class="hljs-operator">=</span> <span class="hljs-number">0</span>;<br><br>    <span class="hljs-comment">// <span class="hljs-doctag">TODO:</span> write your code here</span><br>    <span class="hljs-variable">__asm__</span> <span class="hljs-variable">__volatile__</span>(<br>        <span class="hljs-string">&quot;retry: lr.w  %0, %[output2]<span class="hljs-char escape_">\n</span>&quot;</span>             <span class="hljs-comment">/* Load value of addr */</span><br>        <span class="hljs-string">&quot;       bne   %0, %[input1], fail<span class="hljs-char escape_">\n</span>&quot;</span>        <span class="hljs-comment">/* Compare and check */</span><br>        <span class="hljs-string">&quot;       sc.w  %0, %[input2], %[output2]<span class="hljs-char escape_">\n</span>&quot;</span>  <span class="hljs-comment">/* Store new value */</span><br>        <span class="hljs-string">&quot;       bnez  %0, retry<span class="hljs-char escape_">\n</span>&quot;</span>                  <span class="hljs-comment">/* Whether atom operation succcess */</span><br>        <span class="hljs-string">&quot;       li    %[output1], 1<span class="hljs-char escape_">\n</span>&quot;</span>              <span class="hljs-comment">/* Return code 1 */</span><br>        <span class="hljs-string">&quot;       j     success<span class="hljs-char escape_">\n</span>&quot;</span>                    <span class="hljs-comment">/* Go on following */</span><br>        <span class="hljs-string">&quot;fail:  li    %[output1], 0<span class="hljs-char escape_">\n</span>&quot;</span>              <span class="hljs-comment">/* Return code 0 */</span><br>        <span class="hljs-string">&quot;success: <span class="hljs-char escape_">\n</span>&quot;</span><br>        : [<span class="hljs-variable">output1</span>] <span class="hljs-string">&quot;=&amp;r&quot;</span>(<span class="hljs-variable">ret</span>), [<span class="hljs-variable">output2</span>] <span class="hljs-string">&quot;+A&quot;</span>(<span class="hljs-operator">*</span><span class="hljs-variable">dest</span>)<br>        : [input1] <span class="hljs-string">&quot;rJ&quot;</span>(<span class="hljs-variable">old_value</span>), [input2] <span class="hljs-string">&quot;rJ&quot;</span>(<span class="hljs-variable">new_value</span>)<br>        : <span class="hljs-string">&quot;memory&quot;</span>);<br><br>    <span class="hljs-keyword">return</span> <span class="hljs-variable">ret</span>;<br>&#125;<br></code></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>代码中的注释已经十分详尽，我不再额外啰嗦。</p><h2 id="4-3-测试"><a href="#4-3-测试" class="headerlink" title="4.3 测试"></a>4.3 测试</h2><p>那么接下去测试即可，将 C++文件编译为 RISCV 汇编文件，注意这里使用<code>rv64ia</code>，因为 LR&#x2F;SC 指令是扩展指令。测试结果如下：<br><img src="/../img/riscv/result.png"><br>测试通过！</p><h2 id="4-4-思考（胡言乱语）"><a href="#4-4-思考（胡言乱语）" class="headerlink" title="4.4 思考（胡言乱语）"></a>4.4 思考（胡言乱语）</h2><p>严格来说官方提供的测试文件并不详尽，其也只检测了四字节 LR&#x2F;SC 指令的正确性，此外像多核情况，嵌套问题也被排除在此次 Lab 的考虑范围之外。或许我有空的时候会重新写一下两个指令，将这些问题考虑进去。（人生目标清单喜加一）</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Project</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>riscv</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  
</search>
