<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<search>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Hello World ?</title>
    <link href="/2023/07/03/hello-world/"/>
    <url>/2023/07/03/hello-world/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>欢迎来到我的博客!</p><p>因为在主页上挂着Hexo的Introduction着实是有些奇怪，所以先写一点文字，一是让博客里有一些电子垃圾，二是留一些以后可以怀念的文字。</p><p>当然我并不能确保特定的更新频率，而且维护博客大概也会上我的人生必做清单（这个清单上已经有如下事项：读完紫龙书，读完C++大部头，完成Sencondary Market Project的前后端分离），当然了，也很难想象会有人特地来赏光我的博客。所以，我对于这个博客的定义更倾向于是一点点的个人介绍，大量的生活经历分享和不知所云的灌水文字。</p><p>或许不久以后因为申请会陆续挂上个人简历和项目链接，不过相比全是paper的大佬博客，这儿不过是“存在主义”罢了，仅供commitee或者prof一笑。</p><p>好了，回归正题。</p><p>既然是作为可以怀念的文字，我先写写为何突发奇想创建自己的博客。我现位于UW-Madison，WISC，作为交换生在北美虚度光阴。上学期初寻找系统方向的Prof能够接纳我进组做一些项目<del>带带我水文章</del>，觉得需要创建一个个人网站来贴点CV和toy project。不曾想Prof Xiangyao Yu欣然接受我的申请，并且与我合作了一个项目<del>我觉得大概是CAII写的RISCV Simulator起了作用</del>，导致筹划到一半的个人网站不了了之。到了暑假，不堪项目的推进，托福和GRE，还有几个toy competition的压力，便乘机做个博客，写点不用debug多线程的文字，贴点四处晃荡的图片，以期在满屏error和low performance的大山下苟延残喘。</p><p>对于博客的内容，我想有一部分会是对过往岁月的“追忆”，我对此有充足的理由。首先，根据幸存者偏差的乱用，我们往往会注意到不如以前的事务，比如Madison的中餐让我开始可以接受博海一楼的自选菜。此外，随着心智和年龄的增长，我往往会对过往的人和物有更多的理解和思考，并且自责于当时的错误做法，遗憾于产生的bad ending，留下这些思考可以作为一面明镜，警醒我现在的所作所为，毕竟人往往会进入同一条河流。当然了，更多的其实还是像林海音之于《城南旧事》，曹雪芹之于《红楼梦》，对于自己曾经岁月的无限追忆，因为其美好，其蕴含的无限可能。</p><p>还有一部分会是一些技术的留档，<del>f**k you, CSDN</del>虽然我觉得其实如果自己真要用了使用chatgpt会更方便（GPT-4已经能帮我调多线程Bug了，我哭死）。考虑到之后回国可能的TGW问题，或是一些刁钻的环境问题，或是一些第三方库古怪的调用，我还是会不定期将一些技术整理成文档上传。</p><p>当然了，肯定还有一部分是关于美食，旅游等生活方面的分享，毕竟我已经没有了高中从医救济苍生的伟大理想，Just enjoy the fking world!之后8月中旬会飞往波士顿和旧金山，十分期待某人请客的龙虾。</p><p>最后，创建博客还基于一点点个人的想法，大刘说过“给岁月以文明，给时光以生命”，仅以此给这个宇宙和这片时间一点点来自Zhenghong Yu的痕迹。</p><p>Welcome to my blog!</p><p>Since it’s extraordinary to have Hexo’s Introduction on the homepage, I will write a little bit of text first to keep some e-waste in the blog and leave some text I can remember later.</p><p>Of course, I can’t ensure a specific update frequency, and maintaining the blog would probably be on my life’s must-do list (which already includes the following: finish reading the Purple Dragon book, finish reading the bulk of C++, and finish separating the front and back ends of the Secondary Market Project), and of course, it’s hard to imagine that anyone would specifically come to my blog. So, my definition of this blog is a personal introduction, more of life experience sharing and watered-down words.</p><p>Maybe I’ll put up a CV and links to my toy projects later for my application. Still, compared to a blog full of papers, this is just an “existentialist” blog, just for the committee or prof to have a laugh.</p><p>Okay, back to business.</p><p>Since this is meant to be a nostalgic text, I’ll start by writing about why I suddenly wanted to start my own blog. I am currently located at UW-Madison, WISC, and spend my time in North America as an exchange student. At the beginning of last semester, I was looking for a Prof in the Systems field to take me on as a member of his group to do some projects <del>bring me up to water papers</del> and thought I needed to create a personal website to post some CVs and toy projects. To my surprise, Prof Xiangyao Yu readily accepted my application and collaborated with me on a project<del>It was probably the RISCV Simulator by CAII that did the trick</del>. And caused the half-planned personal website to fall through. In the summer, I was overwhelmed by the project, the TOEFL and GRE, and the pressure of a few toy competitions, so I took the opportunity to make a blog, write some text without debugging multiple threads, and post some pictures that wander around, to survive under the mountain of errors and low performance.</p><p>I think part of the blog’s content will be a “reminiscence” of the past, and I have good reasons for this. By the indiscriminate use of survivorship bias, we tend to notice things that are not as good as they used to be, such as Madison’s Chinese food, which has made the self-chosen dishes on the ground floor of Bohai acceptable to me. In addition, as my mind and age grow, I tend to understand and think more about people and things from the past, blame myself for the mistakes I made at the time, and regret the bad endings that resulted. Leaving these reflections as a clear mirror to remind me of what I do now; after all, people tend to enter the same river. Of course, it is more like Lin Haiyin’s “Old Stories from the South of the City” or Cao Xueqin’s “Dream of the Red Chamber,” the endless remembrance of my former years of its beauty and the infinite possibilities.</p><p>There will also be a part of it that will be some technical documents, <del>f**k you, CSDN</del>. Though it would be more convenient to use chatgpt if I really had to use this (GPT-4 has been able to help me tune multi-threaded bugs, lmao). Considering the possible TGW problems, tricky environment problems, or weird calls to third-party libraries, I will occasionally upload some techniques.</p><p>Of course, I’m sure there will be some food, travel, and other aspects of life to share; after all, I no longer have the great ambition to be a doctor in high school; I just want to enjoy the fking world!</p><p>Finally, the blog is also based on a bit of personal thought; as Liu said, “Give years to civilization, give time to live,” so this is just a way to give this universe and, this time, a little trace from Zhenghong Yu.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Introduction</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
    <tags>
      
      <tag>introduction</tag>
      
    </tags>
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  
</search>
